<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>📻 GM5ALX Radio</title>
<link>https://gm5alx.uk/</link>
<atom:link href="https://gm5alx.uk/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>So many rabbit holes, you’ll struggle to find ground</description>
<generator>quarto-1.5.57</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 13:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Beinn a’Bhuird - North Top</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-004/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>After activating <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-006/">Ben Avon</a>, and a brief stop for some food, it was time to head back to The Sneck and then up to Beinn a’Bhuird.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhuird-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="A barren landscape"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-004/bhuird-3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A barren landscape"></a></p>
<figcaption>A barren landscape</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhuird-6.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="How is it still standing in this wind?"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-004/bhuird-6.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="How is it still standing in this wind?"></a></p>
<figcaption>How is it still standing in this wind?</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The frozen burns were interesting, some I could walk over, and some were only partially frozen. The small waterfalls would trap air underneath and then the bubbles would travel under the ice for a few meters before escaping.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhuird-7.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Frozen burns"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-004/bhuird-7.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Frozen burns"></a></p>
<figcaption>Frozen burns</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The summit was hard to find, my GPS route had come to an end but I couldn’t see anything. Some general blind amberling around eventually found it hidden in the cloud. I was a bit disappointed in the cairn, I was hoping I could at least hide in it, and even when crouched down behind it, the wind still got me.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhuird-8.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="At the summit!"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-004/bhuird-8.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="At the summit!"></a></p>
<figcaption>At the summit!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I then proceeded to spend ages messing about, trying to get setup on HF, but nothing would stay still. The wind pulled out guys and pegs, it bent the top of mast over 90° and so wires would come off, I angled the mast 35° off the ground into the wind, and the top still bent over enough for the wire to be pulled off. I held the mast with my body weight but still the wind could pick me up with only the surface area of the mast! Just when I had everything set for 40m it all blew down :sweat_smile: I thought I’d try 2m but that was just as challenging. I could hear the local lunch time net in Aberdeen but it was hard to get a word in edgeways and I’m not sure they could hear me anyway. So back to HF it was, this time with a short 5.5m vertical random wire for 20m. This I did manage to make some contacts with but, again, the wind blew me and the mast over mid-way through a QSO. By this time I was fed up, cold and wet, but had qualified the summit, so it was time to go! Also, there was no signal just behind the cairn…to add to the fun.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhuird-5.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="Which way was it?"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-004/bhuird-5.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Which way was it?"></a></p>
<figcaption>Which way was it?</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I generally took the same route back, without a compass, or device with a compass, it would be impossible to know which way to go. At one point on the way back it was so windy I could lean into the wind and it would hold me up! But I was soon back at The Sneck and heading down, and it wasn’t long before the conditions were more pleasant again. The weather wasn’t quite so nice down in the valley on the way back, but much nicer than on the summits. Found my bike, generally took the same route back, and was pleased to arrive back at the car to drive home.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhuird-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="Back down and out of the clouds"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-004/bhuird-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Back down and out of the clouds"></a></p>
<figcaption>Back down and out of the clouds</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>A big day out for me, 38 km or so round trip…and did I mention it was windy? 🍃</p>
<p>Also on the <a href="https://reflector.sota.org.uk/t/a-very-windy-ben-avon-gm-es-006-and-beinn-abhuird-gm-es-004/36517">SOTA reflector</a>.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-004/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 13:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-004/bhuird-7.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Ben Avon</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-006/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>After a lovely&nbsp;<a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-008/">Lochnagar trip</a> the other week (with the now amusing subtitle of windy munro), I was keen to do some more high summits before the weather got worse and the darkness set in. Although turns out the weather is already worse! It’s school holidays here, so with no family schedule constraints, I could go out for the whole day, and I decided to try these two big uns - Ben Avon and Beinn A’Bhuird, pronounced Ben Ann and Ben a Vour respectively.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="route.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Journey there and back"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-006/route.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Journey there and back"></a></p>
<figcaption>Journey there and back</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The route is pretty standard for these two, parking at Keiloch, paying the £3.50, then cycling, before hiking. I decided to bike as far as I could towards The Sneck (the T junction between the two summits at 986m), and just retrace my steps from Beinn a’Bhuird back. This is instead of doing the loop where you walk from Beinn a’Bhuird North Top (the full summit name) to South Top across the plateau, then down the side and meet the path again after crossing Quoich Water. As I could see the low cloud I thought I’d rather not be walking that route for the first time, and just retrace my steps. Although given my “retracing” aka wildly veering route, and the completely indistinguishable terrain, it probably didn’t matter. It also meant more cycling on the way in, which helped my timing, for a chance of a good summit to summit with Fraser, MM0EFI, on Mull.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ben-avon-5.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Into the Valley"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-006/ben-avon-5.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Into the Valley"></a></p>
<figcaption>Into the Valley</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The route in has a few parallel paths, including the Fairy Glen, and I’m not sure I took the best ones, and had to push the bike up some steep rocky parts in places. I tried the other way on the way back and it wasn’t much better, and then I missed the turn and went through the Fairy Glen - although didn’t see the secret howff (a hidden bothy), but also didn’t look very hard as I wanted to get back.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ben-avon-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Looking back along Gleann an t-slugain route"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-006/ben-avon-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Looking back along Gleann an t-slugain route"></a></p>
<figcaption>Looking back along Gleann an t-slugain route</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ben-avon-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Low route from fairy glen"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-006/ben-avon-3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Low route from fairy glen"></a></p>
<figcaption>Low route from fairy glen</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ben-avon-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="Some snow on Carn Faiclach"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-006/ben-avon-4.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Some snow on Carn Faiclach"></a></p>
<figcaption>Some snow on Carn Faiclach</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ben-avon-7.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="Path up to The Sneck"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-006/ben-avon-7.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Path up to The Sneck"></a></p>
<figcaption>Path up to The Sneck</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ben-avon-9.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7" title="Lots of waterfalls"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-006/ben-avon-9.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Lots of waterfalls"></a></p>
<figcaption>Lots of waterfalls</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The weather was reasonable in the morning, patches of sun between the clouds and fairly mild for 8am. The forecast had the summits in cloud with strong winds, 30-40 mph with gusts of 50 mph. However, until I got to The Sneck, there was minimal wind, but boy, once I did! 🌬️ It was absolutely relentless, with my hood acting like a reed in a trumpet with an enthusiastic player. I gave the edge a wide berth, not trusting myself if there was a sudden gust that I wasn’t braced for. Snow was minimal on the way to the Ben Avon summit, with just small pockets that resisted being blown away.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ben-avon-11.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-8" title="A bleak route to the summit"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-006/ben-avon-11.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A bleak route to the summit"></a></p>
<figcaption>A bleak route to the summit</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Out of the mist the tor emerges and I have arrived! Peaking through the rock formation - which acted like the mouth piece of the trumpet - revealed more snow on that side.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ben-avon-12.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-9" title="Snow on the east side of the tor"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-006/ben-avon-12.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Snow on the east side of the tor"></a></p>
<figcaption>Snow on the east side of the tor</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I found a nice rock to hide behind and setup the slim G on the carbon mast. My last activation on <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-030/">Carn a’Gheoidh</a>, suffered a lot from the mast bending too much in the wind and the antenna sliding off. Up until this point, I’d forgotten about this and so hadn’t prepared anything else. Luckily the slight sheltering seem to keep the antenna on and I managed to make my QSOs. The most exciting was a summit to summit with Fraser, MM0EFI, who’s on Mull and was up <a href="https://sotl.as/summits/GM/SI-016">GM/SI-016</a>, 100 miles away. We were both on HTs and slim G antenna!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="s2s.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-10" title="160km summit to summit on 2m FM"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-006/s2s.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="160km summit to summit on 2m FM"></a></p>
<figcaption>160km summit to summit on 2m FM</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Off to the next summit! The walk was barren, non-identifiable and had much more snow, oh, plus the wind continued.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ben-avon-14.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-11" title="Selfie at the top"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-006/ben-avon-14.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Selfie at the top"></a></p>
<figcaption>Selfie at the top</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-006/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 10:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-006/ben-avon-5.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Tap O’Noth</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-054/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="tap-o-noth-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Aurora the night before"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-054/tap-o-noth-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Aurora the night before"></a></p>
<figcaption>Aurora the night before</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>A pretty big sun CME hit and caused some lovely aurora all around the UK, however, this meant the bands were wrecked this morning. K of 7. Although dxheat was showing 40m activity in Europe this morning so I thought I’d try it. I had wanted to do some 20m to get a some nice EU contacts, as I thought that might be more interesting.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="tap-o-noth-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Off we go!"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-054/tap-o-noth-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Off we go!"></a></p>
<figcaption>Off we go!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>My mum is visiting and after all the sunny hillside photos I’ve been sending her, she wanted to come out and see the sights for herself. The weather wasn’t quite as spectacular as recent outings to <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-008/">Lochnagar</a> and <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-038/">An Socach</a>, but it was nice enough. After we dropped the kids at school, we headed up. There’s a dedicated car park, Tap O’Noth car park, and a nice track all the way to the top, so it was a straight forward walk. My mum did have a stroke about 11 years ago, and that does limit her at times. I’d hoped this summit wouldn’t be too much for her. When you arrive you’re greeted with this huge lump that sticks out of the ground and looks imposing, I thought I took a photo but it appears not.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="tap-o-noth-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Looking west to The Buck"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-054/tap-o-noth-4.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Looking west to The Buck"></a></p>
<figcaption>Looking west to <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-039/">The Buck</a></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>With a few stops on the way, we all made it to the top in good time. The cloud had come in a little and it was much windier but still decent weather. The top of this hill used to be a fort back in the Dark Ages, and so offers plenty of shelter from the wind.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="tap-o-noth-8.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Fort remains"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-054/tap-o-noth-8.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Fort remains"></a></p>
<figcaption>Fort remains</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I setup near the trig point in a nice recess in the side. I’d brought the G90 and my 5.5m vertical random wire. The G90 can match this tiny length of wire on any band, even 40m! Although probably longer wires would be better. I’d also brought my end fed half wave, but the 5.5m vertical is so fast to setup. As I was worried the novelty of watching me on the radio would wear off soon, and the cold wind would get to everyone, I stuck with this vertical. I gave 40m a shot, and did manage to just hear Phil, G4OBK. We were both 31 with each other. I then heard my HT as locals were chatting and asking if I’d already been and gone or what had happened. I’d emailed earlier in the day saying I was going up but had put 11am and we’d left later so it was closer to 11:30am.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="tap-o-noth-6.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="Braving the wind"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-054/tap-o-noth-6.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Braving the wind"></a></p>
<figcaption>Braving the wind</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I had the RH-770 on the HT and joined in the conversation, saying I was on the summit. Simon, GM4JXP, and Chris, 2M0RVZ, quickly called in and I was more than qualified. Simon was testing a new home made 5 el yagi and was absolutely deafening when he called! I tried one more CQ but I’d done the job so thought it was time I packed up and headed down - we didn’t want to be late for lunch! My mum liked the chats we all had on 2m, and said everyone sounded very friendly. If I had been on 20m or higher frequencies, it might’ve been exciting countries but nothing more than callsigns and RST exchanges.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="tap-o-noth-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="Admiring the view"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-054/tap-o-noth-3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Admiring the view"></a></p>
<figcaption>Admiring the view</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The trip down was easy enough, we actually met a few other walkers on their way up, and we were back in the car heading to Alford to try out a cafe for lunch. Soup and sandwiches all round with a sense of accomplishment by all. A very enjoyable trip out. Tap O’Noth will be a good one to do during the Winter bonus period (30 Nov-14 Mar) to get 5 points from it! The shelter the old fort offers is very nice for keeping out of the cold winds!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="tap-o-noth-7.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7" title="Success! 🌄"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-054/tap-o-noth-7.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Success! 🌄"></a></p>
<figcaption>Success! 🌄</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-054/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-054/drone.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Getting started with Bunkers on the Air</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/bunkers-on-the-air/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>I’ve heard about it before but only just looked into bunkers on the air (or UK BOTA). Turns out there are a lot of sites around and good way to get out and about, use the radio, explore your local region and maybe learn a little bit of history.</p>
<p>Here’s a list of useful sites to get you going:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://bunkersontheair.org/site/">Main site</a></li>
<li><a href="https://bunkerbase.org/">Database</a></li>
<li><a href="https://bunkerbase.org/bunker-3/">Maps</a>
<ul>
<li>The Google Map didn’t appear for me, but the OS map is nice, or use the combined on below:</li>
</ul></li>
<li><a href="https://kwirk.github.io/pota-gb-map/">Combined awards map</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The main rules are:</p>
<ul>
<li>Be within 1000 m of the bunker location (with the right permissions etc.)</li>
<li>Qualify the bunker with 25 HF contacts or 10 VHF+ contacts</li>
</ul>
<p>I’d recommend joining the WhatsApp group listed on the website, and you’ll get invited to the spotting group too.</p>
<p>I was surprised by the number of bunkers locally to me, especailly compared to doing SOTA activations and having to drive at least an hour to get anywhere!</p>
<p>I’ve not activated one yet but there appear to be plenty that have never been done near me.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>BOTA</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/bunkers-on-the-air/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 06 Oct 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/bunkers-on-the-air/UKBOTA.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="81" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Carn a’Gheoidh</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-030/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>After a lovely day yesterday on Lochnagar and Conachcraig, I was looking to see where I could go today. There was a swimming competition on, in addition to the usual activities, so I needed to be back for 3pm. Last week when I was on <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-038/">An Socach</a>, the others went to Carn a’Gheoidh, and I remembered them leaving later than me but arriving at the top at the same time. Sure enough when I check all the times, it looked doable to get there and back in time. The longest part is the drive to Glenshee ski centre, and that’s right at the limit of the electric car - returning home with 20 miles range still makes me a little nervous!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="carnagheoidh-14.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="A grey day"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-030/carnagheoidh-14.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A grey day"></a></p>
<figcaption>A grey day</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The weather forecast had it cloudy with chance of showers and reasonably breezy. It did rain a little on the way out but was dry when I arrived. I wasted about 10 minutes getting a parking ticket from the cafe - I should’ve just opened the link in the car park when I was up the hill and had signal, like I did with Glas Maol.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="carnagheoidh-11.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Look, snow!"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-030/carnagheoidh-11.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Look, snow!"></a></p>
<figcaption>Look, snow!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The track follows up the ski maintenance tracks, which are quite steep to start. There’s a shortcut across part way up which I just walked right past. My Inreach mini started beeping as I’d gone of course and so I backtracked and found it. It was a small track at right angles to the main path just behind a fence, so not too obvious, so thanks to the Garmin!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="carnagheoidh-8.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Navigation via Inreach Mini"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-030/carnagheoidh-8.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Navigation via Inreach Mini"></a></p>
<figcaption>Navigation via Inreach Mini</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I was soon in the cloud and did check on the inreach every so often to make sure I was heading in the right direction. I doesn’t have topo maps, and just a line but it has a compass and so points in the right direction and is enough to make sure you’re following the right path.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="carnagheoidh-7.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Cloudy"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-030/carnagheoidh-7.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Cloudy"></a></p>
<figcaption>Cloudy</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I didn’t see much on the way up, other than about 20m around me, mostly looking like the photo. In exposed places the wind picked up a lot and gave me a good push. At one point I was about 3m from a small loch and I didn’t realise until I was right upon it. The track was decent and only in a few places was it boggy but nothing like The Buck. The final ascent to the summit is steep again after a while of walking on the mostly flat plateau. At this point the wind was howling and I was glad there was a cairn at the top.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="carnagheoidh-6.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="Made it!"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-030/carnagheoidh-6.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Made it!"></a></p>
<figcaption>Made it!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I setup behind the cairn, which was a very good shelter from the wind, had a sandwich and then got on the air. I thought I’d try a bit more power on 2m and see if I could get any further than usual. I’d brought the Kenwood V71 and battery. This is the first time I’ve taken it out with me, and I also haven’t used it much at home, so I was hoping I wouldn’t get into any operating issues with it! I had the slim G, and was glad I hadn’t brought the yagi to try and setup in the wind.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="carnagheoidh-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="Wind battered carbon mast"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-030/carnagheoidh-4.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Wind battered carbon mast"></a></p>
<figcaption>Wind battered carbon mast</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="V71.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7" title="Kenwood V71, trying to keep dry"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-030/V71.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Kenwood V71, trying to keep dry"></a></p>
<figcaption>Kenwood V71, trying to keep dry</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I now wonder if I’d setup the mast on the outside of the cairn pointing into the wind, if I could’ve made it more vertical. Particularly as right at the end the antenna got blown off and I ended up holding it with my arm to finish the QSO - I didn’t do an EMF assessment on that setup…</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="qsos.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-8" title="QSOs"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-030/qsos.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="QSOs"></a></p>
<figcaption>QSOs</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>It was a little slow to start, but eventually I’d work 9 stations, including GM4OAS 90 miles to the west in Mallaig. I did find the lowest squelch on the V71 was quite high and not breaking for several stations. I eventually turned it off and then heard several locals and others. I do wonder how many had been replying to my CQs before. Did 50W make any difference? The map looks remarkably similar to when I was on <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-012/">Glas Maol</a>, and that was with the 5W D72 handheld. Technically, it’s 10 dB which is 1.x S points, and on Glas Maol GM4OAS gave me 32 and this time he gave me 42, so whilst not more power, I was readable more? I do like the form factor of using the mobile rig with the fist mic, means I can position things easier than being tied directly to the end of the mast, but probably for the most part it makes no real difference and it’s all in my head!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="carnagheoidh-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-9" title="Cloud clearing…for a moment"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-030/carnagheoidh-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Cloud clearing…for a moment"></a></p>
<figcaption>Cloud clearing…for a moment</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Keeping an eye on the time, I needed to pack up and head back. The wind was still relentless and on the top I had to lean into it. I was grateful of my big hood as I followed the path back down. It’s amazing how you can forget some of the details of the walk on the way back, being surprised that I had to climb up and down a few places which I didn’t remember on the way up to the summit! For a few moments the wind seemed to blow the clouds away and there was even a hint of sunshine coming through. The view opened up and I could see all around. Certainly not the spectacular views of <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-038/">last week</a>, but enjoyable for the few moments. Back down to the car and back home.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="carnagheoidh-13.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-10" title="Lift to the clouds"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-030/carnagheoidh-13.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Lift to the clouds"></a></p>
<figcaption>Lift to the clouds</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I think this summit and Glas Maol would make a nice day trip out, one in the morning and one in the afternoon, with the option of a hot lunch at the ski centre cafe. For 6 and 8 pointers, they have fairly easy and short walks, and both great locations for 2m, particularly to the south. Doing both would be 14 points, and a lot less walking and climbing than my 14 point day yesterday on <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-008/">Lochnagar</a> and <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-019/">Conachcraig</a>!</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-030/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-030/carnagheoidh-6.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Lochnagar - Cac Carn Beag</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-008/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>I’ve been eyeing Lochnagar <a href="https://summits.sota.org.uk/summit/GM/ES-008">GM/ES-008</a> for a while, and this Thursday’s forecast was looking reasonable, so decided to take the day off. It’s little neighbour, Conachcraig <a href="https://summits.sota.org.uk/summit/GM/ES-019">GM/ES-019</a>, is asking to be activated at the same time. I was going to take the common route starting at Glenmuick, but Fraser, MM0EFI, suggested biking from Balmoral castle.</p>
<p>As I was trying to fit this into the family schedule, any time I could save would be an advantage. I used <a href="https://www.plotaroute.com/">plotaroute</a> to figure out the times for the biking and hiking sections, matching the speed I think I move at, plus the drive back and forth, it looked like the cycle route would be the quickest. 8:05 hrs for the cycle route vs.&nbsp;8:40 for the walk from Glenmuick (times include driving). I considered cycling from Glenmuick but supposedly the path isn’t great beyond the forest, so not really worth it.</p>
<p>Was only a few degrees at the start in Crathie car park, but cycling generally uphill and in the sun I was soon roasting! It was around 1:15 cycle up to the intersection of Lochnagar and Conachcraig and I’d had enough of the bike! Much of the route is a gentle incline but there are areas where it’s steeper and much less enjoyable.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="lochnagar-19.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Summit in sight"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-008/lochnagar-19.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Summit in sight"></a></p>
<figcaption>Summit in sight</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I met a nice German couple on the way up Lochnagar. They’d been in Scotland for nearly 3 weeks and had brillant weather all round. Climbed Ben Nevis, Ben Lomond and visited several cities and towns.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“Of course the weather is always like this”.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>A german ham I know told me: “Nice German” is as redundant as “false error” or “undead zombie”. His choice of words. Enough chit-chat, I had a schedule to keep and kept going.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="lochnagar-15.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Boulders!"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-008/lochnagar-15.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Boulders!"></a></p>
<figcaption>Boulders!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I’ve not been on a popular summit for a while and was surprised to see so many people on a random Thursday. I say so many people, it probably it was about 15, but compared to zero to two, it seemed a lot.</p>
<p>The forecast had said cloudy in the afternoon and I was due on the summit at 1300 local so I was hoping it would stay clear. I wasn’t disappointed.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="lochnagar-14.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Lochnagar"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-008/lochnagar-14.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Lochnagar"></a></p>
<figcaption>Lochnagar</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="lochnagar-13.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Up to the summit"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-008/lochnagar-13.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Up to the summit"></a></p>
<figcaption>Up to the summit</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I waited my turn in the queue to take photos at the summit, offering to take those of others. The wind was strong at this point and you wanted to be sure of your footing whilst scrambling about on the top. The views were incredible in all directions, and anyone on a summit in GM/ES would’ve had a great day.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="lochnagar-8.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="At the top!"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-008/lochnagar-8.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="At the top!"></a></p>
<figcaption>At the top!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="lochnagar-12.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="Looking NW into the hills"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-008/lochnagar-12.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Looking NW into the hills"></a></p>
<figcaption>Looking NW into the hills</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I’d made it to the top ahead of schedule but I spent a long time admiring the views and walking around. The wind was strong so I looked for somewhere sheltered and away from the main path to setup, but ended up just sitting on the grass to one side. With my back to the wind it wasn’t too bad. I setup the slim G on the 6m mast and used my HT to call CQ. I was hoping to qualify the summit on 2m and in short order to keep on my way. I also noticed the clouds rolling in from the south. Got 5 in the log, mostly the locals plus Jace MM7VXJ who called when I was eating a biscuit. Credit to Jace for trying to relay messages to Jack, GM4COX, who was a 59 for me but think I was a 01 for him, and he wanted to move to sideband. I was surprised not to get anyone else further south.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="lochnagar-10.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7" title="Summit instructions from 1924"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-008/lochnagar-10.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Summit instructions from 1924"></a></p>
<figcaption>Summit instructions from 1924</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Time to head back. I should’ve taken a photo of Conachcraig from the summit, as it looked tiny from atop Lochnagar! All around the cliff edges are openings that just drop away, and on a lovely sunny day they’re interesting to look at but if it were cloudy these are a literal death trap!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="lochnagar-7.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-8" title="A straight down"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-008/lochnagar-7.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A straight down"></a></p>
<figcaption>A straight down</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Back down, passed my bike, and then up to the next <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-019/">summit</a>.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="lochnagar-6.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-9" title="Conachcraig"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-008/lochnagar-6.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Conachcraig"></a></p>
<figcaption>Conachcraig</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-008/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-008/lochnagar-5.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Conachcraig</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-019/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>After the <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-008/">big hill</a>, it was time to do the small one - <a href="https://sotl.as/summits/GM/ES-019">Conachcraig</a>. It certainly looked small from Lochnagar summit but it’s still a respectable 865m tall.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="lochnagar-6.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Looking down on Conachcraig from Lochnagar"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-019/lochnagar-6.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Looking down on Conachcraig from Lochnagar"></a></p>
<figcaption>Looking down on Conachcraig from Lochnagar</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>It felt like a short, straight up route on a nice track. I turned and looked back at Lochnagar and could see the cloud hovering over the summit, although not submerging it.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="lochnagar-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Clouds looming on Lochnagar"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-019/lochnagar-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Clouds looming on Lochnagar"></a></p>
<figcaption>Clouds looming on Lochnagar</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The rock formations on Conachcraig are interesting to look at, I haven’t really got a good photo of them so you’ll have to go there yourself. Unsurprisingly, no-one else was at this summit with me and I ducked down behind a rock to keep out the wind whilst I setup again on 2m.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="lochnagar-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Station location"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-019/lochnagar-3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Station location"></a></p>
<figcaption>Station location</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Thanks again to Fraser, MM0EFI, and Chris, 2M0RVZ for their contacts on both summits, then with Simon, GM4JXP, and finally Richie, GM1LKD, in Aberdeen I was set. It was now 3:05pm, and I needed to be home by 5pm, and with an hour+ drive, it was time to pack up and head back to my bike.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="lochnagar-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Back on the bike, and bye bye Lochnagar!"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-019/lochnagar-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Back on the bike, and bye bye Lochnagar!"></a></p>
<figcaption>Back on the bike, and bye bye Lochnagar!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The downhill bike ride back only took 20 minutes, and was a great way to end the trip. 28 km all in, and home in time!</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-019/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-019/lochnagar-6.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Waughton Hill</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-087/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>The <a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/906901577214402/?locale=en_GB">145 Alive!</a> event was planned for today between 1-3pm, which I wanted to join in with. Should be the perfect time to activate a summit on 2m! I had the three little kids with me for the day, so it had to be a easy summit. Particularly as I wanted to bring up the tent and lunch and things for them, to keep them entertained whilst I was on the air. The previous times I’ve brought them, I’ve only been about 20 minutes at most and trying to go much longer would be tricky. Eventually I want to qualify all the GM/ES summits, and so Waughton hill is on my list. It’s quite out of the way with nothing else nearby, so it’s a trip in itself and for one point, I’m not wasting a day off on it! It’s also the lowest summit in GM/ES, and seemed perfect for our adventure.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="Waughton1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="White Horse"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-087/Waughton1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="White Horse"></a></p>
<figcaption>White Horse</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The path up is short, although does cross a field full of cows, and you soon find yourself by the white horse. Walk by its head and you’re on the top of the rise, and heading towards the old hunter’s cottage. The actual summit is a bit further away, requiring you to go down and up the side of the hill again. However, the hunter’s cottage is in the activation zone and the kids thought we’d reached the top and started playing in the house. There was also a nice piece of grass without any sheep or animal droppings on it for the tent I’d brought. The tent and mast went up easily enough and lunch and various toys were unloaded into the tent. It was about 12:55 and I wanted to be on the air for the start of the event, so I swallowed down my rolls and setup the IC-705. Turns out the coax on the slim G with the 6m tactical mini mast is just a little too short for the radio to be on the ground. I usually don’t notice as either using the carbon 6, where the antenna sits a little lower on it, or a HT which I’m holding at standing height. So I ended up having to hold the 705 in my hand the whole time.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="Waughton2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Station setup"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-087/Waughton2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Station setup"></a></p>
<figcaption>Station setup</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I’ve not long had the IC-705 and whilst it is very simple to use, sometimes I get into some modes or settings that I don’t know how to get out of. Today I was already on 2m FM but would the VFO change the frequency? No.&nbsp;First I was worried I’d bashed it in my bag and the dial was broken, then thought perhaps I’d selected 10 or 100 Hz increment but that didn’t seem to matter. I ended up just pressing stuff and then going to band and choosing 144 MHz again seemed to fix it. Phew!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="qsos.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="QSOs"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-087/qsos.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="QSOs"></a></p>
<figcaption>QSOs</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>It was nice having the waterfall to see is there was any activity and there certainly was some! I knew MM0EFI and MM0RFN were going up Ben Macdui and Glas Maol respectively, but not sure if they’d got to the summit in time. Fraser was supposed to be on 145.250, so I tuned to it and heard Bill, GM0NRT, talking to someone but couldn’t hear the other end. I was worried I couldn’t hear Fraser on Ben Macdui, but turned out was just someone else. Tuning around, I heard a guy down at the car park by <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-085/">Hill of Garvock</a> and ended up qualifying the summit with those on his net. I managed to work four summit to summits, two on Ben Macdui, Glas Maol and then Morven. I heard a station down in East Lothian calling on 145.500 but he didn’t hear my reply. After about an hour, I had 10 QSOs and thought it was about time we packed up.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="Waughton3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Off to Aden Country Park"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-087/Waughton3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Off to Aden Country Park"></a></p>
<figcaption>Off to Aden Country Park</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>We headed back down, and went to <a href="https://adencountrypark.org.uk/">Aden Country Park</a> for some more fun. Turned out to be an old timey tractor fair and there were loads of them on the roads as we drove there.</p>
<p>Was a fun day all round, and nice to join in with this event. Maybe next time I’ll try for a higher summit!</p>
<p>The guys up Ben Macdui had a <a href="https://reflector.sota.org.uk/t/carn-amhaim-gm-es-013-ben-macdui-gm-es-001-slightly-broken/36399">fun trip.</a>. Not jealous in the slightest…😅 Also afterwards, Chris, 2M0RVZ, was boasting about his points compared to mine…challenge accepted!</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-087/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 29 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-087/145-alive.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>An Socach</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-038/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Fraser, MM0EFI, messaged asking who wanted to do a Munro midweek, and I thought it was a good opportunity to go. He also rallied Chris, 2M0RVZ, and Simon, GM4JXP. I decided to go up An Socach, whilst Fraser and Chris were going up Carn a’Gheoidh, and Simon on Glas Maol. A notice was posted on the <a href="https://reflector.sota.org.uk/t/upcoming-2m-activity-wednesday-25th-september/36335/65">reflector</a>, and several others were keen to go up summits in Scotland and England. Later on we came to realise that the time posted on the reflector and Alerts was two hours late! Oops…no wonder no-one else turned up “at the right time”.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ansocach-14.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Car Park"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-038/ansocach-14.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Car Park"></a></p>
<figcaption>Car Park</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I got to the start around 7:45, and it was a chilly start, with -1.5 degC in Braemar as I drove through, however, the weather was stunning with clear blue skies and not a breath of wind.</p>
<p>I cycled along the estate track until the actual ascent starts - probably saves about 20-30 minutes walking each way, as I thought Fraser and Chris would have a quicker walk back on their summit. I need to buy an actual mountain bike as this and Mount Keen the other week have felt like I was going to shake the bike, and me, to pieces. The bike made a helpful support when crossing the ford before turning up the hill.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ansocach-12.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Bike ends here"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-038/ansocach-12.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Bike ends here"></a></p>
<figcaption>Bike ends here</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Quite boggy on the way up until the final steep ascent onto the long plateau.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ansocach-13.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Up to the plateau"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-038/ansocach-13.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Up to the plateau"></a></p>
<figcaption>Up to the plateau</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The first cairn is only 6m below the actual summit but still around 2km away. At this point I called in with Fraser and Chris on the HT, and they were a similar 1.5km away from their summit.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ansocach-7.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Passing the residents"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-038/ansocach-7.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Passing the residents"></a></p>
<figcaption>Passing the residents</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Lots of good views and, as already said, lovely weather! I found a nice grassy patch near to the cairn to setup the yagi.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ansocach-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="Yagi and IC-705"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-038/ansocach-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Yagi and IC-705"></a></p>
<figcaption>Yagi and IC-705</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Some good QSOs on 2m FM and SSB, not quite what Fraser managed but his summit was higher and so he was in the way! 😅</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="qsos.jpeg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="Pink for FM and green for SSB"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-038/qsos.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Pink for FM and green for SSB"></a></p>
<figcaption>Pink for FM and green for SSB</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>After calling for a long time on sideband I was impatient on FM and kept jumping around when I saw activity on the waterfall, either following Fraser like an annoying puppy, or jumping onto the calling frequency when it was free. Probably should’ve just stayed still!</p>
<p>I made use of the flat plateau and large activation zone to start heading back but still ready with the HT for Alan, MM0VPM. <a href="https://apps.apple.com/gb/app/sota-goat/id590206108">SotaGoat</a> app kept me in check and that saved a bit of time coming back. My worries of being slow down were unnecessary as I ended up being at the Bothy for a full round of cakes before the others arrived…and I couldn’t let them feel guilty for eating in front of me.</p>
<p>G4IPB reported hearing me on from <a href="https://sotl.as/summits/G/LD-008">Blencathra</a> - in the lake district just north of Keswick - and after seeing his report I realised that I also heard him but we were in the middle of some other QSOs so I never followed up and changed frequency. I was only on the HT and RH770 but he’d give me 55 and he was clear to me, although the first QSO was a bit muffled and dogs barking made it unclear.</p>
<p>The views were spectacular all around, with snow on the high summits.</p>
<div>

</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-panel" data-layout-ncol="3">
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: center;">
<p><a href="ansocach-10.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="my-group"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-038/ansocach-10.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: center;">
<p><a href="ansocach-11.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="my-group"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-038/ansocach-11.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: center;">
<p><a href="ansocach-9.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="my-group"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-038/ansocach-9.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: center;">
<p><a href="ansocach-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="my-group"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-038/ansocach-4.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: center;">
<p><a href="ansocach-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="my-group"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-038/ansocach-3.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
</div>
</div>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-038/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 25 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-038/ansocach-5.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Largo Law</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-ss-259/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>My wife and I had a trip away for the weekend, and I suggested a nice walk nearby…which of course was a SOTA summit! We were staying near St.&nbsp;Andrews, which is quite a flat area, however, there are a few granite lumps you can climb. Today’s one was Largo Law. If the weather was good, we’d have a lovely view of the Forth, Edinburgh and East Lothian. However, that wasn’t the case today…more like gray and cloudy.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="largolaw-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Summit ahead!"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-ss-259/largolaw-4.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Summit ahead!"></a></p>
<figcaption>Summit ahead!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The route is straight forward, as shown on <a href="https://sotl.as/summits/GM/SS-259">Sotlas</a>, park at the school/cemetery, up towards the farm and then straight up the hill! The track was tricky in places as the ground was dry and covered in loose soil, but we made it up fine.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="largolaw-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Looking back down the path over the Firth of Forth"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-ss-259/largolaw-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Looking back down the path over the Firth of Forth"></a></p>
<figcaption>Looking back down the path over the Firth of Forth</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I setup the slim g on the 6m carbon mast, put out a spot and called CQ. It took a few calls but stations did start coming back. Good coverage across Glasgow, Edinburgh and up to Montrose area. Had a nice chat with GM4PKJ, who lives very close to where we used to live around 10 years ago. His wife is a ham too, but I didn’t realise until I got home and looked him up on QRZ, otherwise I could’ve said hi to her too.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="largolaw-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Horses in the field"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-ss-259/largolaw-3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Horses in the field"></a></p>
<figcaption>Horses in the field</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Got my four contacts and packed up. My wife was sat nearby and commented the radio conversation was so “old man”. It was mostly what’s the weather and setup but I probably do adopt some old man tendencies when talking…it’s as though you’ve got to fit in. I should just ignore that and say whatever I want. Although I do like describing the weather on a summit, as quite often it’s different from “ground” level.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="gmss259 lora.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Heard across the water"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-ss-259/gmss259 lora.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Heard across the water"></a></p>
<figcaption>Heard across the water</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I had my Lora tracker with me and looked up if I’d been tracked. Two stations across the water had followed me up and down the summit. One was a new one in the centre of Edinburgh owned by <a href="https://gm5aug.topple.scot/">GM5AUG</a>.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="gm5aug-6 igate.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="GM5AUG-6"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-ss-259/gm5aug-6 igate.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="GM5AUG-6"></a></p>
<figcaption>GM5AUG-6</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>We headed back down and then back to the hotel, to enjoy the silence of no kids for the rest of the weekend!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="largolaw-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="Smile!"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-ss-259/largolaw-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Smile!"></a></p>
<figcaption>Smile!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-ss-259/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 22 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-ss-259/largolaw-5.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Buck</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-039/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Not wanting to waste a glorious day, I had time for a quick activation in the morning and <a href="https://sotl.as/summits/GM/ES-039">The Buck</a> was the recommendation.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="buck-11.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Short ascent"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-039/buck-11.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Short ascent"></a></p>
<figcaption>Short ascent</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The route is pretty easy, not quite a straight line as I’ve drawn but I parked slightly east on the road and walked up until I met this fence line. A quick march and you can be at the top in 30 minutes. The sub-500m area is pretty boggy and wet, even today when it hasn’t rained in a while. It was a little slow in places, trying to avoid plunging my feet into ankle deep water. The path is also vague at this stage but then becomes more defined within about 1km of the summit.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="buck-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="View to the top"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-039/buck-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="View to the top"></a></p>
<figcaption>View to the top</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="buck-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Squelchy"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-039/buck-3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Squelchy"></a></p>
<figcaption>Squelchy</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The weather was amazing, brilliant sunshine, blue skies and not a breath of wind. I was roasting on the way up!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="buck-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Trig point on top of the rocky summit"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-039/buck-4.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Trig point on top of the rocky summit"></a></p>
<figcaption>Trig point on top of the rocky summit</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Even at the top the wind was minimal, and I’ve never seen my carbon-6 stand so straight at a summit before! I made use of the nice clear hole in the trig point and put the mast in it with the slim g on top. I could see for miles and miles!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="buck-6.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="Setup for 2m"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-039/buck-6.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Setup for 2m"></a></p>
<figcaption>Setup for 2m</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I was hoping it would be a quick activation on 2m, as I needed to get back home by lunchtime, and this summit would cover a huge area. Back from his hols in <a href="https://reflector.sota.org.uk/t/the-sota-rough-guide-to-barbados/36296">Barbados</a>, MM0EFI was first in the log. After 5 minutes, Bill in Aberdeen, GM0NRT, called back, and whilst we were talking I heard another station call. This time it was GM0UDL up in Fortrose, just north of Inverness who had seen my Lora tracker being picked up by GM4SJB (even further north!). He told me about his lora setup and how everyone around that area has setup iGates and DMR repeaters. Sounds like a great setup they have. Not long afterwards my fourth 2m contact, needed to qualify the summit, came from GM8ZKU across to the east by the coast. Again, another nice QSO with Simon for the first time. Time was getting on and I did need to be back home, I tried on more CQ but then called it a day.</p>
<p>I</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="buck-7.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="Looking North"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-039/buck-7.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Looking North"></a></p>
<figcaption>Looking North</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>had a quick look around for the <a href="https://www.walkhighlands.co.uk/aberdeenshire/the-buck.shtml">ancient engravings</a> but couldn’t find them. It was a quick walk back down the hill to the car. I’d forgotten about the sogginess but managed to escape with dry feet.</p>
<p>When I got home I looked up the Lora tracking on <a href="https://lora.ham-radio-op.net/">EA2RCF’s mapping page</a>, and was surprised to see just how far away GM4SJB’s receiving igate was! It had also tracked me nearly the whole route up and down, which I then realised was me walking the county boundaries. The power on the tracker is tiny and the antenna isn’t amazing but this time it all worked well. I’ve been carrying it with me on most summits but there haven’t been any igates nearby that have picked me up.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="buck-13.jpeg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7" title="Lora 70cm distance"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-039/buck-13.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Lora 70cm distance"></a></p>
<figcaption>Lora 70cm distance</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="buck-14.jpeg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-8" title="Tracking my route"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-039/buck-14.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Tracking my route"></a></p>
<figcaption>Tracking my route</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="buck-12.jpeg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-9" title="Speedy!"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-039/buck-12.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Speedy!"></a></p>
<figcaption>Speedy!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>A nice quick 4-pointer summit - I’m beginning to think <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-018/">Morven</a> is a brutal 4-pointer! - although not for a wet day, or post a lot of rain. The summit is quite exposed, although maybe you could find some shelter depending on the wind direction. It’s a popular summit to do with Tap O’Noth, as that’s just a few miles away, however, I just didn’t have time on this occasion. Maybe they’ll be a good combo next year during the winter bonus period.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="uncle-buck.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-10" title="What the Buck"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-039/uncle-buck.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="What the Buck"></a></p>
<figcaption>What the Buck</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-039/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-039/buck-8.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>FTDX10 and Omirig - for CloudlogCAT</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/cloudcat-with-ftdx10/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>I’ve been using <a href="https://github.com/magicbug/Cloudlog">Cloudlog</a> for my logs, and have also recently migrated to <a href="https://github.com/wavelog/wavelog">wavelog</a>. Both of these share the same API which you can use with various CAT command software to get data from your radio into the logging program. Most useful for when doing live QSOs and to have it update the frequency and mode for you.</p>
<p>One such tool is <a href="https://github.com/magicbug/CloudlogCAT">CloudlogCAT</a> (windows only). It uses omnirig behind the scenes to interface with the radio. Other tools can be seen on the <a href="https://github.com/wavelog/Wavelog/wiki/Third-Party-Tools">wiki</a> pages of the two loggers. I had this working on another laptop but for various reasons was using a different one. I’d setup the vertical again in the garden and brought out the FTDX10 to use. I spent ages faffing about trying to get this to work and eventually found the right settings.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="cloudcat-omnirig.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Settings to use"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/cloudcat-with-ftdx10/cloudcat-omnirig.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Settings to use"></a></p>
<figcaption>Settings to use</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I also have a nicer way of setting up the spiderbeam mast using a base clamp wooden block and guy wires attached to a hose clamp with rubber nitrile protecting the mast. It takes no time at all to setup, and the remote ATU, radials, cables, and radio are all critical path items now!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="Vertical-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Mast base - I’ve since made the hole bigger so the mast rubber foot goes all the way in"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/cloudcat-with-ftdx10/Vertical-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Mast base - I’ve since made the hole bigger so the mast rubber foot goes all the way in"></a></p>
<figcaption>Mast base - I’ve since made the hole bigger so the mast rubber foot goes all the way in</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I might upgrade to 4mm rope for the guys, as the cleats don’t have much area to bite and in high winds they did slip.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-caution callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Don’t tighten the hose clamps too much, as you’ll damage the mast
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">

</div>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>FTDX10</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/cloudcat-with-ftdx10/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/cloudcat-with-ftdx10/Vertical-1.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Mount Keen</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-014/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="keen-7.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Start of the ascent"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-014/keen-7.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Start of the ascent"></a></p>
<figcaption>Start of the ascent</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Another day off and the forecast was promising blue skies and sunshine. I’d spent the evenings this week trawling sotlas trying to figure out where to go. It was our youngest’s P1 stay and play this morning, plus swim training after school, so I had to fit my trip into that window. I’ve been finding I go faster than OS Maps walking prediction but yet to keep detailed enough records to figure out my speed, so planning a new location is always hit or miss (along with the <a href="https://sotawatch.sota.org.uk/en/">alerts</a> I post!) To complicate matters more, I was planning on cycling the first part of the route before walking. I settled on Mount Keen and left after a fun session with the P1s.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="route.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="OS Map of the route"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-014/route.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="OS Map of the route"></a></p>
<figcaption>OS Map of the route</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I was also going to go the Glen Esk route, from the south, vs.&nbsp;the Glen Tanar one from the north. I thought it was a closer drive to home, but it was actually further, however, I think the walk is shorter this way. The road into Glen Esk seems to go on and on and on! Plus no end of dumb pheasants to watch out for on the road. I’ve actually done this hill before, maybe 12/13 years ago and on that trip we ended up walking through a blizzard! I can’t remember if we even made it to the top or decided to head back down, to then find the stream crossing to be more challenging than the way up!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="keen-8.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Stream crossing"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-014/keen-8.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Stream crossing"></a></p>
<figcaption>Stream crossing</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I cycled from the car park, just before the Lochlee Parish Church, along the north side of the river. My bike is a “hybrid” which is more road bike than mountain bike but has thickish tyres. I think this was probably the limit for it, as it was quite rocky and the ride was very rattly! I made it, and it cut off a good chunk of time but wasn’t always pleasant. I set off at 10:45 from the car park, and cycled for 30 minutes to just before the stream crossing in the picture above. The terrain is fairly flat with only a small incline the whole way. You also pass the Queen’s Well, which is nice to look at if you’ve never seen it before.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="keen-9.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Looking back and Queen’s Well"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-014/keen-9.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Looking back and Queen’s Well"></a></p>
<figcaption>Looking back and Queen’s Well</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The path is very clear and well made the whole way, some places its been eroded by water, or repaired with big chunks of rock. The roadway keeps going and you have to make sure you turn off towards Mount Keen.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="keen-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="A good view back down the Glen on the way up"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-014/keen-4.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A good view back down the Glen on the way up"></a></p>
<figcaption>A good view back down the Glen on the way up</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="keen-5.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="Final path to the summit (beyond the ridge)"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-014/keen-5.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Final path to the summit (beyond the ridge)"></a></p>
<figcaption>Final path to the summit (beyond the ridge)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>After an hour I’d reached the top and had my HT out as MM0VPM was on <a href="https://sotl.as/summits/GM/ES-009">Sgor Gaoith</a> and I was hoping for a summit to summit. Seems the weather wasn’t as good with him inland, and the snow I could see in the distance was probably where he was! I heard GM4CCN calling CQ and tried to answer but the Aberdeen folk thought I was calling CQ and called me back. Made a couple of contacts on the telescopic RH770 with the new FT-65 before setting up the slim G off to the side.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="keen-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7" title="Made it!"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-014/keen-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Made it!"></a></p>
<figcaption>Made it!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>There were quite a few folks on the summit so I was over to the west side. Not sure if that was the best as I was in the shadow of the cairn and perhaps they might’ve been blocking my signal. I heard GM4CCN a few more times and we tried to have a QSO. I found holding the PTT on the FT65 difficult when my hands were getting cold, that I don’t think I was actually transmitting and so we never made the QSO. Bill, GM0NRT, kept saying I dropped out but I think it was not holding the PTT. I was probably holding it wrong, in my right hand and using my finger on the PTT, vs.&nbsp;my left and using my thumb. Or I should’ve put on a glove.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="keen-6.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-8" title="Lochnagar"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-014/keen-6.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Lochnagar"></a></p>
<figcaption>Lochnagar</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I tried the slim G for a bit, had a couple more but not as many as I thought I’d get on this summit. I switched to HF with the 5.5m vertical and tried 20m. A good reply on 20m with 16 in the log. I did try 10m for a bit. I heard a VK station absolutely booming in, who was talking to a MW0 station in Wales, but only one reply to my CQ. By this time I was getting cold and I’d been on the summit an hour, and should probably be getting back.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="keen-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-9" title="Towards Aberdeen"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-014/keen-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Towards Aberdeen"></a></p>
<figcaption>Towards Aberdeen</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>As I was packing up a lady, who I’d passed on my bike, asked me to take a photo of her. She also asked if I was a Russian spy. I said a good spy wouldn’t reveal if they were one - but also that could be double bluffing. We ended up walking back down together until I got to my bike. She was trying to complete all the Munros, and had about 20-odd left. I thought about making my excuses and running ahead but it was nice having a little chat and she wasn’t really any slower than me.</p>
<p>The bike ride back was easier as slightly downhill, so only took 20 minutes, and I was back at the car in no time, and home with 30 minutes to spare! Although only 12% battery in the car. The journey out had used 51% of the battery, which was slightly worrying but I suspect it was the colder morning, and now it was 15 C.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-014/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-014/keen-5.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Carn Ealasaid</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-030/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Sunday and a busy day for the kids planned, however, it did mean my eldest and I were free all morning. She’d enjoyed our <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-068/">last SOTA activation</a> and this time I wanted to try somewhere further afield, and do more than a one-pointer! Especially after my mid-week three summits trip.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ealasaid-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Admiring the view from the ski centre"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-030/ealasaid-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Admiring the view from the ski centre"></a></p>
<figcaption>Admiring the view from the ski centre</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>We drove to the Lecht ski centre through thick fog and mist (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haar_(fog)">haar</a>) for about an hour. I’d looked at the forecast and it was meant to be partially sunny, but I was wondering if it had changed but I’d not seen it. However, with about 20 minutes to go, it suddenly cleared up and when we reached the car park it was a lovely day. This significantly helped the trip as I’m not sure my hiking partner would’ve been too pleased other wise! She immediately commented that the first path looked steep. She wasn’t wrong, it was the steepest part of the journey, although later on, on the way back, it was taxing again.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="route.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="The route"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-030/route.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="The route"></a></p>
<figcaption>The route</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>You walk around the lifts and towards another summit before descending and then ascending again to the final summit. Alone, and determined, I reckon I could do it in 45 minutes, but today it took us 1:15, with a couple of stops to sit down for a bit.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ealasaid-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="View of summit from Beinn A’Chruinnich by the ski lifts"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-030/ealasaid-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="View of summit from Beinn A’Chruinnich by the ski lifts"></a></p>
<figcaption>View of summit from Beinn A’Chruinnich by the ski lifts</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ealasaid-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Admiring the bogs we crossed"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-030/ealasaid-3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Admiring the bogs we crossed"></a></p>
<figcaption>Admiring the bogs we crossed</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The peat bogs weren’t too bad and quite dry, but I can imagine after some rainfall they’d be very squelchy.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ealasaid-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="At the top!"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-030/ealasaid-4.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="At the top!"></a></p>
<figcaption>At the top!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>We made it up the last slope, watching every meter on SOTAGoat app! I emptied out the snacks and set to work getting on 2m.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ealasaid-5.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="Slim G on Carbon-6 mast"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-030/ealasaid-5.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Slim G on Carbon-6 mast"></a></p>
<figcaption>Slim G on Carbon-6 mast</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Annoyingly my Kenwood D72 wouldn’t turn on. It had died on Foudland during the week and I assumed it was just flat. I’d charged it and the charging light had turned green so I assumed all was good. Well no, it wasn’t. I tried fiddling with the battery clip to get it out but couldn’t work the mechanism and soon gave up on it. I had an old TH-79 with me which did turn on (although the LCD screen doesn’t show all the segments and is difficult to read). I have tested the TH-79 at home and it transmitted, but no-one could hear me and I wasn’t sure if it was really working.</p>
<p>I didn’t want to spend too long faffing about as the summit is very exposed, and whilst it was a nice day, my daughter would soon get cold just sitting around. So I switched to HF. I debated between the 5.5m random wire vertical or the 40m EFHW. I wanted to go on 40m and the random wire isn’t necessarily great for 40m. However, I should’ve just gone with the vertical. As I was rushing, it meant it took me ages to get setup as things kept going wrong. Eventually I was sorted, but then the challenge of finding a free frequency. Seemed to be a contest going on, bunkers on the air and all sorts, but I did manage. Got 5 on 40m, including two locals from the SOTA Whatsapp group and that meant success! I thought I’d quickly try 20m. I heard one faint German station but when I looked up the cloud had come right in and we were sat in it. I knew it was time to go, and so we quickly packed up and started heading down. A summit in the cloud is disorientating and cold.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ealasaid-6.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7" title="From fun to fog in five seconds"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-030/ealasaid-6.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="From fun to fog in five seconds"></a></p>
<figcaption>From fun to fog in five seconds</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>We headed back down, and wanted to cut off part of the path up to the first summit, and follow the contours around. We were sort of successful but did get caught up in the bog and ended up walking a bit further downhill than we should’ve. Again, the cloud level didn’t help. It was a big of a struggle to get back on to the path at the top of the ski runs but we made it, and then it was an easy downhill from there.</p>
<p>Quite the change when we got to the bottom, the nice view at the start of this post was replaced by white cloud!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ealasaid-7.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-8" title="What wind turbine?"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-030/ealasaid-7.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="What wind turbine?"></a></p>
<figcaption>What wind turbine?</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I’m glad we arrived when we did, else it would’ve been quite miserable and the only excitement of the radio activation wouldn’t have been shared by all!</p>
<p>We stopped at the Spar in <a href="https://www.undiscoveredscotland.co.uk/strathdon/bellabeg/index.html">Bellabeg</a> for some diet coke and a jam swiss roll, which we ate nearly half each before driving home.</p>
<p>There are a few more 4 pointers in the area, and hopefully I can get back to do some of those. Most have been activated less than 10 times, which suggests they’re maybe not that exciting or easy to get to. <a href="https://sotl.as/summits/GM/ES-023">Brown Cow Hill</a>, <a href="https://sotl.as/summits/GM/ES-036">Geallaig</a>, and <a href="https://sotl.as/summits/GM/ES-034">Mona Gowan</a> don’t seem too bad, so perhaps I should try those first.</p>
<p>When I got home I checked the D72. It wouldn’t turn on, but when I plugged in an external power supply it turned on and then worked fine on battery. I don’t like the reliability of this, and being caught out on a summit again. I might get a new battery pack but I also might look for another HT. Perhaps a Yeasu FT-65 etc. that has great battery life is just a simple HT.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-030/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 08 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-030/ealasaid-3.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Building a portable 2m yagi</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/building-a-2m-portable-yagi/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>I’ve been enjoying activating SOTA summits on 2m, and after visiting <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-012/">Glas Maol</a> and seeing how far I could get with an omni directional antenna, and watching videos of people using a 2m yagi to get into England from the highlands, I wanted to build a yagi.</p>
<p>All my research pointed me towards <a href="https://www.qsl.net/dk7zb/start1.htm">DK7ZB’s</a> designs, specifically the <a href="https://www.qsl.net/dk7zb/PVC-Yagis/PVC-details.htm">lightweight ones</a>. I decided the 4 element design with a 1m boom was optimal between gain and practicalities. This has a gain of 7 dBd and a front to back ratio of 12 dB. It also has the advantage of being able to use it with 70 cms.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="2m-yagi-16.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Parts to build"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/building-a-2m-portable-yagi/2m-yagi-16.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Parts to build"></a></p>
<figcaption>Parts to build</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I went to B&amp;Q and bought some 22mm PVC pipe, some wall clips, 4mm aluminium rods, and a 6mm aluminium tube. I already had some electrical connector blocks and RG58 cable at home. I made the boom a little longer than 1m, so I could hand hold it if I wanted to, otherwise it only needs to be 1m in length.</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<caption>Dimensions from DK7ZB - using 4mm elements</caption>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th></th>
<th style="text-align: center;">Positions along boom (mm)</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">Length of element (mm)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Reflector</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">1020</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Radiator</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">260</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">977</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Director 1</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">470</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">930</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Director 2</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">985</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">910</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p><a href="https://vk1nam.wordpress.com/2018/04/07/antenna-project-portable-2m-4el-dl6wu-yagi/">VK1AD’s post</a> on building a similar yagi helped me decide how to mount everything to the boom, and I set to cutting the aluminium rods and drilling the holes in the clamp. The directors are easy, as they just slide through the clamp as a single piece. The reflector is slightly longer than 1m which the rods come in, so I used the 6mm tube as a connector between two 4mm rods. Sounds good in theory but it’s tricky to get the rods into the tube - precision hammering needed.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="2m-yagi-14.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Best way to drill"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/building-a-2m-portable-yagi/2m-yagi-14.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Best way to drill"></a></p>
<figcaption>Best way to drill</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="2m-yagi-13.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Driven element"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/building-a-2m-portable-yagi/2m-yagi-13.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Driven element"></a></p>
<figcaption>Driven element</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The driven element used the connectors from inside an electrical connector block, zip tied and then glued into one of the clamps. I used some solder wick to attach the coax to and screwed the elements in on each side.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="2m-yagi-12.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Attaching coax"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/building-a-2m-portable-yagi/2m-yagi-12.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Attaching coax"></a></p>
<figcaption>Attaching coax</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="2m-yagi-11.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="More hot glue and amalgamation tape"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/building-a-2m-portable-yagi/2m-yagi-11.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="More hot glue and amalgamation tape"></a></p>
<figcaption>More hot glue and amalgamation tape</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="2m-yagi-10.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="With choke"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/building-a-2m-portable-yagi/2m-yagi-10.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="With choke"></a></p>
<figcaption>With choke</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>RG58 is a bit heavy but it’s all I had so would do. Whilst this was easy to build, it does mean the only way I can transport it is by unscrewing the elements. Not the best solution but I wanted to get it built vs.&nbsp;debating over other ways or buying more things. A common way others do it is with a box mounted on the boom and there’s a coax connector on it, so you can remove the box with driven element in one. My one has about 3-4m of coax on which is enough from the mast mounting position to having the radio on the ground underneath.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Tip
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>The length of the driven element is from tip to tip, including the gap in between.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="2m-yagi-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7" title="Packs up small-ish"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/building-a-2m-portable-yagi/2m-yagi-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Packs up small-ish"></a></p>
<figcaption>Packs up small-ish</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I marked the PVC tube with sharpie for the location of each clamp, together with numbers. I also put a mark in the centre of the rod on the directors so I could centre it if it moved about in the clamp. It’s all about 1m long and I found a thin bag to carry it in. It’s not the greatest but will do. I used bungees to tie it to the side of my backpack.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="2m-yagi-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-8" title="Total weight - including coax"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/building-a-2m-portable-yagi/2m-yagi-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Total weight - including coax"></a></p>
<figcaption>Total weight - including coax</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I’m using a SOTABeams <a href="https://www.sotabeams.co.uk/tactical-mini-compact-ultra-portable-6-m-19-6-ft-mast/">tactical mini</a> mast to support it. It’s 6m telescopic fibreglass pole that has more strength than my usual <a href="https://www.sotabeams.co.uk/carbon-6-ultra-light-6-m-19-6-ft-mast/">Carbon-6</a> mast. There are two conduit wall mounts attached to the boom, so the yagi can be mounted vertically or horizontally. It works well enough, although if I want to change polarisation I have to take the mast down and then put it up again. I could take out all the other sections I don’t need but if I’m only taking one mast on an activation I want the 6m in case I need to setup HF.</p>
<p>I 3D printed some guying rings and rope tensioners from <a href="https://www.thingiverse.com/thing:5616644">this design</a> and cut some cord to length for the mast. The 2nd lowest ring fitted perfectly on the bottom segment of the tactical mini.</p>
<p><a href="2m-yagi-6.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-9"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/building-a-2m-portable-yagi/2m-yagi-6.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p><a href="2m-yagi-7.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-10"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/building-a-2m-portable-yagi/2m-yagi-7.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="2m-yagi-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-11" title="Testing in the garden"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/building-a-2m-portable-yagi/2m-yagi-3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Testing in the garden"></a></p>
<figcaption>Testing in the garden</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>First test was in the garden, listening to the 2m lunchtime net…so it received well enough.</p>
<p>The first outing was to <a href="https://sotl.as/summits/GM/ES-072">Cairn William</a>, where I’d set it up on the top. We’d arranged SSB activity on another summit, although that guy had to pull out, however, we’d also prepared the locals to listen out. I started with SSB and managed to make four contacts locally with it. I then flipped it to FM and made a few more. Including a nice summit to summit with Schiehallion, around 112 km away! I brought it out later in the day on <a href="https://sotl.as/summits/GM/ES-079">Tillymorgan</a>, and managed a contact with Helmsdale, around 100 km to the north…whilst the yagi was pointing south! Turning it around turned me from a 53 and a 59 by the chaser</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="cairn-william.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-12" title="On Cairn William"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/building-a-2m-portable-yagi/cairn-william.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="On Cairn William"></a></p>
<figcaption>On Cairn William</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="tillymorgan-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-13" title="On TIllymorgan"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/building-a-2m-portable-yagi/tillymorgan-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="On TIllymorgan"></a></p>
<figcaption>On TIllymorgan</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="qsos.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-14" title="Long distance QSOs"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/building-a-2m-portable-yagi/qsos.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Long distance QSOs"></a></p>
<figcaption>Long distance QSOs</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I’m pleased with the results and think it worked rather well! It wasn’t too tricky to setup and use in the field, nor heavy to carry. It takes a bit of getting used to the length of it, especially when walking through forests as I kept catching it on trees and causing them to dump all their water onto my back!</p>
<p>I think a different way to connect the coax and the driven element would improve it, and maybe a dedicated mast that was just the right length would be better.</p>
<p>I did find this design for a <a href="https://www.iz2uuf.net/wp/index.php/2013/04/06/100g-yagi/">100g yagi</a> that looks nice, and have saved a few links to 2m moxon’s. Not sure when or if I’ll make these, as I do like the convenience of the slim G. I also <a href="https://www.printables.com/model/754860-mast-clip-for-2m-slim-g-antenna-for-sota-use-espec">printed a clip</a> for it, so it doesn’t flap around in the breeze.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Construction</category>
  <category>sota</category>
  <category>2m</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/building-a-2m-portable-yagi/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/building-a-2m-portable-yagi/cairn-william.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Hill of Tillymorgan</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-079/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="tillymorgan-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Looking back at Foudland"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-079/tillymorgan-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Looking back at Foudland"></a></p>
<figcaption>Looking back at Foudland</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>A quick drive across the A96 and I was parked by the old church - <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/pah11Z7VKxTnonEh7">Kirkton of Culsalmond Old Parish Church</a>. The path is easy, straight up the road to the turbines and then either around them bypassing the fence, or past them and then finding a spot where the barbed wire fence has come down.</p>
<p><a href="tillymorgan-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-079/tillymorgan-2.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="tillymorgan-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="They’re big!"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-079/tillymorgan-3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="They’re big!"></a></p>
<figcaption>They’re big!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="tillymorgan-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="South towards Bennachie"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-079/tillymorgan-4.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="South towards Bennachie"></a></p>
<figcaption>South towards Bennachie</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Doesn’t take long and you’re in the activation zone, but I wanted to get to the trig point. Turns out there’s an old quarry here and you have to navigate it, but the trig offers lovely views all around once you do get there.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="tillymorgan-5.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="Slates"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-079/tillymorgan-5.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Slates"></a></p>
<figcaption>Slates</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Decided to setup the yagi again and try it out, just on FM this time. The wind blew it around a little which caused signal reports to jump up and down. Managed across the water to the North to Helmsdale, about 100 km away…from the back of the yagi! I was 53 at first but when I turned it around I was 59 to him.</p>
<p><a href="tillymorgan-7.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-079/tillymorgan-7.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p>Just managed four in the log but that was enough, starting to feel the days activities now and it was time to be heading home. My shoes hadn’t done well on Cairn William, and were soaked back then, and still wet now.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="tillymorgan-6.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7" title="Looking tired!"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-079/tillymorgan-6.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Looking tired!"></a></p>
<figcaption>Looking tired!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-079/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 04 Sep 2024 16:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-079/bee.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Cairn William</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-072/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>This was the first summit I tested my <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/building-a-2m-portable-yagi/">new 2m yagi</a> on. I was pleased with the summit to summit with Schiehallion around 112 km away.</p>
<p>I parked in a lay by just <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/vJktHhqjE538fz6N6">here</a>, and walked up several mountain bike trails.</p>
<p><a href="route.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-072/route.png" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p>The first part was pretty muddy, but once up on the forestry track and beyond it was fine. It was a nice day if you looked south, but not so much to the north. The summit was in the clouds and somewhat damp.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="cairn-william-8.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Muddy track"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-072/cairn-william-8.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Muddy track"></a></p>
<figcaption>Muddy track</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="cairn-william-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Looking South"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-072/cairn-william-4.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Looking South"></a></p>
<figcaption>Looking South</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="cairn-william-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="North to Millstone"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-072/cairn-william-3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="North to Millstone"></a></p>
<figcaption>North to <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-077/">Millstone</a></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The track is fairly easy to follow, just make sure to turn off the roadway on to the path, and the no entry signs are because the route is intended for mountain bikers.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="cairn-william-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="Turn off here!"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-072/cairn-william-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Turn off here!"></a></p>
<figcaption>Turn off here!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="cairn-william-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="⛔"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-072/cairn-william-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="⛔"></a></p>
<figcaption>⛔</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Was fairly light breeze on the summit but nothing too bad, so it wasn’t hard setting up the mast with the guys. They do get tangled somewhat so I might look at alternatives.</p>
<p><a href="cairn-william-6.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-072/cairn-william-6.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p><a href="cairn-william-7.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-8"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-072/cairn-william-7.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p>Spoke to a couple of locals on the HT, once I was within the activation zone, and then setup the yagi for SSB. Managed 4 on sideband - a first for me - and 2M0RVZ had his first 2m sideband as well. Both of us using the ic-705. I think Chris just used the RH-770 for his antenna on the radio!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="cairn-william-5.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-9" title="Action shot!"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-072/cairn-william-5.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Action shot!"></a></p>
<figcaption>Action shot!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I let Bill, GM0NRT, know I was going up some other hills later that day, so he was going to keep an ear out for me.</p>
<p>As I was packing up I met G0JSO (although now GM0JSO as he’s moved locally) and we had a nice long chat about amateur radio. He’s not been on the air in ages and was asking lots of questions. I sent him an email when I got home, and hopefully we will hear him on the air soon. It would be good to add him to the local SOTA chat for activator and chaser…but will see what happens.</p>
<p>Off to the next summit!</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-072/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 04 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-072/cairn-william-5.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Hill of Foudland</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-071/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Next summit of the day. A short drive up the A96 and off at Colpy to Hill of Foudland. I was approaching from the east so I was close to Tillymorgan but it’s not a very exciting route. I think there’s a better one from the east. I’d read on Walkinghighlands that there’s more <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/CWsRgrzdmu87g1Ma9">parking in the forest</a>, beyond the limits of the public road. Not sure if this is really allowed or not but it seemed better than parking on essentially <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/v4MQV2DuYVNJe6as6">nothing</a>, as I was out of the way. This also saved me some walking along a boring track. After the chat with G0JSO, I was 30 minutes later than planned, and so I wasn’t sure if I was going to make it in time to get at the summit for the lunchtime 2m net.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="foudland-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="View south to Bennachie"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-071/foudland-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="View south to Bennachie"></a></p>
<figcaption>View south to <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-061/">Bennachie</a></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>As I was walking up I had my HT tuned into 145.550 MHz listening out for them. I managed to call into the net and said I was hiking up and I’d come back to them when I was at the top. I knew the top was quite flat, and watching SOTAGoat app I saw I was within the activation zone but still a good ~650 m from the actual summit point. At this stage I setup the telescopic pole between my legs with the slim G on the top.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="slimg.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="3D printed part to keep it attached to mast"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-071/slimg.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="3D printed part to keep it attached to mast"></a></p>
<figcaption>3D printed part to keep it attached to mast</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>On the way up, with the RH770, Bill and Paul couldn’t hear me (nor I Paul), but once I had the slim G up on the 6m mast, everyone was a very good signal. So I had three from the net and Mike was trying break in but the other guys kept chatting! Eventually it came round to me and I was answering their questions and building up to bringing Mike in when the D72 died on me! Luckily I had the 705 and got that hooked up. I rejoined and explained, plus got Mike in. If I just had the KX2 I’d been annoyed about that one!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="foudland-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Towers"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-071/foudland-3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Towers"></a></p>
<figcaption>Towers</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I was sat right in front of the towers but they were quiet on 145.550. I think the 705 had some issues with them but I turned off the pre-amp and that seemed to keep it calm. I said my goodbyes and turned back down the path to my third and final summit of the day!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="foudland-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Tillymorgan, left of the wind turbines"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-071/foudland-4.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Tillymorgan, left of the wind turbines"></a></p>
<figcaption>Tillymorgan, left of the wind turbines</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-071/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 04 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-071/foudland-3.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Beinn Bhrotain</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-007/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>After hearing that Alan, MM0VPM, was doing a <a href="https://reflector.sota.org.uk/t/gm-es-002-003-and-007/36165">tour of the Cairngorms</a>, the local SOTA group was listening out for him. I commented that no one had done <a href="https://sotl.as/summits/GM/ES-007">Beinn Bhrotain</a> for a long time, not even Fraser. His response was, “How about Sunday, then?” The offer included transportation and a loan of a mountain bike, plus, of course, the guided tour—an offer too good to refuse! Free time on the weekends can be tricky, with several sets of kids’ activities and potential birthday parties, so we needed to start early so I could be back in time for my wife to start her coaching session at the swim club. Fraser was good with that, and our rendezvous was at 6 a.m. in the Dinnet car park for the onward journey to the Linn of Dee.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhrotain-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Ready to Ride!"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-007/bhrotain-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Ready to Ride!"></a></p>
<figcaption>Ready to Ride!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>We’d all seen a photo recently shared of the midge in the area, which is quite unusual away from the west of Scotland. Sure enough, there were plenty about when we arrived and unpacked the bikes. We met a DoE group packing up their tents at White Bridge, and they told tales of woe and suffering in the evening; the leader seemed very pleased to be going home. My wife later told me about one of her swimmers sending home a photo of a pan of custard he was cooking on his expedition, which had a nice layer of midges on top. 🤢</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhrotain-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Along the Dee, summit in the clouds"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-007/bhrotain-3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Along the Dee, summit in the clouds"></a></p>
<figcaption>Along the Dee, summit in the clouds</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhrotain-24.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="They’re deeper than they look"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-007/bhrotain-24.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="They’re deeper than they look"></a></p>
<figcaption>They’re deeper than they look</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The weather was pleasant enough, although the promised clear skies had yet to appear, and the cloud level was fairly low. We continued on our ride, following the Dee along a rockier track with plenty of culverts to negotiate. After around 7.5 km of cycling, we left the bikes by the side of the fence and took the track up towards the first summit we could just about see, Carn Cloich-mhuilinn. The path came and went, or we found and lost it several times, but with the rocky peak to aim for, it wasn’t too difficult to navigate. Every so often, Fraser would point out surrounding summits or features, complete with name, SOTA points, and YouTube URL, the names of which I’d immediately forget until he told them to me again on the way back down. The last 200m or so climb of this Carn was bouldery but nice underfoot, a bit like clambering across rocks at a beach. With the interim summit climbed, we admired the view. The cloud was still low, and a few patches of sun were appearing in the distance. It looked promising that it would clear for us, although I wasn’t sure if it would in time for our final ascent.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhrotain-21.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Path to the summit"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-007/bhrotain-21.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Path to the summit"></a></p>
<figcaption>Path to the summit</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhrotain-15.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="View back towards the Dee"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-007/bhrotain-15.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="View back towards the Dee"></a></p>
<figcaption>View back towards the Dee</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>We had a good view across a small gully where the path was as obvious as could be. After a short descent down to a wee stream, the path was lost to us. A few phantom paths appeared, and we followed them, probably veering more towards the west than necessary, but we found a way. I kept my eye on SOTAGoat, to be sure I wasn’t being led astray, and we soon found ourselves both within the activation zone and the cloud. The trig appeared out of the mist, and we had made it!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhrotain-12.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="The summit, with LoRa beaconing (to no-one ☹️)"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-007/bhrotain-12.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="The summit, with LoRa beaconing (to no-one ☹️)"></a></p>
<figcaption>The summit, with LoRa beaconing (to no-one ☹️)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Having eaten breakfast in Aberdeen at 5 a.m., it now felt like lunchtime, even though it was only around 09:15. At this point, I found out one of Fraser’s secrets to successful mountaineering — <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buttery_(bread)">butteries</a>. Claiming “this was all he could find in the cupboard,” he proceeded to eat what I’d estimate to be around 8,000 calories in a matter of minutes. Checking the schedule, we decided we had around 45 minutes on the summit before we should head back down.</p>
<p>Fraser had brought the FT-857 and his <a href="https://www.iz2uuf.net/wp/index.php/2013/04/06/100g-yagi/">100g yagi</a>, and was hopeful to activate on 2m. I was on HF with the KX2 and the 18ft (5.5m) random wire vertical. We each found a suitable pile of rocks to shelter behind and set to work.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhrotain-5.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7" title="Setting up yagi"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-007/bhrotain-5.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Setting up yagi"></a></p>
<figcaption>Setting up yagi</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhrotain-7.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-8" title="A brief spell of sun"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-007/bhrotain-7.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A brief spell of sun"></a></p>
<figcaption>A brief spell of sun</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhrotain-13.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-9" title="Working the south"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-007/bhrotain-13.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Working the south"></a></p>
<figcaption>Working the south</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I started on 40m; the antenna needs a transformer to get a match, and even though it’s short, I’ve made contacts this way before. I thought I’d try 40m, as maybe it’s a desirable trig point or WAB etc., place that folks would want. I could hear some contest callers, but after my spot and calling with no replies, it was clearly completely dead for me, so I moved to 20m. After spotting and calling CQ, a slow trickle of replies came, and I relaxed once I crossed number 4! The replies kept coming, including four summit-to-summit stations in Germany, Switzerland, and Romania. I considered some other bands, but time was marching on, my hands were cold, and everything was getting wet. The sun suddenly shone through for a few moments, and it looked lovely. Two runners then came by, having climbed from the opposite side. They asked what I was doing, to which my usual answer is “amateur radio, speaking to other people on mountains.” They were impressed with Switzerland and asked if I could say hi from them. They soon ran off again, and given they were in running shorts and vests, I’m not surprised they didn’t want to hang around.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhrotain-11.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-10" title="Carbon 6 and 5.5 m vertical"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-007/bhrotain-11.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Carbon 6 and 5.5 m vertical"></a></p>
<figcaption>Carbon 6 and 5.5 m vertical</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhrotain-9.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-11" title="Activation attire"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-007/bhrotain-9.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Activation attire"></a></p>
<figcaption>Activation attire</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="gm5alx-20m.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-12" title="My QSOs on 20m"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-007/gm5alx-20m.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="My QSOs on 20m"></a></p>
<figcaption>My QSOs on 20m</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I could hear Fraser still calling and trying to keep his wind vane under control. I got the thumbs up that he didn’t need to get on HF, so I packed up. We had a brief celebration—this was my first 10-pointer—and then turned around and headed back down.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhrotain-14.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-13" title="Success! ⛰️📻"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-007/bhrotain-14.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Success! ⛰️📻"></a></p>
<figcaption>Success! ⛰️📻</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Once we were down out of the cloud, the view improved significantly! The cloud had started to lift, and we could see the surrounding summits and valleys—spectacular! Similar to the way up, paths came and went, but we had a clear view of the Dee and knew where to go.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhrotain-17.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-14" title="Back into the light"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-007/bhrotain-17.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Back into the light"></a></p>
<figcaption>Back into the light</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhrotain-19.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-15" title="Path back to Carn Cloich-mhuilinn"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-007/bhrotain-19.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Path back to Carn Cloich-mhuilinn"></a></p>
<figcaption>Path back to Carn Cloich-mhuilinn</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhrotain-20.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-16" title="More 10 pointers"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-007/bhrotain-20.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="More 10 pointers"></a></p>
<figcaption>More 10 pointers</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhrotain-25.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-17" title="Dee in the background"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-007/bhrotain-25.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Dee in the background"></a></p>
<figcaption>Dee in the background</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Back on the bikes and back towards civilisation. We had a quick stop at the Chest of Dee waterfalls, where the pool looked lovely and inviting, before the final 5km or so to the car park. Up, activated, and back in under 6 hours.</p>
<p>Fraser did well on 2m, with an FM contact into the Yorkshire coast, 310 km away. Although, I think he would’ve liked some more SSB activity.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="mm0efi-2m.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-18" title="MM0EFI/P on 2m"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-007/mm0efi-2m.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="MM0EFI/P on 2m"></a></p>
<figcaption>MM0EFI/P on 2m</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Back home, and back to reality of family life. A great trip out, and thanks to Fraser for making it happen. I’ve bought a lot of things since starting amateur radio, but didn’t think mountain bike shopping would next on my list! 🚵</p>
<p>OSMaps <a href="https://explore.osmaps.com/route/23148061/gmes007-ben-bhrotain?lat=56.995974&amp;lon=-3.651355&amp;zoom=12.7686&amp;style=Standard&amp;type=2d">route link.</a></p>
<p>Also posted to the <a href="https://reflector.sota.org.uk/t/a-busy-beinn-bhrotain/36174">SOTA Reflector.</a></p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-007/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-007/bhrotain-22.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>More QSL cards</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/more-qsl-cards/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>A formal looking letter arrived for me this morning, when I looked closely I could see it was from Germany. Inside were some nice QSL cards.</p>
<p><a href="dk1mi.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/more-qsl-cards/dk1mi.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p><a href="https://dk1mi.radio/about/">Micheal</a> has two of his own from our HF SSB, HF FT8 and QO-100 QSOs over the past year, plus then the special one, <a href="https://www.qrz.com/db/DF0MF">DF0MF</a>, from the lightship in Emden. <a href="https://dk1mi.radio/amrumbank/">Micheal describes</a> his discovery and subsequent visit and activation of this historical ship.</p>
<p>I shall need to QSL, although Micheal’s two different cards makes me think about making a new QSL card for my portable SOTA operations. ⛰️</p>
<p>The TH-79E in the background of the photo also arrived today. The battery is dead and I have no power supply for it, and it was sold as “seen” so let’s hope a new battery will fix it!</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>QSO</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/more-qsl-cards/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/more-qsl-cards/dk1mi.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
