<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>📻 GM5ALX Radio</title>
<link>https://gm5alx.uk/</link>
<atom:link href="https://gm5alx.uk/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>So many rabbit holes, you’ll struggle to find ground</description>
<generator>quarto-1.6.42</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Fri, 07 Mar 2025 14:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Carn Ealasaid</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-030/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>After the first summit today, I was back to the car, up the road to the Lecht ski centre for Carn Ealasaid! It is very close, so seems silly not to do it. I did this <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-030/">one last year</a> with my daughter, the weather was also lovely, although once I got on the air the cloud moved in and we had to make a quick exit. I was taking the same route today.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ealasaid-10.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Ski centre"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-030/ealasaid-10.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Ski centre"></a></p>
<figcaption>Ski centre</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>In some ways, quite a similar route, steep at first and then undulating to the summit. Oh and peat hags ! 😅</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ealasaid-8.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="No shortcuts!"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-030/ealasaid-8.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="No shortcuts!"></a></p>
<figcaption>No shortcuts!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ealasaid-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Peat Hags!"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-030/ealasaid-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Peat Hags!"></a></p>
<figcaption>Peat Hags!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ealasaid-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="As far as the eye can see"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-030/ealasaid-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="As far as the eye can see"></a></p>
<figcaption>As far as the eye can see</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ealasaid-9.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="Summit in sight"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-030/ealasaid-9.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Summit in sight"></a></p>
<figcaption>Summit in sight</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>You can follow the path that tries to steer clear of them to one side, but it’s hard on the way back, not wanting to take a more direct route!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ealasaid-6.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="Summit"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-030/ealasaid-6.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Summit"></a></p>
<figcaption>Summit</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Not much of a summit, and whilst the wind picked up a little, the cairn was enough support for the mast.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ealasaid-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7" title="Station"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-030/ealasaid-4.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Station"></a></p>
<figcaption>Station</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Simon was still on the Buck, so another S2S with him. Fraser was back home but called in on 2m. 2m was dead otherwise, so back to HF. This time 40m, a S2S with England, then a S2S on 17m and then one QSO on 10m to <a href="https://www.qrz.com/db/N4EX">North Carolina</a>.</p>
<p>Back down to the ski centre, for a cup of tea and slice of tiffen to go.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-030/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 07 Mar 2025 14:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-030/ealasaid-5.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Carn Mor</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-029/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>In a somewhat reminiscent turn of events as the <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-025/">GM/ES Winter Activity Day</a>, a few folks were planning on going out as Gerald, G4OIG, was planning his visit up here. Unfortunately, Gerald was ill in the week and had to cancel 🤒).</p>
<p>However, we had Fraser, MM0EFI, Simon, GM4JXP, Mike, 2M0WNA, myself, and Alan, MM0VPM, was trying hard in England. We weren’t all quite lined up for the same activation time, for various reasons, but we were likely to all overlap at some point.</p>
<p>I decided to do Carn Mor, and was going to climb it starting from the <a href="https://www.openstreetmap.org/way/119437626">Lecht Mine car park</a>, which leads to the Lecht Mine or the Lecht well.</p>
<p>I was one of the latest activators, and on my drive over, I stopped near Corgarff castle to chase Fraser on GM/ES-023 - a complete for me. Then continued further up the road to a layby near the ski centre to chase Mike on GM/ES-068.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="carn-mor-10.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Mine in the distance"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-029/carn-mor-10.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Mine in the distance"></a></p>
<figcaption>Mine in the distance</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="carn-mor-9.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="A hideen history"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-029/carn-mor-9.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A hideen history"></a></p>
<figcaption>A hideen history</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The route follows the path by the stream towards to mine but before you reach it, you turn off and climb up Càrn Liath. The stream has to be crossed, and it’s not a wee burn, nor a great river, but enough to make you ponder the best way over. I went with a running jump at what seemed like a narrow part and felt that was a close call right at the start!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="carn-mor-8.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="View back towards the car park"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-029/carn-mor-8.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="View back towards the car park"></a></p>
<figcaption>View back towards the car park</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The track kicks up on gradient pretty quick, and you climb the 300m elevation in about 1.6km. You’re now at virtually the summit height but still with 3 km to go, with some ups and downs on the way.</p>
<p>The aerial maps show plenty of peat hags on the way up to the top of the first hill but I seemed to manage to avoid them. It was, however, not going to be the case the whole way, and once beyond the nice path next to the fence does one face them.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="carn-mor-6.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Follow the fence"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-029/carn-mor-6.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Follow the fence"></a></p>
<figcaption>Follow the fence</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="carn-mor-5.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="Peat Hags!"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-029/carn-mor-5.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Peat Hags!"></a></p>
<figcaption>Peat Hags!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The south side of the hags seemed easier (as I tried on the North on the way back) and once I got past them I wasn’t really paying attention to the map and continued to follow the track up the next hill. Only to realise this was an unnecessary detour. However, in my detour, I’d managed to avoid some more compared to taking the direct route, so I think a middle ground between going up the summit and the straight line route is best (this is what I’ve added to <a href="https://www.sotamaps.org/tracks">sotamaps</a>.)</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="carn-mor-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="Final path ahead"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-029/carn-mor-4.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Final path ahead"></a></p>
<figcaption>Final path ahead</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>That was the last false summit, and now the end was in sight.</p>
<p>As you can see, the weather was absolutely lovely - also just like the last time Gerald didn’t visit. A slight breeze but nothing much. After not too much longer the trig appeared in sight.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="carn-mor-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7" title="Summit"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-029/carn-mor-3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Summit"></a></p>
<figcaption>Summit</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I managed a 2m summit to summit with Mike, and Simon but Fraser had left, and so he called me from the peat hags on Brown Cow Hill.I setup on HF and had a go on 40m.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="carn-mor-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-8" title="Station"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-029/carn-mor-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Station"></a></p>
<figcaption>Station</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I seemed to be getting rf on the audio on 40m, with the KX2 on the trig point. I moved it onto the ground that that seemed to cure things. Once 40m had dried up, I considered moving to other bands but then I also considered a second summit - given it was such a nice day and I’d driven all this way. So I packed up and headed back - eating my noodles as I walked.</p>
<p>I did try and take a more direct route on the way back but the peat hags said no, and I was better off just following the route I took out.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="carn-mor-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-9" title="Stream crossing again"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-029/carn-mor-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Stream crossing again"></a></p>
<figcaption>Stream crossing again</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-029/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 07 Mar 2025 12:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-029/carn-mor-2.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Sgor Mor</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-026/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="sgor-mor-10.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Linn of Dee path"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-026/sgor-mor-10.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Linn of Dee path"></a></p>
<figcaption>Linn of Dee path</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I was up way too late last night trying to decide what summit or summits to do today. Given it’s still winter bonus period, I’m incentivise to activate the most number of summits, and so I was trying to see if I could do two summits. Generally, two summits in a day is perfectly reasonable, however, I was constrained by school pick up and drop off, and the fact that I’ve done just about all the nearby 2-pointers already. I looked around for another summit, and eventually decided up <a href="https://sotl.as/summits/GM/ES-026">Sgor Mor</a>. Tim, G5OLD, recently activated this summit at the start of the month when we did our <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-025/">GM/ES activation day</a>. However, prior to Tim, no-one had activated this summit since 2021. There’s a good reason for this!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="sgor-mor-13.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Heather for miles and miles"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-026/sgor-mor-13.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Heather for miles and miles"></a></p>
<figcaption>Heather for miles and miles</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I looked at different routes for it, to make sure I could make it up and back in time. The most common way, is to go up the side to the ridge and walk along it to the summit. It’s rough going, as there’s no path for 90% of the route and it’s all heather and bog. There’s also a very long deer fence which just ends in the middle of nowhere. Although there were piles of new fencing laid out on the ground, so I guess they’re coming back to finish it. An alternative route, is to cycle along the Dee, past white bridge and the Chest of Dee, until you’re at the base of the summit. This should only take about 30 minutes, and then you have a steep climb up to the summit. It minimises the amount of heather and bog to cross, and overall it looked shorter. The downside of this, is that you don’t get to do the ridge walk. If the weather is clear, then the ridge walk offers outstanding views into the high Munros of the central Cairngorms - Devil’s Point, Cairn Toul, Ben Macdui, the lot. As well as views to the south to various Munros and high tops. As the weather was looking nice, I decided to go with the ridge walk. I did put the bike in the car, just in case weather was different in Braemar than in Aberdeen, but I didn’t use it.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="sgor-mor-14.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Looking west along the Dee"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-026/sgor-mor-14.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Looking west along the Dee"></a></p>
<figcaption>Looking west along the Dee</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>My route had a short section of the track along the Dee but then turned off and headed straight into the heather, up a steep slope. My route was just a straight line to the ridge, and I tried to follow it as best as possible, whilst avoiding particularly boggy parts. I’d set a pace marker on my watch to do the ascent in 1:20 (vs.&nbsp;the 1:30 predicted) just to give me a bit of extra time to setup and to eat my lunch. It wasn’t quite the perfect blue skies of Aberdeen, but it was clear enough. Once I eventually reached the ridge, I did have great views into Luibeg, <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-013/">Carn a’Mhaim</a>, and all along to Devil’s Point. I kept thinking I was nearly there, and summits I’d seen on the walk up must be my destination, but no, there was still plenty of ridge to walk along!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="sgor-mor-9.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Ridge path"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-026/sgor-mor-9.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Ridge path"></a></p>
<figcaption>Ridge path</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Higher up, the heather did revert to the alpine, low to ground plants, and so it made it easier to walk. However, now quite a cold wind was blowing, and at times there was snow. The snow on the high tops had much reduced since I was on Carn na Drochaide. I did make it to the summit in 1:20, giving me 10 minutes before my alert time. There’s a little cairn at the top, and that was enough to shelter in and keep out of the wind. The stones weren’t very big, so it wasn’t ideal for supporting the mast but I managed to wedge it in and got the job done anyway.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="sgor-mor-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="Summit in sight"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-026/sgor-mor-3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Summit in sight"></a></p>
<figcaption>Summit in sight</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="sgor-mor-7.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="At the top"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-026/sgor-mor-7.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="At the top"></a></p>
<figcaption>At the top</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="sgor-mor-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7" title="Station"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-026/sgor-mor-4.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Station"></a></p>
<figcaption>Station</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I did quickly try 2m, to see if I could get the local SOTA lads. I hadn’t even spotted but a random chap from south of Edinburgh came back to my CQ call straight away. We had a brief chat, and then I could hear Fraser, MM0EFI, calling. I called back but he couldn’t hear me. I didn’t want to be spending too long on the summit, it was cold and I’d only allocated myself 30 minutes, so got started setting up HF.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="sgor-mor-8.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-8" title="Devil’s Point, Cairn Toul behind, in the cloud"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-026/sgor-mor-8.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Devil’s Point, Cairn Toul behind, in the cloud"></a></p>
<figcaption>Devil’s Point, Cairn Toul behind, in the cloud</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I started on 40m, and there was a quick pile up, although it seemed to quickly disappear, without me working that many. A S2S from the Lake District called me too, and I ended up working a few on 40m before being able to hear the locals. I moved to 20m and continued to work stations calling in. I had seen a Czech summit and did call to them but they couldn’t hear me over the others, again, not wanting to hang around I didn’t keep trying. However, one caller told me they were calling me - and I couldn’t hear them for the other chasers - and so I eventually managed to work him on OK/MO-074 around 1,600 km away. By now it was 12:30, and I needed to get going. So I packed up, finished my lunch and headed off. Simon asked if I was doing 2m, so I did get the HT out and make another QSO with him. I probably didn’t have time for that but nevermind.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="sgor-mor-6.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-9" title="Looking south west"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-026/sgor-mor-6.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Looking south west"></a></p>
<figcaption>Looking south west</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I did meet someone else coming up, just as I was leaving the summit, that was surprising given the remoteness of this Corbett. I didn’t volunteer to chat as I had to get back to the car. Going back along the ridge was fine, but soon I had to turn back into the heather and bog. It was downhill all the way, but still tricky to move at speed. Eventually, I came to the hill slope down to the Dee path. It’s quite steep and going down is as difficult as going up. The heather means you can crash your way down, but just being careful of large boulders, or even small cliff faces. I did make it back onto the path at 13:30 - the time I was hoping to leave the car park - and so tried to walk and jog my way back to the car.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="sgor-mor-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-10" title="Steep hill down to the Dee path"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-026/sgor-mor-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Steep hill down to the Dee path"></a></p>
<figcaption>Steep hill down to the Dee path</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Back to the car 15 minutes later and then off home. The duration of the drive varies so much depending on if you get stuck behind tourists, or Land Rover drivers doing 45 mph for miles and miles, but I managed to make reasonable time and get back with 5 minutes to spare!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="sgor-mor-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-11" title="Ridge views"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-026/sgor-mor-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Ridge views"></a></p>
<figcaption>Ridge views</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>It’s quite a remote 4-pointer, and a good amount of work to get there, so it’s not surprising I’m the 9th activator of the summit. If you’re visiting the area, there are so many other hills to do before you’d do this. One for the completionists I think! However, it does offer some of the best views, and so perhaps shouldn’t be overlooked so quickly.</p>
<p>I’ve now past 350 points, and I’m hoping to get to 400 before my Lake District trip in April, as then this should see me over the half way mark to Mountain Goat! My rate will slow down once winter bonus period ends, although with the weather getting warmer (hopefully) there’ll be opportunities to do some of the big hills again, maybe trying different routes if I did them last year. There are a few overnight trips I’d like to do from home - so I can start the walks early in the morning - but finding time with everything else in the family is always the challenge! Still, those hills aren’t going anywhere. ⛰️</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-026/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-026/sgor-mor-8.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Lord Arthur’s Hill</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-062/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Another early morning start, and another opportunity for a pre-work SOTA activation. Last week I did <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-060/">Coiliochbhar</a>, but it was too wet and windy to go across the road to do Lord Arthur’s Hill, and so I decided to head back today. The weather was lovely, clear blue skies, and only a gentle breeze.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="lord-arthur-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Early morning"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-062/lord-arthur-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Early morning"></a></p>
<figcaption>Early morning</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="lord-arthur-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Looking back down the track"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-062/lord-arthur-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Looking back down the track"></a></p>
<figcaption>Looking back down the track</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p><a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-062/">Last time around</a>, I climbed it from the south, through the estate. I thought I’d try another route, and a common one is from the east. The track up is very straight forward and it’s a land rover track the whole way up.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="lord-arthur-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Looking across to the big Cairngorm summits"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-062/lord-arthur-3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Looking across to the big Cairngorm summits"></a></p>
<figcaption>Looking across to the big Cairngorm summits</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I was trying to time my summit with Fraser, MM0EFI, who was across the other side of the Cairngorm’s National Park trying to tick off some of those summits. He ended up being later than me, so I did HF first, and then hung around for a bit to get a S2S with him over 2m.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="lord-arthur-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Station"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-062/lord-arthur-4.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Station"></a></p>
<figcaption>Station</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I’d setup on the trig point, as I didn’t think there’d be anyone else coming up this morning. I used the random wire, starting on 40m and then moving to 20m. Both bands were good this morning.</p>
<p><a href="lord-arthur-5.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-062/lord-arthur-5.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p><a href="lord-arthur-6.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-062/lord-arthur-6.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="lord-arthur-7.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7" title="At the top!"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-062/lord-arthur-7.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="At the top!"></a></p>
<figcaption>At the top!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-062/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-062/lord-arthur-4.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Coiliochbhar Hill</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-060/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>The weather forecast wasn’t great for today, with high winds and rain all day. I had planned on doing both Coiliochbhar and Lord Arthur’s Hill together, as they’re very close, and I did this <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-062/">last</a> <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-060/">time</a>. However, given the weather I decided to just do Coiliochbhar, this is because it has a nice wooded area right by the summit in the activation zone, and I could shelter there.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="coil-7.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Car park view"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-060/coil-7.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Car park view"></a></p>
<figcaption>Car park view</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I thought I’d take a different route from last time, and was setting off south of the summit, and walking through some wind farm and forestry tracks before heading across the hill until you come to some woods again. The OS map appears to name the first summit you climb as Coiliochbhar hill, and there’s a cairn at the top, but then there’s a trig point and another cairn further on at the high spot which is where the SOTA summit is. It does mean the AZ is pretty large, and you have lots of space in the wooded area at the top to setup and be within the activation zone.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="coil-6.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Forestry tracks"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-060/coil-6.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Forestry tracks"></a></p>
<figcaption>Forestry tracks</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="coil-5.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Summit in sight"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-060/coil-5.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Summit in sight"></a></p>
<figcaption>Summit in sight</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Much of the way at the start is in the shelter of trees and so the wind and rain didn’t seem that bad. It wasn’t really raining that much but I could hear the wind blowing around me. You do cross a field between wooded areas, and here the wind was more noticeable. It was behind me, so that helped! There seems to be a very new, and large, roadway that’s been built in the second wooded area which isn’t on the map. I didn’t notice this fact at first as I assumed the path I was following was the track, but then I noticed I was heading downhill and away from the summit. I checked the map and realised I should’ve turned off and be following what looked like a fire break between the trees. I backtracked and found the turn off, following a very old and unused looking land rover track. This took me between the trees and then out onto the first summit of the hill. Being higher and exposed again the wind was back. This time it was much stronger, perhaps also picking up as the day went on. I would not want to be setting up a station in the open.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="coil-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Track between the trees"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-060/coil-4.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Track between the trees"></a></p>
<figcaption>Track between the trees</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="coil-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="Wooded summit"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-060/coil-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Wooded summit"></a></p>
<figcaption>Wooded summit</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I reached the next wooded section, and now I was in the activation zone. Plenty of nice shelter under the trees! I found a spot and setup the mast, making sure to thread the antenna wire between the branches so I could get it out and across. I tied it to a tree on the other side of the path. I tried 40m first, and had a few contacts. I noticed my KX2 was only outputting 5W, so it must’ve been a few activations since I last charged it. I switched to 20m and found a few more contacts. Quite a few 44s or 33 reports, so not as good as Wednesday. Not sure if all the trees around absorb some rf? Anyway, enough contacts for the day as things were starting to get quite wet.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="coil-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="Station in the trees"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-060/coil-3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Station in the trees"></a></p>
<figcaption>Station in the trees</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I went to look at the summit, even though I’ve recently been there, but several trees were blown down across the path, and I didn’t really need to see it that much to bother scrambling over them. Fraser was doing an activation later to celebrate his retirement today, and I wanted to make sure I was home and set up for that, so just headed back. This time into the wind and rain, which now seemed to be coming down more than when I started. I was well waterproofed up and was dry the whole time, apart from my face. If I sound like I’m complaining, I’m not, it was quite the exhilarating walk in the wet and wild. Whilst I was in the trees, and lulled into thinking things were calm, I thought about doing Lord Arthur’s, but as soon as I was back out in the exposed fields I realised that was not a good idea. There is a small cairn you can hide inside on LA but not much cover from the rain. I don’t mind cold, or wind but wet is just a pain with the radio. I also probably don’t want to do all the nearby summits too soon anyway!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="coil-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7" title="Smile!"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-060/coil-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Smile!"></a></p>
<figcaption>Smile!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-060/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-060/coil-2.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Kerloch</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-059/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="kerloch-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Kerloch in the clouds"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-059/kerloch-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Kerloch in the clouds"></a></p>
<figcaption>Kerloch in the clouds</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Since my daughter has swim training at 6:30am, I thought I’d make use of the early start and do a quick, local summit before work. The weather this week hasn’t been and isn’t looking that great, and this morning seemed like as good as it was going to get anyway. Kerloch hill climb is quite quick, but it has a long path leading up to it.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="kerloch-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Path"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-059/kerloch-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Path"></a></p>
<figcaption>Path</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Once I started going uphill, there was some snow on the path, and I followed the track of person and their dog the whole way. It was quite windy but whilst in the woods and behind the hill it was still for me.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="kerloch-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="The bad track"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-059/kerloch-3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="The bad track"></a></p>
<figcaption>The bad track</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Last time I did <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-059/">Kerloch</a>, it was a glorious day, and the path was washed away back then. Now the snow had covered it but you could still tell it was terribly washed away still. It also had the added benefit of fallen trees across the track.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="kerloch-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Fallen trees"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-059/kerloch-4.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Fallen trees"></a></p>
<figcaption>Fallen trees</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>No doubt when this snow melts, it’s not going to help the situation. I made my way up the track at a steady pace, generally keeping to one side where the snow was less and also less like to slide off a boulder. Once I came out of the forest then the wind started to pick up. There were deep drifts across the track and several times I was waist deep in snow having not realised it was so deep.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="kerloch-7.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="Up we go"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-059/kerloch-7.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Up we go"></a></p>
<figcaption>Up we go</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Continuing on, I suddenly see the trig and cairn appear out of the clouds and realised I’ve reached the top. The trig had some lovely ice feathers on it but I didn’t stand around too long to admire as the wind was pretty strong and cold.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="kerloch-6.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="Summit in sight"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-059/kerloch-6.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Summit in sight"></a></p>
<figcaption>Summit in sight</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="kerloch-5.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7" title="Frozen Trig"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-059/kerloch-5.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Frozen Trig"></a></p>
<figcaption>Frozen Trig</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="kerloch-8.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-8" title="At the top"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-059/kerloch-8.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="At the top"></a></p>
<figcaption>At the top</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I settled in the cairn, which did give some shelter from the wind. I had the carbon 6 mast wedged in the rocks and ran my wire up and then across to the fence posts. It did slip off the top of the antenna in the wind, so I used the other hole in my mast fitting to friction fit it on. This hole is larger, and so goes lower down the mast, but I can trap the wire in it up against the mast to wedge it in place. Useful when the wind blows the mast right over. What should be an inverted sloper-L, ends up looking like a twin C arrangement!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="kerloch-10.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-9" title="Station setup"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-059/kerloch-10.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Station setup"></a></p>
<figcaption>Station setup</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I started on 40m, and turned randomly to M7CUW doing a POTA activation. He was coming in 59, and so was I when replying. I spotted and go Chris, 2M0RVZ, a local, but then there was nothing on 40m. The Aberdeenshire SOTA chat group said there was a CME the night before so probably why. I switched to 20m, hoping that would be better and I’d at least get my 4, and that ended up being pretty good with contacts into Greece and Canaries, and most people giving me a 55 report. Content with that, and getting cold hands, I packed away and tried 2m with the HT and RH770 antenna. Fraser and Simon were both ready and we had a quick chat on 2m. Now it was time to get out of the wind, down the hill and off to work!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="kerloch-9.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-10" title="Back down we go"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-059/kerloch-9.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Back down we go"></a></p>
<figcaption>Back down we go</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="qsos" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="qsos">QSOs</h3>
<div class="cell">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code hidden" id="cb1" data-startfrom="0" data-source-offset="-0" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode js code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode javascript" style="counter-reset: source-line -1;"><span id="cb1-0">L <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="pp" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">require</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">'leaflet@1.9.4'</span>)</span>
<span id="cb1-1"></span>
<span id="cb1-2"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">// Load the CSV file</span></span>
<span id="cb1-3">qsosData <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">FileAttachment</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"qsos.json"</span>)<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">json</span>()</span>
<span id="cb1-4"></span>
<span id="cb1-5"></span>
<span id="cb1-6"></span>
<span id="cb1-7">map <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> {</span>
<span id="cb1-8"></span>
<span id="cb1-9">  <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">// Extract my station details</span></span>
<span id="cb1-10">  <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">const</span> myLocation <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> {</span>
<span id="cb1-11">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">lat</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> qsosData<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">my_lat</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-12">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">lon</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> qsosData<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">my_lon</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-13">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">callsign</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> qsosData<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">my_callsign</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-14">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">sota</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> qsosData<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">my_sota</span></span>
<span id="cb1-15">  }<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-16"></span>
<span id="cb1-17">  <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">// Function to assign colors based on the band</span></span>
<span id="cb1-18">  <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">function</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">getBandColor</span>(band) {</span>
<span id="cb1-19">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">const</span> bandColors <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> {</span>
<span id="cb1-20">      <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"40m"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"DarkBlue"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-21">      <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"20m"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Green"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-22">      <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"15m"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Orange"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-23">      <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"10m"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Red"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-24">      <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"2m"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Purple"</span></span>
<span id="cb1-25">    }<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-26">    <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">return</span> bandColors[band] <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">||</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Gray"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span> <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">// Default color if the band is missing</span></span>
<span id="cb1-27">  }</span>
<span id="cb1-28"></span>
<span id="cb1-29">  <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">let</span> container <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> DOM<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">element</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">'div'</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> { <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">style</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">`width:</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">${</span>width<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">px;height:</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">${</span>width<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">/</span><span class="fl" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1.6</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">px`</span> })<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-30">  <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">yield</span> container<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-31"></span>
<span id="cb1-32">  <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">let</span> map <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> L<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">map</span>(container)<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">setView</span>([myLocation<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">lat</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> myLocation<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">lon</span>]<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">7</span>)<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-33">  <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">let</span> osmLayer <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> L<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">tileLayer</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">'https://{s}.tile.openstreetmap.org/{z}/{x}/{y}.png'</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> {</span>
<span id="cb1-34">      <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">attribution</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">'&amp;copy; &lt;a href="https://www.openstreetmap.org/copyright"&gt;OpenStreetMap&lt;/a&gt; contributors'</span></span>
<span id="cb1-35">  })<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">addTo</span>(map)<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-36"></span>
<span id="cb1-37">  <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">// Custom icons</span></span>
<span id="cb1-38">  <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">const</span> myIcon <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> L<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">icon</span>({</span>
<span id="cb1-39">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">iconUrl</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"/flag.png"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-40">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">iconSize</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> [<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">25</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">25</span>]<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-41">  })<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-42"></span>
<span id="cb1-43">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">const</span> sotaIcon <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> L<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">icon</span>({</span>
<span id="cb1-44">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">iconUrl</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"/summit.png"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-45">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">iconSize</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> [<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">25</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">25</span>]<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-46">  })<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-47"></span>
<span id="cb1-48">    <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">// Add marker for my station</span></span>
<span id="cb1-49">  L<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">marker</span>([myLocation<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">lat</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> myLocation<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">lon</span>]<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> { <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">icon</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> myIcon })</span>
<span id="cb1-50">    <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">bindPopup</span>(<span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">`</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">${</span>myLocation<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">callsign</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;br&gt;SOTA Ref: </span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">${</span>myLocation<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">sota</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">`</span>)</span>
<span id="cb1-51">    <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">addTo</span>(map)<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-52"></span>
<span id="cb1-53"></span>
<span id="cb1-54">  <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">// Add QSO markers</span></span>
<span id="cb1-55">  qsosData<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">qsos</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">forEach</span>(({ lat<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> lon<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> callsign<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> band<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> distance_km<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> sota_ref }) <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">=&gt;</span> {</span>
<span id="cb1-56">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">const</span> isSOTA <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> sota_ref <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">!==</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">""</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-57">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">const</span> markerIcon <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> isSOTA <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">?</span> sotaIcon <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">null</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span> <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">// Use SOTA icon if reference exists</span></span>
<span id="cb1-58">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">const</span> color <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">getBandColor</span>(band)<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-59"></span>
<span id="cb1-60">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">const</span> marker <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> isSOTA</span>
<span id="cb1-61">      <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">?</span> L<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">marker</span>([lat<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> lon]<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> { <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">icon</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> markerIcon }) <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">// SOTA markers get an icon</span></span>
<span id="cb1-62">      <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> L<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">circleMarker</span>([lat<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> lon]<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> {</span>
<span id="cb1-63">          <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">radius</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">6</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-64">          <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">color</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> color<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-65">          <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">fillColor</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> color<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-66">          <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">fillOpacity</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="fl" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">0.8</span></span>
<span id="cb1-67">        })<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-68"></span>
<span id="cb1-69">    marker<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">bindPopup</span>(</span>
<span id="cb1-70">      <span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">`Callsign: </span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">${</span>callsign<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;br&gt;Band: </span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">${</span>band<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;br&gt;Distance: </span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">${</span>distance_km<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> km`</span> <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">+</span></span>
<span id="cb1-71">      (isSOTA <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">?</span> <span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">`&lt;br&gt;SOTA Ref: &lt;a href="https://sotl.as/summits/</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">${</span>sota_ref<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">" target="_blank"&gt;</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">${</span>sota_ref<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;/a&gt;`</span> <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">""</span>)</span>
<span id="cb1-72">    )<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">addTo</span>(map)<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-73">  })<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-74"></span>
<span id="cb1-75">}</span></code></pre></div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-display">
<div>
<div id="ojs-cell-1-1" data-nodetype="declaration">

</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-display">
<div>
<div id="ojs-cell-1-2" data-nodetype="declaration">

</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-display">
<div>
<div id="ojs-cell-1-3" data-nodetype="declaration">

</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-059/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-059/kerloch-5.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Creag Nan Gabhar</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-022/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="creag-nan-gabhar-9.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Summit, or at least what is visible from the road"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-022/creag-nan-gabhar-9.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Summit, or at least what is visible from the road"></a></p>
<figcaption>Summit, or at least what is visible from the road</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Last week on the GM/ES activation day, Fraser was on this summit, and so I thought I’d go up and get a complete for me, and Fraser would go up a summit and get a complete for him! (Completing from a summit isn’t necessary but it is much more fun that way!)</p>
<p>Following on from my <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-055/">first summit</a> this morning, I decided to wear some gaiters and take some hiking poles as I was sure there’d be more snow on this summit. Plus it was going to be another trackless ascent over heather and I didn’t want to get soaking boots on this cold day.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="creag-nan-gabhar-8.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Looking back towards Braemar"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-022/creag-nan-gabhar-8.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Looking back towards Braemar"></a></p>
<figcaption>Looking back towards Braemar</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>There are a couple of routes up, and, as always, given I was on a tight schedule I picked the shortest route. This starts from the side of the road and follows a stream up, and then you turn and face the summit and go straight up to the top. Seems to be a theme today…</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="creag-nan-gabhar-7.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Stream and looking back to the road"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-022/creag-nan-gabhar-7.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Stream and looking back to the road"></a></p>
<figcaption>Stream and looking back to the road</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I expected the route to take me around 50 minutes, and the first 20 minutes were easy going along the stream. Once I crossed over that it was then time to head straight up. The hill side was quite sheltered, and even though the air was colder here (certainly felt a lot colder when I got out the car) than Meall Alvie, the lack of wind meant I was pretty warm on my walk.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="creag-nan-gabhar-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Straight up"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-022/creag-nan-gabhar-4.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Straight up"></a></p>
<figcaption>Straight up</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The route up is whatever you can make it. Sometimes following streams, sometimes over heather and sometimes in grassy patches. There was a surprising lack of any snow here. The ridge you can see in the photo is circa 750m and there’s no a single flake. Compared to Meall Alvie where there was snow around 500m, but I guess it’s in the trees and this gets full sun as a south facing slope. I did have a sit down at one point as it’s a bit of a slog, I suppose I had time extra too. Turning around, I was greeted with lovely views to the south of the higher hills all covered in snow.</p>
<p><a href="creag-nan-gabhar-5.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-022/creag-nan-gabhar-5.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p>I pushed on and made it to the top around the 50 minute mark. The top is quite a broad plateau with several cairns, and I relied on my watch to tell me which was the actual summit. Not that it really matters for SOTA given I have 25 vertical meters to play with. It was patchy blue sky but still great views all around. The only trouble was the icy wind that was strong now I was on the top.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="creag-nan-gabhar-6.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="Looking South"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-022/creag-nan-gabhar-6.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Looking South"></a></p>
<figcaption>Looking South</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="creag-nan-gabhar-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7" title="At the top"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-022/creag-nan-gabhar-3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="At the top"></a></p>
<figcaption>At the top</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I picked the largest cairn and put on all the jackets and hats I’d brought! Unfortunately, I only had my thin gloves and so my hands suffered the most. I had about 20 minutes before Fraser was due to arrive, so I wanted to do HF first and then be ready on 2m when he arrived. I setup again on 40m, and called CQ. The band was a little better for me this time. I did stop and then run around for a while to warm up, before going back to the radio for a few more QSOs.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="creag-nan-gabhar-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-8" title="Station"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-022/creag-nan-gabhar-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Station"></a></p>
<figcaption>Station</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>With 11 on 40m, I packed up and setup the slim G for 2m. I’d just spotted on 2m, when Fraser did the same. So I jumped to his frequency and we had a wee chat. With that done, I was also done! I packed up and headed off back the way I came. Fraser was stuck on 3 QSOs, and was equally cold on his summit, so I dug out the HT with the RH-770 and gave him a call on the club callsign. He did manage two more afterwards. Once I was over the ridge and heading back down, I was out of the wind and my hands started to warm up…and burn up!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="creag-nan-gabhar-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-9" title="Looking North"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-022/creag-nan-gabhar-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Looking North"></a></p>
<figcaption>Looking North</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I was glad I took the poles, as they were useful for the steep descent, without them I suspect I’d have been rolling down the mountain. Back to the car, shovel down my super noodles, and then headed home. I made it back by 3pm, with enough time to get changed, make a cup of tea (cooled down with cold water!) and then head over to the school in time for pick up. 🚸</p>
<p>I think next time I come here, I’ll take the longer, but shallower gradient route…at least I hope it’s shallower! There’s only a month left of winter bonus, where the objective is to activate as many summits as possible - as long as they’re 2 or more pointers. So that means four more Fridays, and possibly a bonus day that I’ll take off. The tricky part is choosing which summits to do. I want to complete all the GM/ES summits, but should I also repeat some I’ve already done during winter bonus period as I can do multiple in one day. Some of it does depend on the weather, so I’ll see what’s next. 🏔️</p>
<section id="qsos" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="qsos">QSOs</h3>
<div class="cell">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code hidden" id="cb1" data-startfrom="0" data-source-offset="-0" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode js code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode javascript" style="counter-reset: source-line -1;"><span id="cb1-0">L <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="pp" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">require</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">'leaflet@1.9.4'</span>)</span>
<span id="cb1-1"></span>
<span id="cb1-2"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">// Load the CSV file</span></span>
<span id="cb1-3">qsosData <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">FileAttachment</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"qsos.json"</span>)<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">json</span>()</span>
<span id="cb1-4"></span>
<span id="cb1-5"></span>
<span id="cb1-6"></span>
<span id="cb1-7">map <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> {</span>
<span id="cb1-8"></span>
<span id="cb1-9">  <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">// Extract my station details</span></span>
<span id="cb1-10">  <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">const</span> myLocation <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> {</span>
<span id="cb1-11">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">lat</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> qsosData<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">my_lat</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-12">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">lon</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> qsosData<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">my_lon</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-13">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">callsign</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> qsosData<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">my_callsign</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-14">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">sota</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> qsosData<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">my_sota</span></span>
<span id="cb1-15">  }<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-16"></span>
<span id="cb1-17">  <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">// Function to assign colors based on the band</span></span>
<span id="cb1-18">  <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">function</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">getBandColor</span>(band) {</span>
<span id="cb1-19">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">const</span> bandColors <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> {</span>
<span id="cb1-20">      <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"40m"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"DarkBlue"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-21">      <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"20m"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Green"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-22">      <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"15m"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Orange"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-23">      <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"10m"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Red"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-24">      <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"2m"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Purple"</span></span>
<span id="cb1-25">    }<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-26">    <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">return</span> bandColors[band] <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">||</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Gray"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span> <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">// Default color if the band is missing</span></span>
<span id="cb1-27">  }</span>
<span id="cb1-28"></span>
<span id="cb1-29">  <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">let</span> container <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> DOM<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">element</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">'div'</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> { <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">style</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">`width:</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">${</span>width<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">px;height:</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">${</span>width<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">/</span><span class="fl" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1.6</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">px`</span> })<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-30">  <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">yield</span> container<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-31"></span>
<span id="cb1-32">  <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">let</span> map <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> L<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">map</span>(container)<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">setView</span>([myLocation<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">lat</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> myLocation<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">lon</span>]<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">7</span>)<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-33">  <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">let</span> osmLayer <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> L<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">tileLayer</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">'https://{s}.tile.openstreetmap.org/{z}/{x}/{y}.png'</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> {</span>
<span id="cb1-34">      <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">attribution</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">'&amp;copy; &lt;a href="https://www.openstreetmap.org/copyright"&gt;OpenStreetMap&lt;/a&gt; contributors'</span></span>
<span id="cb1-35">  })<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">addTo</span>(map)<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-36"></span>
<span id="cb1-37">  <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">// Custom icons</span></span>
<span id="cb1-38">  <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">const</span> myIcon <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> L<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">icon</span>({</span>
<span id="cb1-39">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">iconUrl</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"/flag.png"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-40">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">iconSize</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> [<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">25</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">25</span>]<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-41">  })<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-42"></span>
<span id="cb1-43">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">const</span> sotaIcon <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> L<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">icon</span>({</span>
<span id="cb1-44">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">iconUrl</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"/summit.png"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-45">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">iconSize</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> [<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">25</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">25</span>]<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-46">  })<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-47"></span>
<span id="cb1-48">    <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">// Add marker for my station</span></span>
<span id="cb1-49">  L<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">marker</span>([myLocation<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">lat</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> myLocation<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">lon</span>]<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> { <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">icon</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> myIcon })</span>
<span id="cb1-50">    <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">bindPopup</span>(<span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">`</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">${</span>myLocation<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">callsign</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;br&gt;SOTA Ref: </span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">${</span>myLocation<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">sota</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">`</span>)</span>
<span id="cb1-51">    <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">addTo</span>(map)<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-52"></span>
<span id="cb1-53"></span>
<span id="cb1-54">  <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">// Add QSO markers</span></span>
<span id="cb1-55">  qsosData<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">qsos</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">forEach</span>(({ lat<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> lon<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> callsign<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> band<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> distance_km<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> sota_ref }) <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">=&gt;</span> {</span>
<span id="cb1-56">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">const</span> isSOTA <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> sota_ref <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">!==</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">""</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-57">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">const</span> markerIcon <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> isSOTA <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">?</span> sotaIcon <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">null</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span> <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">// Use SOTA icon if reference exists</span></span>
<span id="cb1-58">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">const</span> color <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">getBandColor</span>(band)<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-59"></span>
<span id="cb1-60">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">const</span> marker <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> isSOTA</span>
<span id="cb1-61">      <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">?</span> L<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">marker</span>([lat<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> lon]<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> { <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">icon</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> markerIcon }) <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">// SOTA markers get an icon</span></span>
<span id="cb1-62">      <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> L<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">circleMarker</span>([lat<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> lon]<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> {</span>
<span id="cb1-63">          <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">radius</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">6</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-64">          <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">color</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> color<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-65">          <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">fillColor</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> color<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-66">          <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">fillOpacity</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="fl" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">0.8</span></span>
<span id="cb1-67">        })<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-68"></span>
<span id="cb1-69">    marker<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">bindPopup</span>(</span>
<span id="cb1-70">      <span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">`Callsign: </span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">${</span>callsign<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;br&gt;Band: </span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">${</span>band<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;br&gt;Distance: </span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">${</span>distance_km<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> km`</span> <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">+</span></span>
<span id="cb1-71">      (isSOTA <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">?</span> <span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">`&lt;br&gt;SOTA Ref: &lt;a href="https://sotl.as/summits/</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">${</span>sota_ref<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">" target="_blank"&gt;</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">${</span>sota_ref<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;/a&gt;`</span> <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">""</span>)</span>
<span id="cb1-72">    )<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">addTo</span>(map)<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-73">  })<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-74"></span>
<span id="cb1-75">}</span></code></pre></div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-display">
<div>
<div id="ojs-cell-1-1" data-nodetype="declaration">

</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-display">
<div>
<div id="ojs-cell-1-2" data-nodetype="declaration">

</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-display">
<div>
<div id="ojs-cell-1-3" data-nodetype="declaration">

</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-022/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2025 13:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-022/creag-nan-gabhar-1.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Meall Alvie</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-055/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>First of two summits of the day. The main summit being <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-022/">GM/ES-022</a>, but I decided to do this one first, as Fraser wanted a S2S with me on 022 for a complete for him. He was working until lunchtime, so it made sense for me to do this one first. It’s a short route, that starts from the Keiloch car park on the Invercauld estate.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="meall-alvie-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Estate track"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-055/meall-alvie-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Estate track"></a></p>
<figcaption>Estate track</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>You follow the track, then turn off onto a path, however, this path just goes around the summit, and to get to the top you have to just walk up the hill through the trees and heather. Sometimes it’s nice to not just follow a path and to make your own.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="meall-alvie-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Summit in sight"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-055/meall-alvie-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Summit in sight"></a></p>
<figcaption>Summit in sight</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="meall-alvie-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Big military plane that flew over and I just managed to get a photo of"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-055/meall-alvie-3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Big military plane that flew over and I just managed to get a photo of"></a></p>
<figcaption>Big military plane that flew over and I just managed to get a photo of</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>B</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="meall-alvie-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Track up"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-055/meall-alvie-4.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Track up"></a></p>
<figcaption>Track up</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>eing in the trees, this summit would be ideal on a windy day. However, being in the trees means that there isn’t much of a view from the top. Luckily you get some nice views on the way up and down.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="meall-alvie-7.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="Views to the south over the River Dee"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-055/meall-alvie-7.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Views to the south over the River Dee"></a></p>
<figcaption>Views to the south over the River Dee</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Once you leave the track, the route up is pretty steep all the way to the top. The heather doesn’t help and there was still some snow lying on it which also didn’t help. For a 2-pointer, it’s quite the slog.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="meall-alvie-5.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="Straight up"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-055/meall-alvie-5.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Straight up"></a></p>
<figcaption>Straight up</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Upon reaching the top, there isn’t anything of note, other than the ground levels off. I set to work setting up the mast and wire for 40m. Plenty of trees and branches to secure the mast to, although being careful to not get the wire tangled in the trees. I then just draped the other end over a branch to form a nearly straight inverted L. Doing two summits, and aiming to be home in time for school pick up, means I don’t have much time to hang around! I started on 40m and it was quite slow, most contacts reporting heavy QSB. I did manage to make 4 on 40m and considered packing up, but kept going for a fifth and then moved to 20m. 20m was much better, although a loud station popped up just next to me and was drowning me out for many people. As this summit is likely a POTA site or two, I wanted to get at least 10 QSOs for that - not that I spotted on POTA.app. With that done, it was time to pack up and head down and then across to my next summit.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="meall-alvie-6.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7" title="Station in the trees - mast avoiding the overhead branches"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-055/meall-alvie-6.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Station in the trees - mast avoiding the overhead branches"></a></p>
<figcaption>Station in the trees - mast avoiding the overhead branches</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="meall-alvie-8.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-8" title="Still a lovely view on the way down"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-055/meall-alvie-8.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Still a lovely view on the way down"></a></p>
<figcaption>Still a lovely view on the way down</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>With springy heather underfoot, I could bound down the side and be back at the car in about 15 minutes, saving some time on my schedule. A short 15 minute drive through Braemar and down the A93 brought me to my next <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-022/">summit</a>.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-055/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2025 10:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-055/meall-alvie-3.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Introducing wen goat 🐐 app</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2025/wen-goat/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>As you can tell from this blog, I’ve been doing a lot of <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota.html">SOTA summits</a>. The big award is at 1,000 points, when you can proudly claim to be a Mountain Goat. Since I started being more serious about this late last year, I’ve been looking at how long it will take me to achieve MG. My friend Tim, G5OLD, has also been looking at the same thing - although he’s much closer than I am! It seemed to me like a wee webapp was needed for this and thus “<a href="https://wengoat.streamlit.app/">wen goat</a>” was born!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="thumb.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="wen goat?"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2025/wen-goat/thumb.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="wen goat?"></a></p>
<figcaption>wen goat?</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>It’s a python app and hosted on streamlit.io, as that makes everything very easy. Ideally, I’d integrate it into this blog but maybe another time. You enter your callsign and then it looks up your activation data (assuming you’re a SOTA activator and have an account and logged your activations) and then it plots these plus a few trends forwards towards the 1,000 point mark.</p>
<p>It’s gone through a few iterations, including contributions by <a href="https://www.qrz.com/db/OE5JFE">OE5JFE</a>, which was very kind of Joe. It shows you your historical performance, and gives you the option to enter your own expected future performance. Further down the page it allows you to set a target date when you want to achieve MG by, and then it’ll tell you how many points per week you need to get there. <a href="https://reflector.sota.org.uk/t/introducing-the-wen-goat-app/37331?u=gm5alx">Several people</a> have tried it out and had fun with it. My most recent update included doing the calculation for subsequent Mountain Goat awards, i.e.&nbsp;those that already have 1,000 points or more and are working their way towards the next 1,000 mark.</p>
<p>I had fun making it, and Streamlit makes it so easy to get online. Visit it at this link, and here’s an embedded version below - although it’s not the greatest experience that way.</p>
<iframe src="https://wengoat.streamlit.app?embed=true" style="height: 900px; width: 100%;">
</iframe>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <category>programming</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2025/wen-goat/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2025/wen-goat/thumb.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="136" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Tap o’Noth</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-054/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Fraser, MM0EFI, and Tim, G5OLD, were going out to <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-019/">Conachcraig</a> today and asked who else was going out. I was keen to go (as always) but lots of family activities were going to limit me. So what better way to solve it, than to bring the kids with me!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="tap-onoth-9.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Up to the top"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-054/tap-onoth-9.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Up to the top"></a></p>
<figcaption>Up to the top</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>It was a bit cold, around 0-1 °C when we set off. Everyone was excited to go at home, but when we got there everyone was complaining! We made reasonable time to the top, and I setup the tent for the kids so they could keep out of the wind and have their snack in comfort. I setup on 2m by the edge of the fort remains to try and keep out of the wind.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="tap-onoth-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Tent and station"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-054/tap-onoth-4.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Tent and station"></a></p>
<figcaption>Tent and station</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Fraser and Tim just came on 2m as I was setup and so had two summit to summits with them. Sounded a lot snowier and colder with them. Then had a succession of chasers on 2m. I did hear someone on a HEMA summit work Fraser but I never worked them. My HT was on dual channel monitoring and I kept hearing someone talking on 145.150 but I couldn’t remember how to turn that off or change the secondary channel, so that was distracting. I was going to setup on HF but it was a bit cold and the kids probably wouldn’t have lasted much longer. Also seems the base of the tent isn’t waterproof anymore and several were complaining of wet areas.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="tap-onoth-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Selfie on the trig"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-054/tap-onoth-3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Selfie on the trig"></a></p>
<figcaption>Selfie on the trig</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I packed up and we had some photos, then set off back to the car park. No convincing people to walk this time, everyone was running down the hill and I was the last one!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="tap-onoth-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Descent. Ben Rinnes in the distance."><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-054/tap-onoth-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Descent. Ben Rinnes in the distance."></a></p>
<figcaption>Descent. Ben Rinnes in the distance.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Back home for lunch and then a Sunday afternoon at home.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-054/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-054/tap-onoth-5.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Carn na Drochaide</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-025/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Originally, Gerald, G4OIG, was coming to visit the area and do some summits, so we’d arranged all to go out today. However, Gerald ended up not being able to make it, but after posting on the <a href="https://reflector.sota.org.uk/t/gm-es-winter-activity-day-friday-7-february-2025/37340">forum</a>, we now had quite a list of summits expected to be activated in GM. It could possibly be the most at once in Scotland.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="alerts.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Alerts the day before"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-025/alerts.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Alerts the day before"></a></p>
<figcaption>Alerts the day before</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I set off after dropping the kids and school and headed out to my summit. Carn na Drochaide is right at the “end of the line”, so it took a while to get to the start. There are a few routes up and I was taking the shortest, as I was trying to meet the 11:30 time.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="Drochaide-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Summit on the right"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-025/Drochaide-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Summit on the right"></a></p>
<figcaption>Summit on the right</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The weather was absolutely spectacular! Chilly, around -5°C at the car park, but no wind and lovely blue skies. The path is generally good, although comes and goes in places - or maybe that’s me from the path - and some heather bashing is required. Carn Dearg ascent gives you a bit of a false hope, as you then descend a little before climbing the final summit. As I was heading up 2m was starting up as the others were on their summits and calling CQ. I checked in with the <a href="https://www.qrz.com/db/GM0ESS">GM0ESS</a> callsign, and said I’d be at the top soon. The views were starting to become very good as I climbed, with all the big peaks becoming visible.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="Drochaide-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="High Cairngorms - Cairn Toul being most noticeable in the centre"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-025/Drochaide-4.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="High Cairngorms - Cairn Toul being most noticeable in the centre"></a></p>
<figcaption>High Cairngorms - Cairn Toul being most noticeable in the centre</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="Drochaide-11.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Path to the top"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-025/Drochaide-11.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Path to the top"></a></p>
<figcaption>Path to the top</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I reached the AZ just after 11:30, and heard G5OLD calling on 2m, and so he was the first S2S in the log. After our brief chat I was at the summit cairn, and started working the other activators. Four in the log on the HT and whip, and I started to setup the slim g on the mast. I’d also brought the Kenwood V71 for a little more power.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="Drochaide-9.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="2m Station"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-025/Drochaide-9.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="2m Station"></a></p>
<figcaption>2m Station</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>With virtually no wind on the summit, a few rocks held the 7m mast in place and I had the sun warming my back as the air was still cold. I started setting up HF, had the wire up and just about to plug in when I heard @MM0FMF on 2m, who I’d spoken to before I was at the summit, and was glad to make a contact, as my first complete of the day. I then carried on on 2m working three more summits, including MM7DCD on what sounded like a very wet and windy Ben Lomond, GM/SS-011. My second complete of the day (after only just <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-ss-011/">activating it</a> in the Christmas holidays). Was also great to get Barry, GM4TOE, on GM/ES-084, the Grandfather of GM/ES…just look at the first activator of pretty much any GM/ES summit.</p>
<p>17 QSOs on 2m of which 12 were summit to summits! So there was at least 13 GM summits today…I wonder if we beat the previous record set in <a href="https://reflector.sota.org.uk/t/gm-es-winter-activity-day-friday-7-february-2025/37340/46">August 2012</a>? I shall look into that later.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="Drochaide-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="Braemar"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-025/Drochaide-3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Braemar"></a></p>
<figcaption>Braemar</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The views from Carn na Drochaide were spectacular…Ben Avon, Beinn a’Bhuird, Beinn Bhreac (not SOTA), Cairn toul, Beinn Bhrotain, and no end to SW which I don’t know what’s what. Plus lovely views down into the Dee valley and Braemar.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="Drochaide-5.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7" title="Looking south"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-025/Drochaide-5.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Looking south"></a></p>
<figcaption>Looking south</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="Drochaide-8.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-8" title="Ben Avon and others to the North"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-025/Drochaide-8.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Ben Avon and others to the North"></a></p>
<figcaption>Ben Avon and others to the North</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Many of us met in Braemar at The Bothy for tea and medals afterwards, this being the first time I’ve met all but two activators!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="Drochaide-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-9" title="The GM SOTA Elite"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-025/Drochaide-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="The GM SOTA Elite"></a></p>
<figcaption>The GM SOTA Elite</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-025/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-025/hams.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Buck</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-039/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Another lovely day and this time a quick outing to The Buck. <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-039/">Not a new summit</a> for me, but a good one on points/hour ratio! The subtitle for this post is <em>The Bog</em>, and even on a cold day like today, it’s still a bog at the bottom. Probably best to do when the ground is frozen, then you’re not hopping from tuft to tuft trying not to get soaked feet.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="buck-7.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Looking up at the summit"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-039/buck-7.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Looking up at the summit"></a></p>
<figcaption>Looking up at the summit</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="buck-8.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Looking back down, in the shadow of the mountain"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-039/buck-8.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Looking back down, in the shadow of the mountain"></a></p>
<figcaption>Looking back down, in the shadow of the mountain</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>It’s a quick one, about 40 minutes to the top. The SOTA chat group were all about and I had a few 2m QSOs with them before I setup my new AX1 for the KX2, to try and use it like a HF HT!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="buck-5.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="At the top"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-039/buck-5.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="At the top"></a></p>
<figcaption>At the top</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="buck-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Ben Rinnes in the distance, the two Convals on the right"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-039/buck-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Ben Rinnes in the distance, the two Convals on the right"></a></p>
<figcaption>Ben Rinnes in the distance, the two Convals on the right</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I was using the AX1 for 20m - it can do 15m and 17m and then 30m/40m with the extension coil. Probably does 10m too. You have a counterpoise wire that trails along the ground - which for 40m is pretty long! I had it attached straight into the BNC connector on the KX2, and I was going to use internal mic. I did wear headphones as it was a bit windy and I wanted to be sure I could hear. The idea was to use it in one hand and then log with the other.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="buck-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="HF HT"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-039/buck-3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="HF HT"></a></p>
<figcaption>HF HT</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>It was my first time, but it was also quite awkward. I hadn’t realised the PTT, XMIT button, was toggled, so I have to press it against to unkey, and the button isn’t in the easiest place to press. I ended up putting my phone on the trig point, holding the KX2 in the right hand and then using my left hand to press the XMIT button, I also had to shelter the KX2 in my shadow to minimise wind noise. Probably would’ve helped if I wasn’t standing right on the summit, and found somewhere sheltered but the whole point was to do it from right at the top! I got used to it, and managed 18 QSOs on 20m.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="buck-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="Pict markings"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-039/buck-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Pict markings"></a></p>
<figcaption>Pict markings</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I don’t think I could’ve done this with the coil for 40m, it would feel very unstable with all that weight on the BNC. I do want to use it again, as it’s quick to setup. I am thinking that perhaps a headset and PTT button might be easiest, one where I could hold it in my hand and use that had to key up. Alternatively, I could get an elbow BNC and set it up on the ground or backpack etc. and just use the regular mic. I’ll try one of these again some other time. Was a good activation and with a quick trot down the hill I was back home in no time.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="buck-6.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7" title="Summit"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-039/buck-6.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Summit"></a></p>
<figcaption>Summit</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="buck-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-8" title="Close up of Pict markings"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-039/buck-4.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Close up of Pict markings"></a></p>
<figcaption>Close up of Pict markings</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Last time I didn’t see the pict markings of the three fish. Not sure how as it was right in front of the summit as you come down! Probably circa 400-900 AD.There is also a small visitor book hidden in one of the walls nearby, that I forgot to look for…so next time!</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-039/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-039/buck-4.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Pressendye</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-047/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>I headed over to Tarland and the Douneside Hotel were I was going to park for the ascent. Fraser, MM0EFI, was off up <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-059/">Kerloch</a> and was going to arrive at 2:30pm. My route up was the longest of the day, and I estimated around an hour to get to the top, and so had to get a march on to make sure I was on time! In the end it only took me 45 minutes but I was quite tired when I got to the top!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="pressendye-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Looking back down the track, across to Mount Keen in the distance"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-047/pressendye-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Looking back down the track, across to Mount Keen in the distance"></a></p>
<figcaption>Looking back down the track, across to Mount Keen in the distance</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The cloud had been moving further east, but so had I, and I was still enjoying the blue skies, particularly if I looked towards Aberdeen. I got a bit lost going through the Tarland trails mountain biking course and ended up walking along some of it and then between it as a few bikes were about. On the way back down I realised I should’ve walked further away from the summit to find the footpath, but on the way up I was trying to take the most direct route possible!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="pressendye-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Pressendye summit ahead"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-047/pressendye-4.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Pressendye summit ahead"></a></p>
<figcaption>Pressendye summit ahead</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="pressendye-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Morven looking very mountain-esk"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-047/pressendye-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Morven looking very mountain-esk"></a></p>
<figcaption>Morven looking very mountain-esk</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The views were still good, I particularly liked <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-018/">Morven</a>. I got to the top just before Fraser was on the summit and I called CQ on my HT. I managed to work him and then 3 more stations around. I had originally thought about setting up HF, but it was getting on and I needed to get home, so with the minimum 4 QSOs to qualify I headed back down the hill and home again. 15 points today, 3 new summits and a complete on Kerloch.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="pressendye-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="At the top"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-047/pressendye-3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="At the top"></a></p>
<figcaption>At the top</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="pressendye-6.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="Nearby cairn"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-047/pressendye-6.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Nearby cairn"></a></p>
<figcaption>Nearby cairn</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The summit does have a nice big cairn, and posts giving plenty of mast and shelter options.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-047/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2025 14:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-047/pressendye-1.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Ben Newe</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-053/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ben-newe-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="This way"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-053/ben-newe-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="This way"></a></p>
<figcaption>This way</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The middle hill of the day and just a short drive from Ladylea. Again, a fairly short route up, following the signs and path. Someone else and their dog had been up before me, as I was following their footsteps the whole way.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ben-newe-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Jets…I promise"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-053/ben-newe-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Jets…I promise"></a></p>
<figcaption>Jets…I promise</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>There were still jet planes flying around and whilst you can’t really see them, this picture has them just at the peak of the hill in the far distance. I didn’t quite manage to zoom in on my phone before they were gone. It’s still a nice view even without them.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ben-newe-6.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Summit in sight"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-053/ben-newe-6.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Summit in sight"></a></p>
<figcaption>Summit in sight</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Once you round the path to the base of the heather hill, you do find there are several paths up to the top. The sign posts take you the longest way around, but there are several tracks leading straight up. So after following the path for a bit, I decided to head across the heather and join one of these tracks leading up to the summit. There are a few trees at the top, so this would be a good summit on a windy day. As with Ladylea, there was hardly any wind at all, and I setup right on the trig.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ben-newe-7.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Views to the north"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-053/ben-newe-7.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Views to the north"></a></p>
<figcaption>Views to the north</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ben-newe-9.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="Station"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-053/ben-newe-9.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Station"></a></p>
<figcaption>Station</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The trig point has a few wooden planks around it, that act like benches, so you can get quite comfy up here, as long as the wind isn’t too cold. I’d called on 2m first, and then moved onto 40m. Not masses of activity but perfectly pleasant enough on both bands getting some contacts. As I spoke with Fraser, MM0EFI, he said he was heading to Kerloch to climb that. I was meant to be doing a summit to summit with him on my next peak, so I quickly got packed up and headed down through the trees on a more direct path back to the car.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ben-newe-8.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="At the top"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-053/ben-newe-8.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="At the top"></a></p>
<figcaption>At the top</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-053/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2025 12:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-053/ben-newe-1.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Ladylea Hill</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-049/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Another day off, and some more SOTA summits to activate! Today I wanted to knock off some 2-pointers with winter bonus that I’ve not climbed before. First on the list was Ladylea Hill. I did have some concerns when driving to Ladylea and droves of tweed men with hounds were scratching around with shotguns looking for turkeys or something. Luckily they were a couple of hills over and I wasn’t going to get shot.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ladylea-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Parking area"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-049/ladylea-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Parking area"></a></p>
<figcaption>Parking area</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>It seems anything west of Morven was covered with snow and Ladylea was one of those. The main concern was parking, and not being able to get the car out once I returned to it. So I just parked on the verge pointing downhill, even though there is a nice off road parking area. The ascent is pretty quick and I was soon on the summit. There was no wind whatsoever and the wire didn’t even flinch on the mast. Whilst it was chilly it was very pleasant in the sun. The clouds were over the high peaks and it did gradually moved east during the day.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ladylea-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Path through the forest"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-049/ladylea-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Path through the forest"></a></p>
<figcaption>Path through the forest</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ladylea-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="A new toy in action"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-049/ladylea-4.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A new toy in action"></a></p>
<figcaption>A new toy in action</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ladylea-5.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="At the top"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-049/ladylea-5.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="At the top"></a></p>
<figcaption>At the top</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The top has a convenient post for securing a mast to. I decided just to do 40m and 2m today and both were active at an easy pace.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ladylea-8.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="Station"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-049/ladylea-8.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Station"></a></p>
<figcaption>Station</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>On the way down from Ladylea, a path leading straight down was too tempting as a shortcut - especially as I still had two more to go. I looked at the map and whilst the path didn’t return to the road, there was just a short stretch of forest to walk through, so I figured “why not”. It started well, making good progress down the hill, until I came to the forest, surrounded by fencing. I did spy a gap under it, which I had to literally crawl through!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ladylea-10.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="Crawl space"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-049/ladylea-10.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Crawl space"></a></p>
<figcaption>Crawl space</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ladylea-9.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7" title="A very old car!"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-049/ladylea-9.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A very old car!"></a></p>
<figcaption>A very old car!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>That was only the start of my problems, as the forest was thick fallen trees, and I had to scramble over and under them to make any progress, but by this time I wasn’t going to go back up the hill now. So I pushed on.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ladylea-11.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-8" title="Fallen trees"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-049/ladylea-11.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Fallen trees"></a></p>
<figcaption>Fallen trees</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Eventually I made it through and out onto the road, where I walked back to the car. Looking at my route and satellite imagery, I do wonder if it would’ve been better to walk further south and avoid the trees. Although at the time I don’t remember it looking clear.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="route.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-9" title="My GPS Tracks"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-049/route.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="My GPS Tracks"></a></p>
<figcaption>My GPS Tracks</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Well on to the next one, Ben Newe!</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-049/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2025 10:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-049/ladylea-8.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>145 Alive Net</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2025/145-alive/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>145 Alive is a scheme to promote 2m activity in the UK. Most of the organisation is done online via a <a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/906901577214402/?locale=en_GB">facebook group</a>. They co-ordinate dates and frequencies of nets that people volunteer to do. This year Chris, 2M0RVZ, and I were going to run a net and park on the Cairn O’Mount. However, the snow gates were still closed this morning and turned out to have fallen trees on the road. We could approach it from the south but we didn’t know the conditions, so changed to Garvock hill near Laurencekirk. At the last 145 Alive event I was on <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-087/">Waughton Hill</a> and called into a couple of nets, this time I was going to be running one!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="snowgates.jpeg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Closed snow gates"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2025/145-alive/snowgates.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Closed snow gates"></a></p>
<figcaption>Closed snow gates</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Chris has a newly converted Land Rover which has a pop up roof, and comfy seating in the back. Plus a heater, kettle, running water… the works! So we were going to spend a couple of hours in that and see who we could get.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="145a-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Setting up"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2025/145-alive/145a-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Setting up"></a></p>
<figcaption>Setting up</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>We were using a slim G up a 10m mast, and I’d brought my 50W Kenwood V71 FM radio. Chris had an ecoflow power bank, although the radio kept restarting when we keyed up, so we swapped to my golf buggy battery. We were set up quickly and then discussed strategy for handling the net. The net was 12-3pm, and at 12:00pm we were ready to call CQ.</p>
<p>We did hear a station down in East Lothian who was overlapping with another net, and also us, on the same frequency but he couldn’t hear us then disappeared.</p>
<p>We were using the new GM/ES SOTA Society callsign of GM0ESS for today - as there were two of us, and our first CQ went out and … nothing 😅</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="operating.jpeg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="GM0ESS operation"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2025/145-alive/operating.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="GM0ESS operation"></a></p>
<figcaption>GM0ESS operation</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>After a while a few stations did start calling in and we managed about 12 in total, even had a couple who could work each other. Many times we had one station to our North and one to our South and they couldn’t hear each other. We also called into the Dundee net and had a couple more contacts there. It was quite relaxed and we chatted and ate and drank in between times. I was glad we weren’t sat out on a hillside, as we’d have packed up after 4 contacts for the summit!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="qsos.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="QSOs"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2025/145-alive/qsos.jpg" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-center figure-img" width="293" alt="QSOs"></a></p>
</figure>
</div>
<figcaption>QSOs</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I had to get back home by 2:30pm, so I left about 1:50pm, Chris kept going for another half an hour but didn’t manage to work anyone else. Either his 10W from his IC-705 wasn’t enough, or just no-one was listening!</p>
<p>Was a fun afternoon, and quite relaxing as there wasn’t really any net to manage 😅 Plus got to check out the fancy Land Rover. The events are usually on Sunday and I can’t always get out then, so not sure if I’ll run one again, or just climb up a hill and call in.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="tea-time.jpeg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="Tea time"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2025/145-alive/tea-time.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Tea time"></a></p>
<figcaption>Tea time</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>2m</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2025/145-alive/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jan 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2025/145-alive/145a-2.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Mount Keen</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-014/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>After <a href="https://reflector.sota.org.uk/t/the-lazy-guide-to-cyprus/37279/19">living it large in Cyprus</a> for a week, with lunchtime beers and drive on summits, Fraser MM0EFI, was looking to do some real walking for fear of turning into another passenger on the Axiom. Earlier in the week he’d asked if anyone was interested in an outing on Wednesday. I was planning on going out Friday but then Fraser pointed out the weather forecast and I rearranged things accordingly.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="weather.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Storm Éowyn"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-014/weather.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Storm Éowyn"></a></p>
<figcaption>Storm Éowyn</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>If you hadn’t guessed, Mount Keen, GM/ES-014, was our destination, and we were climbing from Glen Tanar. This is a longer route than the one from the other side in Glen Esk, however, it’s much nearer both our houses, particularly Fraser’s, and I wanted to try it. It’s a bike and hike route, about an hour of each. You could walk but it’s a long way, about 15 km each way (Glen Esk route is 9 km each way and that feels like a long walk).</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="route.jpeg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Our route"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-014/route.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Our route"></a></p>
<figcaption>Our route</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>0730 was our rendezvous time, and after debating how many layers to wear - it was about -4°C - we set off along the nice tracks.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="m-keen-6.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Headlines and hats needed!"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-014/m-keen-6.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Headlines and hats needed!"></a></p>
<figcaption>Headlines and hats needed!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>It is uphill most of the way, but the gradient is fairly shallow that it’s not a slog. The first part is through a nice forest of Caledonian scots pinewoods and past a frozen loch, although it was still quite dark so not much of it could be admired.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="keen-17.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Frosty landscape"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-014/keen-17.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Frosty landscape"></a></p>
<figcaption>Frosty landscape</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Out of the forest and you’re greeted with the hills surrounding Mount Keen. All the snow in the area has completely gone, with only very minor patches left, and this morning the white was the frost.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="keen-16.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="Lights off; taps off"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-014/keen-16.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Lights off; taps off"></a></p>
<figcaption>Lights off; taps off</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Soon enough Mount Keen came into view, although looked like the summit was in the clouds. Hopefully we wouldn’t be too early and suffer those clouds.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="keen-15.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="Mount Keen coming into view"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-014/keen-15.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Mount Keen coming into view"></a></p>
<figcaption>Mount Keen coming into view</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>We reached the bridge at the base of the climb and decided to leave our bikes here. You could ride/push your bike up the path someway to have a quicker route down but it seemed unnecessary and Fraser told me of a time where he got a puncture doing just this. Preparing for the hike</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="m-keen-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7" title="Preparing for the hike - Mount Keen above my head"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-014/m-keen-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Preparing for the hike - Mount Keen above my head"></a></p>
<figcaption>Preparing for the hike - Mount Keen above my head</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>We’d made good time on the bikes to this point, a few minutes shy of an hour, and set off on foot.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="keen-14.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-8" title="Looking back down"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-014/keen-14.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Looking back down"></a></p>
<figcaption>Looking back down</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Things were going okay for the first 10 minutes but then Fraser seemed to be falling behind and huffing and puffing. Turned out he had bad cramp in his leg and couldn’t shake it off - even a packet of Haribo didn’t cure him. With a few stops we pressed on to the top.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="keen-12.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-9" title="Admiring the view"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-014/keen-12.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Admiring the view"></a></p>
<figcaption>Admiring the view</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="keen-11.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-10" title="Summit in sight"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-014/keen-11.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Summit in sight"></a></p>
<figcaption>Summit in sight</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>As we neared the top, the cloud had lifted and the views all around were stunning. The air was still cold but it was perfectly still.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="keen-9.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-11" title="Made it!"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-014/keen-9.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Made it!"></a></p>
<figcaption>Made it!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The summit was covered in thick frost and a little slippery underfoot. After admiring the views and remarking that even Lochnagar was lacking in snow we started to set up our stations. Fraser was on 2m with his HT and yagi, and I was on HF with the KX2 and 41’ of wire.</p>
<p>Fraser had a good run on 2m FM, with 10 contacts from around Scotland.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="keen-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-12" title="Yakking on a yagi"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-014/keen-4.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Yakking on a yagi"></a></p>
<figcaption>Yakking on a yagi</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="m-keen-7.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-13" title="2m QSOs"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-014/m-keen-7.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="2m QSOs"></a></p>
<figcaption>2m QSOs</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I started on 40m, which was noisy and a bit slow. I then switched to 20m and that was absolutely popping. The pile up was crazy, just a wall of noise coming back to me each time. My particular highlight was a HB9 QSO which was 59 both ways. The other guy tells me he’s running 1.5 kW, and I reply with “10W here!”. I probably could’ve continued for another hour non-stop. I managed to work through about 40 of them before I was too cold and needed to pack up. Thankfully there was still no wind on the summit, otherwise I would’ve stopped after 40m! Fraser had Jack, GM4COX, on when I was finishing up they were having a good yaggin (yakking with a yagi?).</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="m-keen-5.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-14" title="Working the pile up"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-014/m-keen-5.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Working the pile up"></a></p>
<figcaption>Working the pile up</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="m-keen-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-15" title="HF Station"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-014/m-keen-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="HF Station"></a></p>
<figcaption>HF Station</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="hf-qsos.jpeg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-16" title="HF QSOs"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-014/hf-qsos.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="HF QSOs"></a></p>
<figcaption>HF QSOs</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>We hadn’t seen anyone all morning but at the summit a couple of people came by. I was buried on 20m so didn’t look up but Fraser acted as the Mount Keen, Cairngorms and amateur radio tour guide. Particularly to a guy who had just climbed Mount Keen as his first Munro.</p>
<p>We’d been on the summit about an hour and both content with our activations. The joy of radio seemed to have cured Fraser’s ailments and he was hopping and skipping again. Plus it was downhill all the way, and the bike section only took 30 minutes on the way back. This time we could admire the loch and forest before returning to the car park.</p>
<p>Fraser invited me back for lunch, and promptly called Mo to let her know to set the table for more one, and “yes, he is normal”. After admiring the array of Land Rovers in Fraser’s drive, we were ushered into the dining room for a very fine lunch. Think that’s two lunches I owe you now!</p>
<p>Unfortunately, I had to pull myself free of the sofa, fire and tea to head back home to do my half day’s work.</p>
<p><a href="keen-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-17"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-014/keen-1.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p><a href="keen-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-18"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-014/keen-2.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p><a href="keen-6.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-19"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-014/keen-6.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p>Whilst the route is longer, and more to ascend, I think I like it more than Glen Esk. The view of Mount Keen as you approach, the forest cycle, and the nice track up to the top are the best parts. Plus I suspect it’s slightly quieter than the other way.</p>
<p><a href="https://reflector.sota.org.uk/t/from-lazy-to-overly-keen/37299">Also on the reflector.</a></p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-014/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-014/m-keen-6.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Bennachie</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-061/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Back in March last year, I set out on my <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-061/">first SOTA activation</a>. As it’s a new year, you can activate summits again and get the points, and with the winter bonus a 2-point summit is 5 point. As I was heading out in the afternoon, this was a nice quick one for the morning.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bennachie-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Looking east on the way up"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-061/bennachie-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Looking east on the way up"></a></p>
<figcaption>Looking east on the way up</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The weather was nicer this time than my last climb, although still windy on the top. I took the same route up from the Back O’Bennachie car park. There were quite a few other walkers about this morning. Chris, 2M0RVZ, was heading up Ben Aigan, <a href="https://sotl.as/summits/GM/ES-069">GM/ES-069</a>, so hopefully we’d get a 2m summit to summit.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bennachie-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="At the top"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-061/bennachie-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="At the top"></a></p>
<figcaption>At the top</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>It’s a quick route up and I was ready about 10:15, just in time for Chris arriving for our 2m QSO. Simon, GM4JXP, was also on 2m but he couldn’t hear Chris and was keen to get a complete for Aigan. The wind was strong on the summit, so I was looking for somewhere sheltered and also out the main route with other walkers coming and going. I found a good spot just south of the summit down the side of the summit.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bennachie-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Station setup"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-061/bennachie-3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Station setup"></a></p>
<figcaption>Station setup</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Just like my first visit, I brought the G90, although this time a much small and lighter battery! Another chase by Fraser, 5B/M0EFI, from Cyprus on 15m, we compared his EFHW and the 41’ wire. Both were about the same and probably more variation in propagation than anything else, but perhaps the 41’ was slightly better. I moved onto 40m, and then 20m before looking for other summits to chase. I had a nice QSO with Esther, EI4KT, who was out in the north of Ireland (not to be confused with Northern Ireland!) By this time I’d been on the air about an hour and whilst I was in a sheltered spot I was getting cold and stiff legs.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bennachie-5.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="View to Mither Tap"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-061/bennachie-5.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="View to Mither Tap"></a></p>
<figcaption>View to Mither Tap</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="qsos" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="qsos">QSOs</h3>
<div class="cell">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code hidden" id="cb1" data-startfrom="0" data-source-offset="-0" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode js code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode javascript" style="counter-reset: source-line -1;"><span id="cb1-0">L <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="pp" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">require</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">'leaflet@1.9.4'</span>)</span>
<span id="cb1-1"></span>
<span id="cb1-2"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">// Load the CSV file</span></span>
<span id="cb1-3">qsosData <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">FileAttachment</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"qsos.json"</span>)<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">json</span>()</span>
<span id="cb1-4"></span>
<span id="cb1-5"></span>
<span id="cb1-6"></span>
<span id="cb1-7">map <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> {</span>
<span id="cb1-8"></span>
<span id="cb1-9">  <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">// Extract my station details</span></span>
<span id="cb1-10">  <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">const</span> myLocation <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> {</span>
<span id="cb1-11">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">lat</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> qsosData<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">my_lat</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-12">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">lon</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> qsosData<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">my_lon</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-13">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">callsign</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> qsosData<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">my_callsign</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-14">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">sota</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> qsosData<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">my_sota</span></span>
<span id="cb1-15">  }<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-16"></span>
<span id="cb1-17">  <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">// Function to assign colors based on the band</span></span>
<span id="cb1-18">  <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">function</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">getBandColor</span>(band) {</span>
<span id="cb1-19">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">const</span> bandColors <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> {</span>
<span id="cb1-20">      <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"40m"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"DarkBlue"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-21">      <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"20m"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Green"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-22">      <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"15m"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Orange"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-23">      <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"10m"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Red"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-24">      <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"2m"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Purple"</span></span>
<span id="cb1-25">    }<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-26">    <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">return</span> bandColors[band] <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">||</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Gray"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span> <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">// Default color if the band is missing</span></span>
<span id="cb1-27">  }</span>
<span id="cb1-28"></span>
<span id="cb1-29">  <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">let</span> container <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> DOM<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">element</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">'div'</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> { <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">style</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">`width:</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">${</span>width<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">px;height:</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">${</span>width<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">/</span><span class="fl" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1.6</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">px`</span> })<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-30">  <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">yield</span> container<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-31"></span>
<span id="cb1-32">  <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">let</span> map <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> L<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">map</span>(container)<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">setView</span>([myLocation<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">lat</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> myLocation<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">lon</span>]<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">7</span>)<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-33">  <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">let</span> osmLayer <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> L<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">tileLayer</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">'https://{s}.tile.openstreetmap.org/{z}/{x}/{y}.png'</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> {</span>
<span id="cb1-34">      <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">attribution</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">'&amp;copy; &lt;a href="https://www.openstreetmap.org/copyright"&gt;OpenStreetMap&lt;/a&gt; contributors'</span></span>
<span id="cb1-35">  })<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">addTo</span>(map)<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-36"></span>
<span id="cb1-37">  <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">// Custom icons</span></span>
<span id="cb1-38">  <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">const</span> myIcon <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> L<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">icon</span>({</span>
<span id="cb1-39">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">iconUrl</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"/flag.png"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-40">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">iconSize</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> [<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">25</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">25</span>]<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-41">  })<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-42"></span>
<span id="cb1-43">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">const</span> sotaIcon <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> L<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">icon</span>({</span>
<span id="cb1-44">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">iconUrl</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"/summit.png"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-45">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">iconSize</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> [<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">25</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">25</span>]<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-46">  })<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-47"></span>
<span id="cb1-48">    <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">// Add marker for my station</span></span>
<span id="cb1-49">  L<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">marker</span>([myLocation<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">lat</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> myLocation<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">lon</span>]<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> { <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">icon</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> myIcon })</span>
<span id="cb1-50">    <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">bindPopup</span>(<span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">`</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">${</span>myLocation<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">callsign</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;br&gt;SOTA Ref: </span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">${</span>myLocation<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">sota</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">`</span>)</span>
<span id="cb1-51">    <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">addTo</span>(map)<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-52"></span>
<span id="cb1-53"></span>
<span id="cb1-54">  <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">// Add QSO markers</span></span>
<span id="cb1-55">  qsosData<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">qsos</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">forEach</span>(({ lat<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> lon<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> callsign<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> band<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> distance_km<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> sota_ref }) <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">=&gt;</span> {</span>
<span id="cb1-56">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">const</span> isSOTA <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> sota_ref <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">!==</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">""</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-57">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">const</span> markerIcon <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> isSOTA <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">?</span> sotaIcon <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">null</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span> <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">// Use SOTA icon if reference exists</span></span>
<span id="cb1-58">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">const</span> color <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">getBandColor</span>(band)<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-59"></span>
<span id="cb1-60">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">const</span> marker <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> isSOTA</span>
<span id="cb1-61">      <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">?</span> L<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">marker</span>([lat<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> lon]<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> { <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">icon</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> markerIcon }) <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">// SOTA markers get an icon</span></span>
<span id="cb1-62">      <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> L<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">circleMarker</span>([lat<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> lon]<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> {</span>
<span id="cb1-63">          <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">radius</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">6</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-64">          <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">color</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> color<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-65">          <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">fillColor</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> color<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-66">          <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">fillOpacity</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="fl" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">0.8</span></span>
<span id="cb1-67">        })<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-68"></span>
<span id="cb1-69">    marker<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">bindPopup</span>(</span>
<span id="cb1-70">      <span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">`Callsign: </span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">${</span>callsign<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;br&gt;Band: </span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">${</span>band<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;br&gt;Distance: </span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">${</span>distance_km<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> km`</span> <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">+</span></span>
<span id="cb1-71">      (isSOTA <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">?</span> <span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">`&lt;br&gt;SOTA Ref: &lt;a href="https://sotl.as/summits/</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">${</span>sota_ref<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">" target="_blank"&gt;</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">${</span>sota_ref<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;/a&gt;`</span> <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">""</span>)</span>
<span id="cb1-72">    )<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">addTo</span>(map)<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-73">  })<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-74"></span>
<span id="cb1-75">}</span></code></pre></div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-display">
<div>
<div id="ojs-cell-1-1" data-nodetype="declaration">

</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-display">
<div>
<div id="ojs-cell-1-2" data-nodetype="declaration">

</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-display">
<div>
<div id="ojs-cell-1-3" data-nodetype="declaration">

</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-061/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-061/bennachie-2.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Knockan</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-081/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>The final summit of the day. As I had time, I thought I’d do this one as I knew it would be a quick walk. There are a few 1 pointers in this area which I’d like to activate eventually, and this helped tick it off my list.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="knockan-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Looking across to Ben Rinnes"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-081/knockan-4.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Looking across to Ben Rinnes"></a></p>
<figcaption>Looking across to Ben Rinnes</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>It seems a popular spot for dog walkers as the “car park” was nearly full when I arrived. A wind farm has been built on the hill, so it’s made up roads nearly to the top. It’s also a very gentle gradient of hardly any climb, so pushing the very limits of the definition of summit. It took less than 20 minutes to reach the summit, a few well balanced stones.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="knockan-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="At the top"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-081/knockan-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="At the top"></a></p>
<figcaption>At the top</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I went back to the road to make use of the snow markers as a support for the mast and setup. Fraser wanted to try and make a contact as he wanted Knockan for a complete (where you activate and chase a summit). Quite the lengths to get a complete whilst on holiday in Cyprus! We tried 15m to start and he was pretty good this time, 43 to me. After that I started looking around for other summits but I was wasting time and just wanted to get it qualified and done, so moved to 20m and soon had a nice run for 5 minutes before calling it quits. Takes longer to setup and take down the station than get to the top! Back to the car in no time and away home.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="knockan-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Roadside station"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-081/knockan-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Roadside station"></a></p>
<figcaption>Roadside station</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="qsos" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="qsos">QSOs</h3>
<div class="cell">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code hidden" id="cb1" data-startfrom="0" data-source-offset="-0" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode js code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode javascript" style="counter-reset: source-line -1;"><span id="cb1-0">L <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="pp" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">require</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">'leaflet@1.9.4'</span>)</span>
<span id="cb1-1"></span>
<span id="cb1-2"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">// Load the CSV file</span></span>
<span id="cb1-3">qsosData <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">FileAttachment</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"qsos.json"</span>)<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">json</span>()</span>
<span id="cb1-4"></span>
<span id="cb1-5"></span>
<span id="cb1-6"></span>
<span id="cb1-7">map <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> {</span>
<span id="cb1-8"></span>
<span id="cb1-9">  <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">// Extract my station details</span></span>
<span id="cb1-10">  <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">const</span> myLocation <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> {</span>
<span id="cb1-11">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">lat</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> qsosData<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">my_lat</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-12">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">lon</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> qsosData<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">my_lon</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-13">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">callsign</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> qsosData<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">my_callsign</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-14">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">sota</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> qsosData<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">my_sota</span></span>
<span id="cb1-15">  }<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-16"></span>
<span id="cb1-17">  <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">// Function to assign colors based on the band</span></span>
<span id="cb1-18">  <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">function</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">getBandColor</span>(band) {</span>
<span id="cb1-19">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">const</span> bandColors <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> {</span>
<span id="cb1-20">      <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"40m"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"DarkBlue"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-21">      <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"20m"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Green"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-22">      <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"15m"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Orange"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-23">      <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"10m"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Red"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-24">      <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"2m"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Purple"</span></span>
<span id="cb1-25">    }<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-26">    <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">return</span> bandColors[band] <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">||</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Gray"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span> <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">// Default color if the band is missing</span></span>
<span id="cb1-27">  }</span>
<span id="cb1-28"></span>
<span id="cb1-29">  <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">let</span> container <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> DOM<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">element</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">'div'</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> { <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">style</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">`width:</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">${</span>width<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">px;height:</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">${</span>width<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">/</span><span class="fl" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1.6</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">px`</span> })<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-30">  <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">yield</span> container<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-31"></span>
<span id="cb1-32">  <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">let</span> map <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> L<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">map</span>(container)<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">setView</span>([myLocation<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">lat</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> myLocation<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">lon</span>]<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">7</span>)<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-33">  <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">let</span> osmLayer <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> L<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">tileLayer</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">'https://{s}.tile.openstreetmap.org/{z}/{x}/{y}.png'</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> {</span>
<span id="cb1-34">      <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">attribution</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">'&amp;copy; &lt;a href="https://www.openstreetmap.org/copyright"&gt;OpenStreetMap&lt;/a&gt; contributors'</span></span>
<span id="cb1-35">  })<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">addTo</span>(map)<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-36"></span>
<span id="cb1-37">  <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">// Custom icons</span></span>
<span id="cb1-38">  <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">const</span> myIcon <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> L<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">icon</span>({</span>
<span id="cb1-39">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">iconUrl</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"/flag.png"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-40">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">iconSize</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> [<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">25</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">25</span>]<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-41">  })<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-42"></span>
<span id="cb1-43">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">const</span> sotaIcon <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> L<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">icon</span>({</span>
<span id="cb1-44">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">iconUrl</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"/summit.png"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-45">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">iconSize</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> [<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">25</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">25</span>]<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-46">  })<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-47"></span>
<span id="cb1-48">    <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">// Add marker for my station</span></span>
<span id="cb1-49">  L<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">marker</span>([myLocation<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">lat</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> myLocation<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">lon</span>]<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> { <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">icon</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> myIcon })</span>
<span id="cb1-50">    <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">bindPopup</span>(<span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">`</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">${</span>myLocation<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">callsign</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;br&gt;SOTA Ref: </span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">${</span>myLocation<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">sota</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">`</span>)</span>
<span id="cb1-51">    <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">addTo</span>(map)<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-52"></span>
<span id="cb1-53"></span>
<span id="cb1-54">  <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">// Add QSO markers</span></span>
<span id="cb1-55">  qsosData<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">qsos</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">forEach</span>(({ lat<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> lon<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> callsign<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> band<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> distance_km<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> sota_ref }) <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">=&gt;</span> {</span>
<span id="cb1-56">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">const</span> isSOTA <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> sota_ref <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">!==</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">""</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-57">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">const</span> markerIcon <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> isSOTA <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">?</span> sotaIcon <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">null</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span> <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">// Use SOTA icon if reference exists</span></span>
<span id="cb1-58">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">const</span> color <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">getBandColor</span>(band)<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-59"></span>
<span id="cb1-60">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">const</span> marker <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> isSOTA</span>
<span id="cb1-61">      <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">?</span> L<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">marker</span>([lat<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> lon]<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> { <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">icon</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> markerIcon }) <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">// SOTA markers get an icon</span></span>
<span id="cb1-62">      <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> L<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">circleMarker</span>([lat<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> lon]<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> {</span>
<span id="cb1-63">          <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">radius</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">6</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-64">          <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">color</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> color<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-65">          <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">fillColor</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> color<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-66">          <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">fillOpacity</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="fl" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">0.8</span></span>
<span id="cb1-67">        })<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-68"></span>
<span id="cb1-69">    marker<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">bindPopup</span>(</span>
<span id="cb1-70">      <span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">`Callsign: </span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">${</span>callsign<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;br&gt;Band: </span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">${</span>band<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;br&gt;Distance: </span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">${</span>distance_km<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> km`</span> <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">+</span></span>
<span id="cb1-71">      (isSOTA <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">?</span> <span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">`&lt;br&gt;SOTA Ref: &lt;a href="https://sotl.as/summits/</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">${</span>sota_ref<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">" target="_blank"&gt;</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">${</span>sota_ref<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;/a&gt;`</span> <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">""</span>)</span>
<span id="cb1-72">    )<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">addTo</span>(map)<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-73">  })<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-74"></span>
<span id="cb1-75">}</span></code></pre></div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-display">
<div>
<div id="ojs-cell-1-1" data-nodetype="declaration">

</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-display">
<div>
<div id="ojs-cell-1-2" data-nodetype="declaration">

</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-display">
<div>
<div id="ojs-cell-1-3" data-nodetype="declaration">

</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-081/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 15:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-081/knockan-3.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Little Conval</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-057/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>After packing up from it’s bigger sibling, Meikle Conval, I set off towards Little Conval. Little meaning 18m shorter. The route is straight forward, follow the path down Meikle and then up Little. The activation area is quite large and there are several cairns on the top. Not sure if the cairn I stood at was the summit but close enough!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="l-conval-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Little Conval from Meikle"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-057/l-conval-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Little Conval from Meikle"></a></p>
<figcaption>Little Conval from Meikle</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="l-conval-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="At the summit with Ben Rinnes behind"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-057/l-conval-3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="At the summit with Ben Rinnes behind"></a></p>
<figcaption>At the summit with Ben Rinnes behind</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The wind was still strong and there was even less shelter on this summit. I spotted a tree a little down the side of the hill, which looked ideal for a mast support and perhaps a wind break. I setup by it, and enjoyed looking out at the two hills I’d already climbed. The wind did stop at times and it was really quite warm when it did.</p>
<p>Fraser was back at his hotel after his activation and wanted to try and chase. We tried 10m but nothing and then 15m. I only called CQ once and a Polish guy jumped in and had a chat for a bit! It took a few goes with Fraser but eventually just managed a QSO, although somewhat supported by the WhatsApp chat to say if we could hear anything or not. I went back to 10m and tried it, getting a couple of contacts, then back on 15m before chasing a Spanish summit, EA6/MA-005 and deciding that was enough.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="l-conval-5.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Tree supported station"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-057/l-conval-5.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Tree supported station"></a></p>
<figcaption>Tree supported station</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>There are two routes back, one is back up and over Meikle Conval again, and the second is around the side of it and along the road. I think the over the hill route is shorter and maybe quicker but I decided to go around. It did end with about 1-1.5km along the road, which was a bit boring. The RAF mountain rescue group were just returning to the road, after they must’ve done the big loop over Ben Rinnes and towards Baby’s Hill and back to the road.</p>
<p>As I was back in good time, I decided to tick off one of the local 1-pointers.</p>
<section id="qsos" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="qsos">QSOs</h3>
<div class="cell">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code hidden" id="cb1" data-startfrom="0" data-source-offset="-0" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode js code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode javascript" style="counter-reset: source-line -1;"><span id="cb1-0">L <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="pp" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">require</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">'leaflet@1.9.4'</span>)</span>
<span id="cb1-1"></span>
<span id="cb1-2"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">// Load the CSV file</span></span>
<span id="cb1-3">qsosData <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">FileAttachment</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"qsos.json"</span>)<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">json</span>()</span>
<span id="cb1-4"></span>
<span id="cb1-5"></span>
<span id="cb1-6"></span>
<span id="cb1-7">map <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> {</span>
<span id="cb1-8"></span>
<span id="cb1-9">  <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">// Extract my station details</span></span>
<span id="cb1-10">  <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">const</span> myLocation <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> {</span>
<span id="cb1-11">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">lat</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> qsosData<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">my_lat</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-12">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">lon</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> qsosData<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">my_lon</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-13">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">callsign</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> qsosData<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">my_callsign</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-14">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">sota</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> qsosData<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">my_sota</span></span>
<span id="cb1-15">  }<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-16"></span>
<span id="cb1-17">  <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">// Function to assign colors based on the band</span></span>
<span id="cb1-18">  <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">function</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">getBandColor</span>(band) {</span>
<span id="cb1-19">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">const</span> bandColors <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> {</span>
<span id="cb1-20">      <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"40m"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"DarkBlue"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-21">      <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"20m"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Green"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-22">      <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"15m"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Orange"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-23">      <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"10m"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Red"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-24">      <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"2m"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Purple"</span></span>
<span id="cb1-25">    }<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-26">    <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">return</span> bandColors[band] <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">||</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Gray"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span> <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">// Default color if the band is missing</span></span>
<span id="cb1-27">  }</span>
<span id="cb1-28"></span>
<span id="cb1-29">  <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">let</span> container <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> DOM<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">element</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">'div'</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> { <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">style</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">`width:</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">${</span>width<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">px;height:</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">${</span>width<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">/</span><span class="fl" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1.6</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">px`</span> })<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-30">  <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">yield</span> container<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-31"></span>
<span id="cb1-32">  <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">let</span> map <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> L<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">map</span>(container)<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">setView</span>([myLocation<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">lat</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> myLocation<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">lon</span>]<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">7</span>)<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-33">  <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">let</span> osmLayer <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> L<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">tileLayer</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">'https://{s}.tile.openstreetmap.org/{z}/{x}/{y}.png'</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> {</span>
<span id="cb1-34">      <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">attribution</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">'&amp;copy; &lt;a href="https://www.openstreetmap.org/copyright"&gt;OpenStreetMap&lt;/a&gt; contributors'</span></span>
<span id="cb1-35">  })<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">addTo</span>(map)<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-36"></span>
<span id="cb1-37">  <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">// Custom icons</span></span>
<span id="cb1-38">  <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">const</span> myIcon <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> L<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">icon</span>({</span>
<span id="cb1-39">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">iconUrl</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"/flag.png"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-40">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">iconSize</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> [<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">25</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">25</span>]<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-41">  })<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-42"></span>
<span id="cb1-43">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">const</span> sotaIcon <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> L<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">icon</span>({</span>
<span id="cb1-44">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">iconUrl</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"/summit.png"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-45">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">iconSize</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> [<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">25</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">25</span>]<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-46">  })<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-47"></span>
<span id="cb1-48">    <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">// Add marker for my station</span></span>
<span id="cb1-49">  L<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">marker</span>([myLocation<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">lat</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> myLocation<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">lon</span>]<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> { <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">icon</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> myIcon })</span>
<span id="cb1-50">    <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">bindPopup</span>(<span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">`</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">${</span>myLocation<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">callsign</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;br&gt;SOTA Ref: </span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">${</span>myLocation<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">sota</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">`</span>)</span>
<span id="cb1-51">    <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">addTo</span>(map)<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-52"></span>
<span id="cb1-53"></span>
<span id="cb1-54">  <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">// Add QSO markers</span></span>
<span id="cb1-55">  qsosData<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">qsos</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">forEach</span>(({ lat<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> lon<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> callsign<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> band<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> distance_km<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> sota_ref }) <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">=&gt;</span> {</span>
<span id="cb1-56">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">const</span> isSOTA <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> sota_ref <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">!==</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">""</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-57">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">const</span> markerIcon <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> isSOTA <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">?</span> sotaIcon <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">null</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span> <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">// Use SOTA icon if reference exists</span></span>
<span id="cb1-58">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">const</span> color <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">getBandColor</span>(band)<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-59"></span>
<span id="cb1-60">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">const</span> marker <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> isSOTA</span>
<span id="cb1-61">      <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">?</span> L<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">marker</span>([lat<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> lon]<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> { <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">icon</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> markerIcon }) <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">// SOTA markers get an icon</span></span>
<span id="cb1-62">      <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> L<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">circleMarker</span>([lat<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> lon]<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span> {</span>
<span id="cb1-63">          <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">radius</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">6</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-64">          <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">color</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> color<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-65">          <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">fillColor</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> color<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb1-66">          <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">fillOpacity</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="fl" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">0.8</span></span>
<span id="cb1-67">        })<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-68"></span>
<span id="cb1-69">    marker<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">bindPopup</span>(</span>
<span id="cb1-70">      <span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">`Callsign: </span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">${</span>callsign<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;br&gt;Band: </span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">${</span>band<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;br&gt;Distance: </span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">${</span>distance_km<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> km`</span> <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">+</span></span>
<span id="cb1-71">      (isSOTA <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">?</span> <span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">`&lt;br&gt;SOTA Ref: &lt;a href="https://sotl.as/summits/</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">${</span>sota_ref<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">" target="_blank"&gt;</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">${</span>sota_ref<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="vs" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;/a&gt;`</span> <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">""</span>)</span>
<span id="cb1-72">    )<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">addTo</span>(map)<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-73">  })<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-74"></span>
<span id="cb1-75">}</span></code></pre></div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-display">
<div>
<div id="ojs-cell-1-1" data-nodetype="declaration">

</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-display">
<div>
<div id="ojs-cell-1-2" data-nodetype="declaration">

</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-display">
<div>
<div id="ojs-cell-1-3" data-nodetype="declaration">

</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-057/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 12:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2025/gm-es-057/l-conval-5.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
