<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>📻 GM5ALX Radio</title>
<link>https://gm5alx.uk/</link>
<atom:link href="https://gm5alx.uk/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>So many rabbit holes, you’ll struggle to find ground</description>
<generator>quarto-1.5.57</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Sun, 29 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Waughton Hill</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-087/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>The <a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/906901577214402/?locale=en_GB">145 Alive!</a> event was planned for today between 1-3pm, which I wanted to join in with. Should be the perfect time to activate a summit on 2m! I had have the three little kids with me for the day, so it had to be a easy summit. Particularly, as I wanted to bring up the tent and lunch and things for them, to keep them entertained whilst I was on the air. The previous times I’ve brought them, I’ve only been about 20 minutes at most and trying to go much longer would be tricky. Eventually, I want to qualify all the GM/ES summits, and so Waughton hill is on my list. It’s quite out of the way with nothing else nearby, so it’s a trip in itself and for one point, I’m not wasting a day off on it! It’s also the lowest summit in GM/ES, and seemed perfect for our adventure.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="Waughton1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="White Horse"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-087/Waughton1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="White Horse"></a></p>
<figcaption>White Horse</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The path up is short, although does cross a field full of cows, and you soon find yourself by the white horse. Walk by its head and you’re on the top of the rise, and heading towards the old hunter’s cottage. The actual summit is a bit further away, requiring you to go down and up the side of the hill again. However, the hunter’s cottage is in the activation zone and the kids thought we’d reached the top and started playing in the house. There was also a nice piece of grass without any sheep or animal droppings on it for the tent I’d brought. The tent and mast went up easily enough and lunch and various toys were unloaded into the tent. It was about 12:55 and I wanted to be on the air for the start of the event, so swallowed down my rolls and setup the IC-705.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="Waughton2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Station setup"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-087/Waughton2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Station setup"></a></p>
<figcaption>Station setup</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I’ve not long had the IC-705 and whilst it is very simple to use, sometimes I get into some modes or settings that I don’t know how to get out of. Today I was already on 2m FM but would the VFO change the frequency? No.&nbsp;First I was worried I’d bashed it in my bag and the dial was broken, then thought perhaps I’d selected 10 or 100 Hz increment but that didn’t seem to matter. I ended up just pressing stuff and then going to band and choosing 144 MHz again seemed to fix it. Phew!</p>
<p>It was nice having the waterfall to see is there was any activity and there certainly was some! I knew MM0EFI and MM0RFN were going up Ben Macdui and Glas Maol respectively but not sure if they’d got to the summit in time. Fraser was supposed to be on 145.250, so I tuned to it and heard Bill, GM0NRT, talking to someone but couldn’t hear the other end. I was worried I could’ve hear Fraser on Ben Macdui, but turned out was just someone else. Tuning around, I heard a guy down at the car park by <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-085/">Hill of Garvock</a> and ended up qualifying the summit with those on his net. I managed to work four summit to summits, two on Ben Macdui, Glas Maol and then Morven. I heard a station down in East Lothian calling on 145.500 but he didn’t hear my reply. Afte rabout an hour, I had 10 QSOs and thought it was about time we packed up.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="Waughton3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Off to Aden Country Park"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-087/Waughton3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Off to Aden Country Park"></a></p>
<figcaption>Off to Aden Country Park</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>We headed back down, and went to <a href="https://adencountrypark.org.uk/">Aden Country Park</a> for some more fun. Turned out to be an old timey tractor fair and there were loads of them on the roads as we drove there.</p>
<p>Was a fun day all round, and nice to join in with this event. Maybe next time I’ll try for a higher summit!</p>
<p>The guys up Ben Macdui had a <a href="https://reflector.sota.org.uk/t/carn-amhaim-gm-es-013-ben-macdui-gm-es-001-slightly-broken/36399">fun trip.</a>. Not jealous in the slightest…😅 Also afterwards, Chris, 2M0RVZ, was boasting about his points compared to mine…challenge accepted!</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-087/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 29 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-087/145-alive.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>An Socach</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-038/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Fraser, MM0EFI, messaged asking who wanted to do a Munro midweek, and I thought it was a good opportunity to go. He also rallied Chris, 2M0RVZ, and Simon, GM4JXP. I decided to go up An Socach, whilst Fraser and Chris were going up Carn a’Gheoidh, and Simon on Glas Maol. A notice was posted on the <a href="https://reflector.sota.org.uk/t/upcoming-2m-activity-wednesday-25th-september/36335/65">reflector</a>, and several others were keen to go up summits in Scotland and England. Later on we came to realise that the time posted on the reflector and Alerts was two hours late! Oops…no wonder no-one else turned up “at the right time”.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ansocach-14.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Car Park"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-038/ansocach-14.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Car Park"></a></p>
<figcaption>Car Park</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I got to the start around 7:45, and it was a chilly start, with -1.5 degC in Braemar as I drove through, however, the weather was stunning with clear blue skies and not a breath of wind.</p>
<p>I cycled along the estate track until the actual ascent starts - probably saves about 20-30 minutes walking each way, as I thought Fraser and Chris would have a quicker walk back on their summit. I need to buy an actual mountain bike as this and Mount Keen the other week have felt like I was going to shake the bike, and me, to pieces. The bike made a helpful support when crossing the ford before turning up the hill.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ansocach-12.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Bike ends here"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-038/ansocach-12.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Bike ends here"></a></p>
<figcaption>Bike ends here</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Quite boggy on the way up until the final steep ascent onto the long plateau.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ansocach-13.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Up to the plateau"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-038/ansocach-13.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Up to the plateau"></a></p>
<figcaption>Up to the plateau</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The first cairn is only 6m below the actual summit but still around 2km away. At this point I called in with Fraser and Chris on the HT, and they were a similar 1.5km away from their summit.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ansocach-7.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Passing the residents"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-038/ansocach-7.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Passing the residents"></a></p>
<figcaption>Passing the residents</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Lots of good views and, as already said, lovely weather! I found a nice grassy patch near to the cairn to setup the yagi.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ansocach-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="Yagi and IC-705"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-038/ansocach-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Yagi and IC-705"></a></p>
<figcaption>Yagi and IC-705</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Some good QSOs on 2m FM and SSB, not quite what Fraser managed but his summit was higher and so he was in the way! 😅</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="qsos.jpeg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="Pink for FM and green for SSB"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-038/qsos.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Pink for FM and green for SSB"></a></p>
<figcaption>Pink for FM and green for SSB</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>After calling for a long time on sideband I was impatient on FM and kept jumping around when I saw activity on the waterfall, either following Fraser like an annoying puppy, or jumping onto the calling frequency when it was free. Probably should’ve just stayed still!</p>
<p>I made use of the flat plateau and large activation zone to start heading back but still ready with the HT for Alan, MM0VPM. <a href="https://apps.apple.com/gb/app/sota-goat/id590206108">SotaGoat</a> app kept me in check and that saved a bit of time coming back. My worries of being slow down were unnecessary as I ended up being at the Bothy for a full round of cakes before the others arrived…and I couldn’t let them feel guilty for eating in front of me.</p>
<p>G4IPB reported hearing me on from <a href="https://sotl.as/summits/G/LD-008">Blencathra</a> - in the lake district just north of Keswick - and after seeing his report I realised that I also heard him but we were in the middle of some other QSOs so I never followed up and changed frequency. I was only on the HT and RH770 but he’d give me 55 and he was clear to me, although the first QSO was a bit muffled and dogs barking made it unclear.</p>
<p>The views were spectacular all around, with snow on the high summits.</p>
<div>

</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-panel" data-layout-ncol="3">
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: center;">
<p><a href="ansocach-10.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="my-group"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-038/ansocach-10.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: center;">
<p><a href="ansocach-11.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="my-group"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-038/ansocach-11.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: center;">
<p><a href="ansocach-9.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="my-group"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-038/ansocach-9.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: center;">
<p><a href="ansocach-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="my-group"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-038/ansocach-4.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: center;">
<p><a href="ansocach-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="my-group"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-038/ansocach-3.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
</div>
</div>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-038/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 25 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-038/ansocach-5.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Largo Law</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-ss-259/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>My wife and I had a trip away for the weekend, and I suggested a nice walk nearby…which of course was a SOTA summit! We were staying near St.&nbsp;Andrews, which is quite a flat area, however, there are a few granite lumps you can climb. Today’s one was Largo Law. If the weather was good, we’d have a lovely view of the Forth, Edinburgh and East Lothian. However, that wasn’t the case today…more like gray and cloudy.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="largolaw-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Summit ahead!"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-ss-259/largolaw-4.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Summit ahead!"></a></p>
<figcaption>Summit ahead!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The route is straight forward, as shown on <a href="https://sotl.as/summits/GM/SS-259">Sotlas</a>, park at the school/cemetery, up towards the farm and then straight up the hill! The track was tricky in places as the ground was dry and covered in loose soil, but we made it up fine.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="largolaw-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Looking back down the path over the Firth of Forth"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-ss-259/largolaw-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Looking back down the path over the Firth of Forth"></a></p>
<figcaption>Looking back down the path over the Firth of Forth</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I setup the slim g on the 6m carbon mast, put out a spot and called CQ. It took a few calls but stations did start coming back. Good coverage across Glasgow, Edinburgh and up to Montrose area. Had a nice chat with GM4PKJ, who lives very close to where we used to live around 10 years ago. His wife is a ham too, but I didn’t realise until I got home and looked him up on QRZ, otherwise I could’ve said hi to her too.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="largolaw-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Horses in the field"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-ss-259/largolaw-3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Horses in the field"></a></p>
<figcaption>Horses in the field</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Got my four contacts and packed up. My wife was sat nearby and commented the radio conversation was so “old man”. It was mostly what’s the weather and setup but I probably do adopt some old man tendencies when talking…it’s as though you’ve got to fit in. I should just ignore that and say whatever I want. Although I do like describing the weather on a summit, as quite often it’s different from “ground” level.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="gmss259 lora.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Heard across the water"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-ss-259/gmss259 lora.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Heard across the water"></a></p>
<figcaption>Heard across the water</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I had my Lora tracker with me and looked up if I’d been tracked. Two stations across the water had followed me up and down the summit. One was a new one in the centre of Edinburgh owned by <a href="https://gm5aug.topple.scot/">GM5AUG</a>.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="gm5aug-6 igate.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="GM5AUG-6"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-ss-259/gm5aug-6 igate.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="GM5AUG-6"></a></p>
<figcaption>GM5AUG-6</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>We headed back down and then back to the hotel, to enjoy the silence of no kids for the rest of the weekend!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="largolaw-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="Smile!"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-ss-259/largolaw-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Smile!"></a></p>
<figcaption>Smile!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-ss-259/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 22 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-ss-259/largolaw-5.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Buck</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-039/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Not wanting to waste a glorious day, I had time for a quick activation in the morning and <a href="https://sotl.as/summits/GM/ES-039">The Buck</a> was the recommendation.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="buck-11.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Short ascent"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-039/buck-11.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Short ascent"></a></p>
<figcaption>Short ascent</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The route is pretty easy, not quite a straight line as I’ve drawn but I parked slightly east on the road and walked up until I met this fence line. A quick march and you can be at the top in 30 minutes. The sub-500m area is pretty boggy and wet, even today when it hasn’t rained in a while. It was a little slow in places, trying to avoid plunging my feet into ankle deep water. The path is also vague at this stage but then becomes more defined within about 1km of the summit.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="buck-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="View to the top"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-039/buck-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="View to the top"></a></p>
<figcaption>View to the top</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="buck-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Squelchy"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-039/buck-3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Squelchy"></a></p>
<figcaption>Squelchy</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The weather was amazing, brilliant sunshine, blue skies and not a breath of wind. I was roasting on the way up!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="buck-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Trig point on top of the rocky summit"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-039/buck-4.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Trig point on top of the rocky summit"></a></p>
<figcaption>Trig point on top of the rocky summit</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Even at the top the wind was minimal, and I’ve never seen my carbon-6 stand so straight at a summit before! I made use of the nice clear hole in the trig point and put the mast in it with the slim g on top. I could see for miles and miles!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="buck-6.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="Setup for 2m"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-039/buck-6.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Setup for 2m"></a></p>
<figcaption>Setup for 2m</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I was hoping it would be a quick activation on 2m, as I needed to get back home by lunchtime, and this summit would cover a huge area. Back from his hols in <a href="https://reflector.sota.org.uk/t/the-sota-rough-guide-to-barbados/36296">Barbados</a>, MM0EFI was first in the log. After 5 minutes, Bill in Aberdeen, GM0NRT, called back, and whilst we were talking I heard another station call. This time it was GM0UDL up in Fortrose, just north of Inverness who had seen my Lora tracker being picked up by GM4SJB (even further north!). He told me about his lora setup and how everyone around that area has setup iGates and DMR repeaters. Sounds like a great setup they have. Not long afterwards my fourth 2m contact, needed to qualify the summit, came from GM8ZKU across to the east by the coast. Again, another nice QSO with Simon for the first time. Time was getting on and I did need to be back home, I tried on more CQ but then called it a day.</p>
<p>I</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="buck-7.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="Looking North"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-039/buck-7.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Looking North"></a></p>
<figcaption>Looking North</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>had a quick look around for the <a href="https://www.walkhighlands.co.uk/aberdeenshire/the-buck.shtml">ancient engravings</a> but couldn’t find them. It was a quick walk back down the hill to the car. I’d forgotten about the sogginess but managed to escape with dry feet.</p>
<p>When I got home I looked up the Lora tracking on <a href="https://lora.ham-radio-op.net/">EA2RCF’s mapping page</a>, and was surprised to see just how far away GM4SJB’s receiving igate was! It had also tracked me nearly the whole route up and down, which I then realised was me walking the county boundaries. The power on the tracker is tiny and the antenna isn’t amazing but this time it all worked well. I’ve been carrying it with me on most summits but there haven’t been any igates nearby that have picked me up.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="buck-13.jpeg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7" title="Lora 70cm distance"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-039/buck-13.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Lora 70cm distance"></a></p>
<figcaption>Lora 70cm distance</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="buck-14.jpeg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-8" title="Tracking my route"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-039/buck-14.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Tracking my route"></a></p>
<figcaption>Tracking my route</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="buck-12.jpeg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-9" title="Speedy!"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-039/buck-12.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Speedy!"></a></p>
<figcaption>Speedy!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>A nice quick 4-pointer summit - I’m beginning to think <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-018/">Morven</a> is a brutal 4-pointer! - although not for a wet day, or post a lot of rain. The summit is quite exposed, although maybe you could find some shelter depending on the wind direction. It’s a popular summit to do with Tap O’Noth, as that’s just a few miles away, however, I just didn’t have time on this occasion. Maybe they’ll be a good combo next year during the winter bonus period.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="uncle-buck.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-10" title="What the Buck"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-039/uncle-buck.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="What the Buck"></a></p>
<figcaption>What the Buck</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-039/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-039/buck-8.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>FTDX10 and Omirig - for CloudlogCAT</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/cloudcat-with-ftdx10/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>I’ve been using <a href="https://github.com/magicbug/Cloudlog">Cloudlog</a> for my logs, and have also recently migrated to <a href="https://github.com/wavelog/wavelog">wavelog</a>. Both of these share the same API which you can use with various CAT command software to get data from your radio into the logging program. Most useful for when doing live QSOs and to have it update the frequency and mode for you.</p>
<p>One such tool is <a href="https://github.com/magicbug/CloudlogCAT">CloudlogCAT</a> (windows only). It uses omnirig behind the scenes to interface with the radio. Other tools can be seen on the <a href="https://github.com/wavelog/Wavelog/wiki/Third-Party-Tools">wiki</a> pages of the two loggers. I had this working on another laptop but for various reasons was using a different one. I’d setup the vertical again in the garden and brought out the FTDX10 to use. I spent ages faffing about trying to get this to work and eventually found the right settings.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="cloudcat-omnirig.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Settings to use"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/cloudcat-with-ftdx10/cloudcat-omnirig.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Settings to use"></a></p>
<figcaption>Settings to use</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I also have a nicer way of setting up the spiderbeam mast using a base clamp wooden block and guy wires attached to a hose clamp with rubber nitrile protecting the mast. It takes no time at all to setup, and the remote ATU, radials, cables, and radio are all critical path items now!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="Vertical-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Mast base - I’ve since made the hole bigger so the mast rubber foot goes all the way in"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/cloudcat-with-ftdx10/Vertical-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Mast base - I’ve since made the hole bigger so the mast rubber foot goes all the way in"></a></p>
<figcaption>Mast base - I’ve since made the hole bigger so the mast rubber foot goes all the way in</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I might upgrade to 4mm rope for the guys, as the cleats don’t have much area to bite and in high winds they did slip.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-caution callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Don’t tighten the hose clamps too much, as you’ll damage the mast
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">

</div>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>FTDX10</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/cloudcat-with-ftdx10/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/cloudcat-with-ftdx10/Vertical-1.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Mount Keen</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-014/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="keen-7.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Start of the ascent"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-014/keen-7.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Start of the ascent"></a></p>
<figcaption>Start of the ascent</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Another day off and the forecast was promising blue skies and sunshine. I’d spent the evenings this week trawling sotlas trying to figure out where to go. It was our youngest’s P1 stay and play this morning, plus swim training after school, so I had to fit my trip into that window. I’ve been finding I go faster than OS Maps walking prediction but yet to keep detailed enough records to figure out my speed, so planning a new location is always hit or miss (along with the <a href="https://sotawatch.sota.org.uk/en/">alerts</a> I post!) To complicate matters more, I was planning on cycling the first part of the route before walking. I settled on Mount Keen and left after a fun session with the P1s.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="route.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="OS Map of the route"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-014/route.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="OS Map of the route"></a></p>
<figcaption>OS Map of the route</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I was also going to go the Glen Esk route, from the south, vs.&nbsp;the Glen Tanar one from the north. I thought it was a closer drive to home, but it was actually further, however, I think the walk is shorter this way. The road into Glen Esk seems to go on and on and on! Plus no end of dumb pheasants to watch out for on the road. I’ve actually done this hill before, maybe 12/13 years ago and on that trip we ended up walking through a blizzard! I can’t remember if we even made it to the top or decided to head back down, to then find the stream crossing to be more challenging than the way up!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="keen-8.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Stream crossing"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-014/keen-8.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Stream crossing"></a></p>
<figcaption>Stream crossing</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I cycled from the car park, just before the Lochlee Parish Church, along the north side of the river. My bike is a “hybrid” which is more road bike than mountain bike but has thickish tyres. I think this was probably the limit for it, as it was quite rocky and the ride was very rattly! I made it, and it cut off a good chunk of time but wasn’t always pleasant. I set off at 10:45 from the car park, and cycled for 30 minutes to just before the stream crossing in the picture above. The terrain is fairly flat with only a small incline the whole way. You also pass the Queen’s Well, which is nice to look at if you’ve never seen it before.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="keen-9.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Looking back and Queen’s Well"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-014/keen-9.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Looking back and Queen’s Well"></a></p>
<figcaption>Looking back and Queen’s Well</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The path is very clear and well made the whole way, some places its been eroded by water, or repaired with big chunks of rock. The roadway keeps going and you have to make sure you turn off towards Mount Keen.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="keen-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="A good view back down the Glen on the way up"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-014/keen-4.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A good view back down the Glen on the way up"></a></p>
<figcaption>A good view back down the Glen on the way up</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="keen-5.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="Final path to the summit (beyond the ridge)"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-014/keen-5.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Final path to the summit (beyond the ridge)"></a></p>
<figcaption>Final path to the summit (beyond the ridge)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>After an hour I’d reached the top and had my HT out as MM0VPM was on <a href="https://sotl.as/summits/GM/ES-009">Sgor Gaoith</a> and I was hoping for a summit to summit. Seems the weather wasn’t as good with him inland, and the snow I could see in the distance was probably where he was! I heard GM4CCN calling CQ and tried to answer but the Aberdeen folk thought I was calling CQ and called me back. Made a couple of contacts on the telescopic RH770 with the new FT-65 before setting up the slim G off to the side.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="keen-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7" title="Made it!"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-014/keen-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Made it!"></a></p>
<figcaption>Made it!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>There were quite a few folks on the summit so I was over to the west side. Not sure if that was the best as I was in the shadow of the cairn and perhaps they might’ve been blocking my signal. I heard GM4CCN a few more times and we tried to have a QSO. I found holding the PTT on the FT65 difficult when my hands were getting cold, that I don’t think I was actually transmitting and so we never made the QSO. Bill, GM0NRT, kept saying I dropped out but I think it was not holding the PTT. I was probably holding it wrong, in my right hand and using my finger on the PTT, vs.&nbsp;my left and using my thumb. Or I should’ve put on a glove.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="keen-6.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-8" title="Lochnagar"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-014/keen-6.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Lochnagar"></a></p>
<figcaption>Lochnagar</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I tried the slim G for a bit, had a couple more but not as many as I thought I’d get on this summit. I switched to HF with the 5.5m vertical and tried 20m. A good reply on 20m with 16 in the log. I did try 10m for a bit. I heard a VK station absolutely booming in, who was talking to a MW0 station in Wales, but only one reply to my CQ. By this time I was getting cold and I’d been on the summit an hour, and should probably be getting back.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="keen-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-9" title="Towards Aberdeen"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-014/keen-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Towards Aberdeen"></a></p>
<figcaption>Towards Aberdeen</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>As I was packing up a lady, who I’d passed on my bike, asked me to take a photo of her. She also asked if I was a Russian spy. I said a good spy wouldn’t reveal if they were one - but also that could be double bluffing. We ended up walking back down together until I got to my bike. She was trying to complete all the Munros, and had about 20-odd left. I thought about making my excuses and running ahead but it was nice having a little chat and she wasn’t really any slower than me.</p>
<p>The bike ride back was easier as slightly downhill, so only took 20 minutes, and I was back at the car in no time, and home with 30 minutes to spare! Although only 12% battery in the car. The journey out had used 51% of the battery, which was slightly worrying but I suspect it was the colder morning, and now it was 15 C.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-014/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-014/keen-5.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Carn Ealasaid</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-030/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Sunday and a busy day for the kids planned, however, it did mean my eldest and I were free all morning. She’d enjoyed our <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-068/">last SOTA activation</a> and this time I wanted to try somewhere further afield, and do more than a one-pointer! Especially after my mid-week three summits trip.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ealasaid-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Admiring the view from the ski centre"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-030/ealasaid-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Admiring the view from the ski centre"></a></p>
<figcaption>Admiring the view from the ski centre</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>We drove to the Lecht ski centre through thick fog and mist (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haar_(fog)">haar</a>) for about an hour. I’d looked at the forecast and it was meant to be partially sunny, but I was wondering if it had changed but I’d not seen it. However, with about 20 minutes to go, it suddenly cleared up and when we reached the car park it was a lovely day. This significantly helped the trip as I’m not sure my hiking partner would’ve been too pleased other wise! She immediately commented that the first path looked steep. She wasn’t wrong, it was the steepest part of the journey, although later on, on the way back, it was taxing again.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="route.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="The route"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-030/route.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="The route"></a></p>
<figcaption>The route</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>You walk around the lifts and towards another summit before descending and then ascending again to the final summit. Alone, and determined, I reckon I could do it in 45 minutes, but today it took us 1:15, with a couple of stops to sit down for a bit.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ealasaid-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="View of summit from Beinn A’Chruinnich by the ski lifts"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-030/ealasaid-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="View of summit from Beinn A’Chruinnich by the ski lifts"></a></p>
<figcaption>View of summit from Beinn A’Chruinnich by the ski lifts</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ealasaid-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Admiring the bogs we crossed"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-030/ealasaid-3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Admiring the bogs we crossed"></a></p>
<figcaption>Admiring the bogs we crossed</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The peat bogs weren’t too bad and quite dry, but I can imagine after some rainfall they’d be very squelchy.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ealasaid-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="At the top!"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-030/ealasaid-4.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="At the top!"></a></p>
<figcaption>At the top!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>We made it up the last slope, watching every meter on SOTAGoat app! I emptied out the snacks and set to work getting on 2m.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ealasaid-5.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="Slim G on Carbon-6 mast"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-030/ealasaid-5.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Slim G on Carbon-6 mast"></a></p>
<figcaption>Slim G on Carbon-6 mast</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Annoyingly my Kenwood D72 wouldn’t turn on. It had died on Foudland during the week and I assumed it was just flat. I’d charged it and the charging light had turned green so I assumed all was good. Well no, it wasn’t. I tried fiddling with the battery clip to get it out but couldn’t work the mechanism and soon gave up on it. I had an old TH-79 with me which did turn on (although the LCD screen doesn’t show all the segments and is difficult to read). I have tested the TH-79 at home and it transmitted, but no-one could hear me and I wasn’t sure if it was really working.</p>
<p>I didn’t want to spend too long faffing about as the summit is very exposed, and whilst it was a nice day, my daughter would soon get cold just sitting around. So I switched to HF. I debated between the 5.5m random wire vertical or the 40m EFHW. I wanted to go on 40m and the random wire isn’t necessarily great for 40m. However, I should’ve just gone with the vertical. As I was rushing, it meant it took me ages to get setup as things kept going wrong. Eventually I was sorted, but then the challenge of finding a free frequency. Seemed to be a contest going on, bunkers on the air and all sorts, but I did manage. Got 5 on 40m, including two locals from the SOTA Whatsapp group and that meant success! I thought I’d quickly try 20m. I heard one faint German station but when I looked up the cloud had come right in and we were sat in it. I knew it was time to go, and so we quickly packed up and started heading down. A summit in the cloud is disorientating and cold.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ealasaid-6.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7" title="From fun to fog in five seconds"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-030/ealasaid-6.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="From fun to fog in five seconds"></a></p>
<figcaption>From fun to fog in five seconds</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>We headed back down, and wanted to cut off part of the path up to the first summit, and follow the contours around. We were sort of successful but did get caught up in the bog and ended up walking a bit further downhill than we should’ve. Again, the cloud level didn’t help. It was a big of a struggle to get back on to the path at the top of the ski runs but we made it, and then it was an easy downhill from there.</p>
<p>Quite the change when we got to the bottom, the nice view at the start of this post was replaced by white cloud!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ealasaid-7.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-8" title="What wind turbine?"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-030/ealasaid-7.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="What wind turbine?"></a></p>
<figcaption>What wind turbine?</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I’m glad we arrived when we did, else it would’ve been quite miserable and the only excitement of the radio activation wouldn’t have been shared by all!</p>
<p>We stopped at the Spar in <a href="https://www.undiscoveredscotland.co.uk/strathdon/bellabeg/index.html">Bellabeg</a> for some diet coke and a jam swiss roll, which we ate nearly half each before driving home.</p>
<p>There are a few more 4 pointers in the area, and hopefully I can get back to do some of those. Most have been activated less than 10 times, which suggests they’re maybe not that exciting or easy to get to. <a href="https://sotl.as/summits/GM/ES-023">Brown Cow Hill</a>, <a href="https://sotl.as/summits/GM/ES-036">Geallaig</a>, and <a href="https://sotl.as/summits/GM/ES-034">Mona Gowan</a> don’t seem too bad, so perhaps I should try those first.</p>
<p>When I got home I checked the D72. It wouldn’t turn on, but when I plugged in an external power supply it turned on and then worked fine on battery. I don’t like the reliability of this, and being caught out on a summit again. I might get a new battery pack but I also might look for another HT. Perhaps a Yeasu FT-65 etc. that has great battery life is just a simple HT.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-030/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 08 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-030/ealasaid-3.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Building a portable 2m yagi</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/building-a-2m-portable-yagi/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>I’ve been enjoying activating SOTA summits on 2m, and after visiting <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-012/">Glas Maol</a> and seeing how far I could get with an omni directional antenna, and watching videos of people using a 2m yagi to get into England from the highlands, I wanted to build a yagi.</p>
<p>All my research pointed me towards <a href="https://www.qsl.net/dk7zb/start1.htm">DK7ZB’s</a> designs, specifically the <a href="https://www.qsl.net/dk7zb/PVC-Yagis/PVC-details.htm">lightweight ones</a>. I decided the 4 element design with a 1m boom was optimal between gain and practicalities. This has a gain of 7 dBd and a front to back ratio of 12 dB. It also has the advantage of being able to use it with 70 cms.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="2m-yagi-16.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Parts to build"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/building-a-2m-portable-yagi/2m-yagi-16.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Parts to build"></a></p>
<figcaption>Parts to build</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I went to B&amp;Q and bought some 22mm PVC pipe, some wall clips, 4mm aluminium rods, and a 6mm aluminium tube. I already had some electrical connector blocks and RG58 cable at home. I made the boom a little longer than 1m, so I could hand hold it if I wanted to, otherwise it only needs to be 1m in length.</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<caption>Dimensions from DK7ZB - using 4mm elements</caption>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th></th>
<th style="text-align: center;">Positions along boom (mm)</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">Length of element (mm)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Reflector</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">1020</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Radiator</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">260</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">977</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Director 1</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">470</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">930</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Director 2</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">985</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">910</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p><a href="https://vk1nam.wordpress.com/2018/04/07/antenna-project-portable-2m-4el-dl6wu-yagi/">VK1AD’s post</a> on building a similar yagi helped me decide how to mount everything to the boom, and I set to cutting the aluminium rods and drilling the holes in the clamp. The directors are easy, as they just slide through the clamp as a single piece. The reflector is slightly longer than 1m which the rods come in, so I used the 6mm tube as a connector between two 4mm rods. Sounds good in theory but it’s tricky to get the rods into the tube - precision hammering needed.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="2m-yagi-14.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Best way to drill"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/building-a-2m-portable-yagi/2m-yagi-14.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Best way to drill"></a></p>
<figcaption>Best way to drill</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="2m-yagi-13.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Driven element"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/building-a-2m-portable-yagi/2m-yagi-13.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Driven element"></a></p>
<figcaption>Driven element</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The driven element used the connectors from inside an electrical connector block, zip tied and then glued into one of the clamps. I used some solder wick to attach the coax to and screwed the elements in on each side.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="2m-yagi-12.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Attaching coax"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/building-a-2m-portable-yagi/2m-yagi-12.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Attaching coax"></a></p>
<figcaption>Attaching coax</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="2m-yagi-11.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="More hot glue and amalgamation tape"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/building-a-2m-portable-yagi/2m-yagi-11.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="More hot glue and amalgamation tape"></a></p>
<figcaption>More hot glue and amalgamation tape</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="2m-yagi-10.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="With choke"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/building-a-2m-portable-yagi/2m-yagi-10.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="With choke"></a></p>
<figcaption>With choke</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>RG58 is a bit heavy but it’s all I had so would do. Whilst this was easy to build, it does mean the only way I can transport it is by unscrewing the elements. Not the best solution but I wanted to get it built vs.&nbsp;debating over other ways or buying more things. A common way others do it is with a box mounted on the boom and there’s a coax connector on it, so you can remove the box with driven element in one. My one has about 3-4m of coax on which is enough from the mast mounting position to having the radio on the ground underneath.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Tip
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>The length of the driven element is from tip to tip, including the gap in between.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="2m-yagi-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7" title="Packs up small-ish"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/building-a-2m-portable-yagi/2m-yagi-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Packs up small-ish"></a></p>
<figcaption>Packs up small-ish</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I marked the PVC tube with sharpie for the location of each clamp, together with numbers. I also put a mark in the centre of the rod on the directors so I could centre it if it moved about in the clamp. It’s all about 1m long and I found a thin bag to carry it in. It’s not the greatest but will do. I used bungees to tie it to the side of my backpack.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="2m-yagi-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-8" title="Total weight - including coax"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/building-a-2m-portable-yagi/2m-yagi-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Total weight - including coax"></a></p>
<figcaption>Total weight - including coax</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I’m using a SOTABeams <a href="https://www.sotabeams.co.uk/tactical-mini-compact-ultra-portable-6-m-19-6-ft-mast/">tactical mini</a> mast to support it. It’s 6m telescopic fibreglass pole that has more strength than my usual <a href="https://www.sotabeams.co.uk/carbon-6-ultra-light-6-m-19-6-ft-mast/">Carbon-6</a> mast. There are two conduit wall mounts attached to the boom, so the yagi can be mounted vertically or horizontally. It works well enough, although if I want to change polarisation I have to take the mast down and then put it up again. I could take out all the other sections I don’t need but if I’m only taking one mast on an activation I want the 6m in case I need to setup HF.</p>
<p>I 3D printed some guying rings and rope tensioners from <a href="https://www.thingiverse.com/thing:5616644">this design</a> and cut some cord to length for the mast. The 2nd lowest ring fitted perfectly on the bottom segment of the tactical mini.</p>
<p><a href="2m-yagi-6.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-9"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/building-a-2m-portable-yagi/2m-yagi-6.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p><a href="2m-yagi-7.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-10"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/building-a-2m-portable-yagi/2m-yagi-7.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="2m-yagi-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-11" title="Testing in the garden"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/building-a-2m-portable-yagi/2m-yagi-3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Testing in the garden"></a></p>
<figcaption>Testing in the garden</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>First test was in the garden, listening to the 2m lunchtime net…so it received well enough.</p>
<p>The first outing was to <a href="https://sotl.as/summits/GM/ES-072">Cairn William</a>, where I’d set it up on the top. We’d arranged SSB activity on another summit, although that guy had to pull out, however, we’d also prepared the locals to listen out. I started with SSB and managed to make four contacts locally with it. I then flipped it to FM and made a few more. Including a nice summit to summit with Schiehallion, around 112 km away! I brought it out later in the day on <a href="https://sotl.as/summits/GM/ES-079">Tillymorgan</a>, and managed a contact with Helmsdale, around 100 km to the north…whilst the yagi was pointing south! Turning it around turned me from a 53 and a 59 by the chaser</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="cairn-william.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-12" title="On Cairn William"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/building-a-2m-portable-yagi/cairn-william.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="On Cairn William"></a></p>
<figcaption>On Cairn William</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="tillymorgan-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-13" title="On TIllymorgan"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/building-a-2m-portable-yagi/tillymorgan-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="On TIllymorgan"></a></p>
<figcaption>On TIllymorgan</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="qsos.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-14" title="Long distance QSOs"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/building-a-2m-portable-yagi/qsos.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Long distance QSOs"></a></p>
<figcaption>Long distance QSOs</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I’m pleased with the results and think it worked rather well! It wasn’t too tricky to setup and use in the field, nor heavy to carry. It takes a bit of getting used to the length of it, especially when walking through forests as I kept catching it on trees and causing them to dump all their water onto my back!</p>
<p>I think a different way to connect the coax and the driven element would improve it, and maybe a dedicated mast that was just the right length would be better.</p>
<p>I did find this design for a <a href="https://www.iz2uuf.net/wp/index.php/2013/04/06/100g-yagi/">100g yagi</a> that looks nice, and have saved a few links to 2m moxon’s. Not sure when or if I’ll make these, as I do like the convenience of the slim G. I also <a href="https://www.printables.com/model/754860-mast-clip-for-2m-slim-g-antenna-for-sota-use-espec">printed a clip</a> for it, so it doesn’t flap around in the breeze.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Construction</category>
  <category>sota</category>
  <category>2m</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/building-a-2m-portable-yagi/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/building-a-2m-portable-yagi/cairn-william.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Hill of Tillymorgan</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-079/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="tillymorgan-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Looking back at Foudland"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-079/tillymorgan-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Looking back at Foudland"></a></p>
<figcaption>Looking back at Foudland</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>A quick drive across the A96 and I was parked by the old church - <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/pah11Z7VKxTnonEh7">Kirkton of Culsalmond Old Parish Church</a>. The path is easy, straight up the road to the turbines and then either around them bypassing the fence, or past them and then finding a spot where the barbed wire fence has come down.</p>
<p><a href="tillymorgan-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-079/tillymorgan-2.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="tillymorgan-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="They’re big!"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-079/tillymorgan-3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="They’re big!"></a></p>
<figcaption>They’re big!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="tillymorgan-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="South towards Bennachie"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-079/tillymorgan-4.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="South towards Bennachie"></a></p>
<figcaption>South towards Bennachie</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Doesn’t take long and you’re in the activation zone, but I wanted to get to the trig point. Turns out there’s an old quarry here and you have to navigate it, but the trig offers lovely views all around once you do get there.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="tillymorgan-5.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="Slates"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-079/tillymorgan-5.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Slates"></a></p>
<figcaption>Slates</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Decided to setup the yagi again and try it out, just on FM this time. The wind blew it around a little which caused signal reports to jump up and down. Managed across the water to the North to Helmsdale, about 100 km away…from the back of the yagi! I was 53 at first but when I turned it around I was 59 to him.</p>
<p><a href="tillymorgan-7.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-079/tillymorgan-7.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p>Just managed four in the log but that was enough, starting to feel the days activities now and it was time to be heading home. My shoes hadn’t done well on Cairn William, and were soaked back then, and still wet now.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="tillymorgan-6.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7" title="Looking tired!"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-079/tillymorgan-6.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Looking tired!"></a></p>
<figcaption>Looking tired!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-079/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 04 Sep 2024 16:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-079/bee.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Hill of Foudland</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-071/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Next summit of the day. A short drive up the A96 and off at Colpy to Hill of Foudland. I was approaching from the east so I was close to Tillymorgan but it’s not a very exciting route. I think there’s a better one from the east. I’d read on Walkinghighlands that there’s more <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/CWsRgrzdmu87g1Ma9">parking in the forest</a>, beyond the limits of the public road. Not sure if this is really allowed or not but it seemed better than parking on essentially <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/v4MQV2DuYVNJe6as6">nothing</a>, as I was out of the way. This also saved me some walking along a boring track. After the chat with G0JSO, I was 30 minutes later than planned, and so I wasn’t sure if I was going to make it in time to get at the summit for the lunchtime 2m net.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="foudland-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="View south to Bennachie"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-071/foudland-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="View south to Bennachie"></a></p>
<figcaption>View south to <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-061/">Bennachie</a></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>As I was walking up I had my HT tuned into 145.550 MHz listening out for them. I managed to call into the net and said I was hiking up and I’d come back to them when I was at the top. I knew the top was quite flat, and watching SOTAGoat app I saw I was within the activation zone but still a good ~650 m from the actual summit point. At this stage I setup the telescopic pole between my legs with the slim G on the top.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="slimg.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="3D printed part to keep it attached to mast"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-071/slimg.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="3D printed part to keep it attached to mast"></a></p>
<figcaption>3D printed part to keep it attached to mast</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>On the way up, with the RH770, Bill and Paul couldn’t hear me (nor I Paul), but once I had the slim G up on the 6m mast, everyone was a very good signal. So I had three from the net and Mike was trying break in but the other guys kept chatting! Eventually it came round to me and I was answering their questions and building up to bringing Mike in when the D72 died on me! Luckily I had the 705 and got that hooked up. I rejoined and explained, plus got Mike in. If I just had the KX2 I’d been annoyed about that one!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="foudland-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Towers"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-071/foudland-3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Towers"></a></p>
<figcaption>Towers</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I was sat right in front of the towers but they were quiet on 145.550. I think the 705 had some issues with them but I turned off the pre-amp and that seemed to keep it calm. I said my goodbyes and turned back down the path to my third and final summit of the day!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="foudland-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Tillymorgan, left of the wind turbines"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-071/foudland-4.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Tillymorgan, left of the wind turbines"></a></p>
<figcaption>Tillymorgan, left of the wind turbines</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-071/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 04 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-071/foudland-3.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Cairn William</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-072/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>This was the first summit I tested my <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/building-a-2m-portable-yagi/">new 2m yagi</a> on. I was pleased with the summit to summit with Schiehallion around 112 km away.</p>
<p>I parked in a lay by just <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/vJktHhqjE538fz6N6">here</a>, and walked up several mountain bike trails.</p>
<p><a href="route.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-072/route.png" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p>The first part was pretty muddy, but once up on the forestry track and beyond it was fine. It was a nice day if you looked south, but not so much to the north. The summit was in the clouds and somewhat damp.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="cairn-william-8.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Muddy track"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-072/cairn-william-8.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Muddy track"></a></p>
<figcaption>Muddy track</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="cairn-william-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Looking South"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-072/cairn-william-4.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Looking South"></a></p>
<figcaption>Looking South</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="cairn-william-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="North to Millstone"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-072/cairn-william-3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="North to Millstone"></a></p>
<figcaption>North to <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-077/">Millstone</a></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The track is fairly easy to follow, just make sure to turn off the roadway on to the path, and the no entry signs are because the route is intended for mountain bikers.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="cairn-william-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="Turn off here!"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-072/cairn-william-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Turn off here!"></a></p>
<figcaption>Turn off here!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="cairn-william-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="⛔"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-072/cairn-william-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="⛔"></a></p>
<figcaption>⛔</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Was fairly light breeze on the summit but nothing too bad, so it wasn’t hard setting up the mast with the guys. They do get tangled somewhat so I might look at alternatives.</p>
<p><a href="cairn-william-6.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-072/cairn-william-6.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p><a href="cairn-william-7.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-8"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-072/cairn-william-7.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p>Spoke to a couple of locals on the HT, once I was within the activation zone, and then setup the yagi for SSB. Managed 4 on sideband - a first for me - and 2M0RVZ had his first 2m sideband as well. Both of us using the ic-705. I think Chris just used the RH-770 for his antenna on the radio!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="cairn-william-5.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-9" title="Action shot!"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-072/cairn-william-5.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Action shot!"></a></p>
<figcaption>Action shot!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I let Bill, GM0NRT, know I was going up some other hills later that day, so he was going to keep an ear out for me.</p>
<p>As I was packing up I met G0JSO (although now GM0JSO as he’s moved locally) and we had a nice long chat about amateur radio. He’s not been on the air in ages and was asking lots of questions. I sent him an email when I got home, and hopefully we will hear him on the air soon. It would be good to add him to the local SOTA chat for activator and chaser…but will see what happens.</p>
<p>Off to the next summit!</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-072/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 04 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-072/cairn-william-5.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Beinn Bhrotain</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-007/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>After hearing that Alan, MM0VPM, was doing a <a href="https://reflector.sota.org.uk/t/gm-es-002-003-and-007/36165">tour of the Cairngorms</a>, the local SOTA group was listening out for him. I commented that no one had done <a href="https://sotl.as/summits/GM/ES-007">Beinn Bhrotain</a> for a long time, not even Fraser. His response was, “How about Sunday, then?” The offer included transportation and a loan of a mountain bike, plus, of course, the guided tour—an offer too good to refuse! Free time on the weekends can be tricky, with several sets of kids’ activities and potential birthday parties, so we needed to start early so I could be back in time for my wife to start her coaching session at the swim club. Fraser was good with that, and our rendezvous was at 6 a.m. in the Dinnet car park for the onward journey to the Linn of Dee.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhrotain-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Ready to Ride!"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-007/bhrotain-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Ready to Ride!"></a></p>
<figcaption>Ready to Ride!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>We’d all seen a photo recently shared of the midge in the area, which is quite unusual away from the west of Scotland. Sure enough, there were plenty about when we arrived and unpacked the bikes. We met a DoE group packing up their tents at White Bridge, and they told tales of woe and suffering in the evening; the leader seemed very pleased to be going home. My wife later told me about one of her swimmers sending home a photo of a pan of custard he was cooking on his expedition, which had a nice layer of midges on top. 🤢</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhrotain-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Along the Dee, summit in the clouds"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-007/bhrotain-3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Along the Dee, summit in the clouds"></a></p>
<figcaption>Along the Dee, summit in the clouds</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhrotain-24.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="They’re deeper than they look"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-007/bhrotain-24.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="They’re deeper than they look"></a></p>
<figcaption>They’re deeper than they look</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The weather was pleasant enough, although the promised clear skies had yet to appear, and the cloud level was fairly low. We continued on our ride, following the Dee along a rockier track with plenty of culverts to negotiate. After around 7.5 km of cycling, we left the bikes by the side of the fence and took the track up towards the first summit we could just about see, Carn Cloich-mhuilinn. The path came and went, or we found and lost it several times, but with the rocky peak to aim for, it wasn’t too difficult to navigate. Every so often, Fraser would point out surrounding summits or features, complete with name, SOTA points, and YouTube URL, the names of which I’d immediately forget until he told them to me again on the way back down. The last 200m or so climb of this Carn was bouldery but nice underfoot, a bit like clambering across rocks at a beach. With the interim summit climbed, we admired the view. The cloud was still low, and a few patches of sun were appearing in the distance. It looked promising that it would clear for us, although I wasn’t sure if it would in time for our final ascent.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhrotain-21.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Path to the summit"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-007/bhrotain-21.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Path to the summit"></a></p>
<figcaption>Path to the summit</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhrotain-15.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="View back towards the Dee"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-007/bhrotain-15.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="View back towards the Dee"></a></p>
<figcaption>View back towards the Dee</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>We had a good view across a small gully where the path was as obvious as could be. After a short descent down to a wee stream, the path was lost to us. A few phantom paths appeared, and we followed them, probably veering more towards the west than necessary, but we found a way. I kept my eye on SOTAGoat, to be sure I wasn’t being led astray, and we soon found ourselves both within the activation zone and the cloud. The trig appeared out of the mist, and we had made it!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhrotain-12.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="The summit, with LoRa beaconing (to no-one ☹️)"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-007/bhrotain-12.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="The summit, with LoRa beaconing (to no-one ☹️)"></a></p>
<figcaption>The summit, with LoRa beaconing (to no-one ☹️)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Having eaten breakfast in Aberdeen at 5 a.m., it now felt like lunchtime, even though it was only around 09:15. At this point, I found out one of Fraser’s secrets to successful mountaineering — <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buttery_(bread)">butteries</a>. Claiming “this was all he could find in the cupboard,” he proceeded to eat what I’d estimate to be around 8,000 calories in a matter of minutes. Checking the schedule, we decided we had around 45 minutes on the summit before we should head back down.</p>
<p>Fraser had brought the FT-857 and his <a href="https://www.iz2uuf.net/wp/index.php/2013/04/06/100g-yagi/">100g yagi</a>, and was hopeful to activate on 2m. I was on HF with the KX2 and the 18ft (5.5m) random wire vertical. We each found a suitable pile of rocks to shelter behind and set to work.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhrotain-5.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7" title="Setting up yagi"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-007/bhrotain-5.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Setting up yagi"></a></p>
<figcaption>Setting up yagi</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhrotain-7.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-8" title="A brief spell of sun"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-007/bhrotain-7.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A brief spell of sun"></a></p>
<figcaption>A brief spell of sun</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhrotain-13.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-9" title="Working the south"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-007/bhrotain-13.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Working the south"></a></p>
<figcaption>Working the south</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I started on 40m; the antenna needs a transformer to get a match, and even though it’s short, I’ve made contacts this way before. I thought I’d try 40m, as maybe it’s a desirable trig point or WAB etc., place that folks would want. I could hear some contest callers, but after my spot and calling with no replies, it was clearly completely dead for me, so I moved to 20m. After spotting and calling CQ, a slow trickle of replies came, and I relaxed once I crossed number 4! The replies kept coming, including four summit-to-summit stations in Germany, Switzerland, and Romania. I considered some other bands, but time was marching on, my hands were cold, and everything was getting wet. The sun suddenly shone through for a few moments, and it looked lovely. Two runners then came by, having climbed from the opposite side. They asked what I was doing, to which my usual answer is “amateur radio, speaking to other people on mountains.” They were impressed with Switzerland and asked if I could say hi from them. They soon ran off again, and given they were in running shorts and vests, I’m not surprised they didn’t want to hang around.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhrotain-11.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-10" title="Carbon 6 and 5.5 m vertical"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-007/bhrotain-11.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Carbon 6 and 5.5 m vertical"></a></p>
<figcaption>Carbon 6 and 5.5 m vertical</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhrotain-9.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-11" title="Activation attire"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-007/bhrotain-9.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Activation attire"></a></p>
<figcaption>Activation attire</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="gm5alx-20m.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-12" title="My QSOs on 20m"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-007/gm5alx-20m.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="My QSOs on 20m"></a></p>
<figcaption>My QSOs on 20m</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I could hear Fraser still calling and trying to keep his wind vane under control. I got the thumbs up that he didn’t need to get on HF, so I packed up. We had a brief celebration—this was my first 10-pointer—and then turned around and headed back down.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhrotain-14.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-13" title="Success! ⛰️📻"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-007/bhrotain-14.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Success! ⛰️📻"></a></p>
<figcaption>Success! ⛰️📻</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Once we were down out of the cloud, the view improved significantly! The cloud had started to lift, and we could see the surrounding summits and valleys—spectacular! Similar to the way up, paths came and went, but we had a clear view of the Dee and knew where to go.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhrotain-17.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-14" title="Back into the light"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-007/bhrotain-17.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Back into the light"></a></p>
<figcaption>Back into the light</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhrotain-19.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-15" title="Path back to Carn Cloich-mhuilinn"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-007/bhrotain-19.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Path back to Carn Cloich-mhuilinn"></a></p>
<figcaption>Path back to Carn Cloich-mhuilinn</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhrotain-20.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-16" title="More 10 pointers"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-007/bhrotain-20.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="More 10 pointers"></a></p>
<figcaption>More 10 pointers</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhrotain-25.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-17" title="Dee in the background"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-007/bhrotain-25.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Dee in the background"></a></p>
<figcaption>Dee in the background</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Back on the bikes and back towards civilisation. We had a quick stop at the Chest of Dee waterfalls, where the pool looked lovely and inviting, before the final 5km or so to the car park. Up, activated, and back in under 6 hours.</p>
<p>Fraser did well on 2m, with an FM contact into the Yorkshire coast, 310 km away. Although, I think he would’ve liked some more SSB activity.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="mm0efi-2m.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-18" title="MM0EFI/P on 2m"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-007/mm0efi-2m.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="MM0EFI/P on 2m"></a></p>
<figcaption>MM0EFI/P on 2m</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Back home, and back to reality of family life. A great trip out, and thanks to Fraser for making it happen. I’ve bought a lot of things since starting amateur radio, but didn’t think mountain bike shopping would next on my list! 🚵</p>
<p>OSMaps <a href="https://explore.osmaps.com/route/23148061/gmes007-ben-bhrotain?lat=56.995974&amp;lon=-3.651355&amp;zoom=12.7686&amp;style=Standard&amp;type=2d">route link.</a></p>
<p>Also posted to the <a href="https://reflector.sota.org.uk/t/a-busy-beinn-bhrotain/36174">SOTA Reflector.</a></p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-007/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-007/bhrotain-22.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>More QSL cards</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/more-qsl-cards/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>A formal looking letter arrived for me this morning, when I looked closely I could see it was from Germany. Inside were some nice QSL cards.</p>
<p><a href="dk1mi.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/more-qsl-cards/dk1mi.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p><a href="https://dk1mi.radio/about/">Micheal</a> has two of his own from our HF SSB, HF FT8 and QO-100 QSOs over the past year, plus then the special one, <a href="https://www.qrz.com/db/DF0MF">DF0MF</a>, from the lightship in Emden. <a href="https://dk1mi.radio/amrumbank/">Micheal describes</a> his discovery and subsequent visit and activation of this historical ship.</p>
<p>I shall need to QSL, although Micheal’s two different cards makes me think about making a new QSL card for my portable SOTA operations. ⛰️</p>
<p>The TH-79E in the background of the photo also arrived today. The battery is dead and I have no power supply for it, and it was sold as “seen” so let’s hope a new battery will fix it!</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>QSO</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/more-qsl-cards/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/more-qsl-cards/dk1mi.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Xiegu G90 WSJT-X Setup</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/g90-wsjtx-setup/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Last weekend when playing with the <a href="../../../posts/2024/something-for-the-weekend/">new antenna</a>, I ended up using my G90 for running FT8. However, it had been a long time since I’d used it for this and I’d forgotten what to do, even of which cable to plug in where! I also ran into a few issues, so this post is a reminder for myself of what to do.</p>
<section id="hardware" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="hardware">Hardware</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="g90-cables.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Cabling required"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/g90-wsjtx-setup/g90-cables.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Cabling required"></a></p>
<figcaption>Cabling required</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I’m using the CAT cable that comes with the radio (with the blue USB), this plugs into the side of the head unit, with the person image (under the headphones). For audio I use a USB soundcard dongle (random off Amazon), and a headphones/mic splitter, and then a 8 pin mini DIN to TRRS audio cable. Think I bought this off ebay, like this <a href="https://www.ebay.co.uk/itm/176417679066">one</a>. The alternative is buying the CE-19 expansion port…but that’s more expensive. This cable plugs into the DIN port on the back and then the USB into the computer.</p>
<p>On the G90 (I have firmware 1.78 so no U-D data mode), put the audio to line in with Fn+Power button, turn off compressor, turn off Preamo, and push the volume knob so it switches to headphones (unless you like listening to data modes!). There are some other recommended settings <a href="https://www.digitalshack.org/xiegu-g90-ft8/">from the internet</a> in the menu. Not sure how important they really are but I set them anyway:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>RF gain 50%</p></li>
<li><p>Mic Gain to 10</p></li>
<li><p>AUX In volume to 8</p></li>
<li><p>AUX out volume to 15</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="software" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="software">Software</h2>
<p>WSJT-X has Xiegu G90 in the Radio menu but it’s very temperamental…at least for me. I found using <a href="http://www.w1hkj.com/">FLRig</a> as an intermediate for CAT control to be much better. You could just use VOX and skip CAT control. I also found newer version of FLRig had issues and went back to <a href="http://www.w1hkj.com/files/archives/Windows/flrig-1.4.8_setup.exe">v1.4.8</a> for a more stable experience.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="flrig.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="FLRig Setup"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/g90-wsjtx-setup/flrig.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="FLRig Setup"></a></p>
<figcaption>FLRig Setup</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Once FLRig is running, you can then setup WSJT-X as follows:</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="wsjtx-3.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Radio Settings"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/g90-wsjtx-setup/wsjtx-3.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Radio Settings"></a></p>
<figcaption>Radio Settings</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="wsjtx-2.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Audio Settings"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/g90-wsjtx-setup/wsjtx-2.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Audio Settings"></a></p>
<figcaption>Audio Settings</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I adjust the sound in Windows Sound Settings so that the receive on the left is about 70 dB, and then adjust the slider in WSJT-X for the transmit power such that ALC is 99-100 on the G90. This should correspond to the power output set.</p>
<p>Then enjoy your digital operations! Probably works for all digital modes with other software too.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>FT8</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/g90-wsjtx-setup/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/g90-wsjtx-setup/g90-cables.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Millstone Hill</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-077/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="millstone4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Route Map"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-077/millstone4.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Route Map"></a></p>
<figcaption>Route Map</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Took two of the kids with me on this one. They were keen for an adventure! Even packed their own bags with toys and random things, including ice cream and tea sets for a picnic on the summit. We parked in Donview forest car park and followed the red route up. Quite a steep bit near the start with wooden steps that the kids started counting, but then eased off and a more gentle climb after that. Nice and sheltered in the trees for much of the way. When we did get near the summit the wind was blowing an absolute gale - which everyone found amusing. We hunkered down behind a rock and the kids has their snack and picnic and I tried 2m FM. Managed three and then was worried I wouldn’t get my fourth. Heard MM0EFI calling but he couldn’t hear me, so I walked over the summit to the west side, just holding the pole with the slim G waving as the wind was blowing and then managed the QSO and even one more after that. Glad I didn’t have to get out HF as I think the kids had had enough of me messing about. Plus we had to be back in time for swim training.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="millstone1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="At the summit"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-077/millstone1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="At the summit"></a></p>
<figcaption>At the summit</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The walk down was much easier, the little one started getting tired half way down but kept soldering on. We went into Kemney in search of a cafe for lunch but they were all closed except one. That one was mobbed and looked too fancy for us, so we had a picnic in the car from the Co-op!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="millstone5.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Well prepared"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-077/millstone5.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Well prepared"></a></p>
<figcaption>Well prepared</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Little one is keen to go again and packed several backpacks in the garage, so will have to see what’s next for us.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="millstone2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="View towards Mither Tap"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-077/millstone2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="View towards Mither Tap"></a></p>
<figcaption>View towards Mither Tap</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-077/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-077/millstone2.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Something for the weekend</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/something-for-the-weekend/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Ever since I’ve been on HF, I had the same EFHW in the back garden as my antenna. It’s been great, lots of contacts made all over the world on SSB and digital modes. Pretty much worldwide with FT8/4 but also good DX on SSB into South Africa, Japan, Brazil amongst others. Plus of course nice chats in UK/EU predominately across 40m and 20m. If the conditions are right, then pretty much any bit of wire in the air will work! However, I’ve been looking to try something else, particularly a vertical and see how that works. I’ve spoken to Mike, M0AWS, several times about different antenna and he recommended the <a href="https://m0aws.co.uk/?p=1998">vertical that he uses</a>. It’s a multiband antenna from 80-10m and, as you can see from his article, he’s made many contacts with it around the world. It seemed like something that I could put up in the garden on a temporary basis and give it a go…so with my ordered delivered and wire measured I was ready to go!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="schematic.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Schematic of setup"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/something-for-the-weekend/schematic.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Schematic of setup"></a></p>
<figcaption>Schematic of setup</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The antenna is fairly simple, and relies on a remote ATU to match the wire to the band of interest. I managed to pick up a CG-3000 from ebay recently, but there are many brands and options available, you can even use a manual tuner at the base - obviously less convenient. I’ve seen the CG-3000 go for as little as £75, although they’re typically around £150. The radiating element is a 13.4m long piece of wire, attached to the CG-3000, up the side of the mast and then around 1m of it is tucked inside the mast. On the ground connector of the CG-3000 I connected an earth rod, suitable beaten into the ground around 60cm, and then four ~12m long radials laid on the ground at 90° to each other. The CG-3000 has a SO-239 connector for coax and a 4 pin connector for the power and control cable. Mine came with 5m of control cable, so that was my limiting factor in this setup. The controller on my unit was missing the power cable, it seemed to have been cut off only leaving two tiny ends of wire. I wanted to hook it into my Anderson powerpole junction box but turned out I had no red and black cables, and the replacement connector I found had the terminals the wrong way around. So I present the most error trap prone design for powering the CG-3000. My controller is an older model and says “Tune” next to the button at the top, but really that’s reset - which is what it says on later models.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="controller-2.jpeg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="my-gallery" title="Power and Reset - but you never need to press it"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/something-for-the-weekend/controller-2.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Power and Reset - but you never need to press it"></a></p>
<figcaption>Power and Reset - but you never need to press it</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="controller.jpeg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="my-gallery" title="It works…but not recommended!"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/something-for-the-weekend/controller.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="It works…but not recommended!"></a></p>
<figcaption>It works…but not recommended!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="spiderbeam.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="my-gallery" title="A wonky mast, pre-base fitting - also, it’s so tall!"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/something-for-the-weekend/spiderbeam.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A wonky mast, pre-base fitting - also, it’s so tall!"></a></p>
<figcaption>A wonky mast, pre-base fitting - also, it’s so tall!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>As I knew this was a temporary setup I didn’t do anything too special with the mounting, I made use of a piece of 68mm diameter drain pipe, a kids toy structure, some straps and a piece of wood with a hole drilled for the pole and some for ground pegs. DJ0IP has lots of <a href="https://www.dj0ip.de/spiderbeam/fiberglass-spiderpole/">good information</a> on using a spiderbeam pole, including mounting options. I found the wooden base was needed to keep it from tilting over, and luckily I had a holesaw of the right size. Although with the rubber cap on the bottom, it’s a tight fit and repeated taking in and out could rub the rubber away, so I might enlarge the hole a little. With the drain pipe mounted and the pole inside it was just a case of pulling up each section and tightening them. I think for long term installation, putting hose clamps at the base of each section, just above the section below, helps stop it collapsing. There’s lots of info online about this.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="cg3000.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="ATU at mast base"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/something-for-the-weekend/cg3000.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="ATU at mast base"></a></p>
<figcaption>ATU at mast base</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I did install a ground post next to the tuner, but in retrospect, for a temporary setup, I think this wasn’t necessary…mostly as it was a pain to get back out again, which I’ll come to later. I laid the radials out on the ground, trying to get them to cover the most space. The advantage of setting up in the middle of the garden is being able to lay them out in all directions. Any permanent home I find for it will likely be along one side of the garden, so the radials will have to just go where they can.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="station.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="Temporary kitchen shack"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/something-for-the-weekend/station.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Temporary kitchen shack"></a></p>
<figcaption>Temporary kitchen shack</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>My shack isn’t convenient for this setup, particularly with only 5m of control cable - although I suppose there’s no need for the control to be next to the radio - so I just setup in the kitchen and ran the cables out the door. This temporary setup just used a big LiFePO4 battery for radio and ATU, and that lasted the whole time. For my testing I wanted to use FT4/8, so I hooked up the G90 to my laptop. It’s been a long time since I’ve used the G90 with WSJTX, and that ended up taking me a while to sort out. I wanted to use the IC-705 as it’s so easy to use with a computer, however, this doesn’t work with the ATU. The CG3000 will automatically match the frequency when it receives rf of about 3-5W. The IC-705 has a protection system that will immediately reduce the output power to 1W when it detects a high SWR, this means it won’t trigger the tuning. I’ve seen people online use a manual tuner in between the 705 and ATU to prevent the 705 dropping the power and getting it to tune, they then bypass the manual one. Of course the <a href="https://icomuk.co.uk/AH-705-HF-50-MHz-automatic-antenna-tuner/4051/1359/41/">AH-705</a> would be ideal for this situation and work effortlessly, perhaps perfect for portable/mobile setups. After some faffing things were fine. I could always put the radio into AM and hit the PTT and I could hear the relays working and watch the SWR drop.</p>
<p>It tuned every band from 80m to 10m, most were virtually 1.0 except 30m and 17m which were nearly 2, not sure why that was but they still worked fine and I made many contacts on 30m. I put out a test CQ on 20m to see what was what and the first pskreporter view was pleasing. I should’ve saved the pskreporter view after my first 24 hours operation but I forgot.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="pskreporter.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7" title="Good Tx on 20m"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/something-for-the-weekend/pskreporter.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Good Tx on 20m"></a></p>
<figcaption>Good Tx on 20m</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>By the time I had it all sorted out on the first day, it was pretty late at night, so I had a look on 80m, 60m, and 40m. Lots of activity on 60m which I’ve never really been on, so that was fun, and I spent most of the evening there. The next day I tried as many bands as I could. Conditions weren’t the greatest but I still managed some nice contacts with a few new DX locations. I did notice I could hear all around the world, and many places I’d never heard before, so that was fun too. The most exciting from a DX perspective was 15m, particularly early evening, there seemed to be several openings both east and west. They’d come and go, but around long enough to make a QSO.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="qsos-2.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-8" title="My weekend’s activity"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/something-for-the-weekend/qsos-2.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="My weekend’s activity"></a></p>
<figcaption>My weekend’s activity</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Highlights included California, Uruguay, Kyrgyzstan, Svalbard, Japan and Australia. I had potential to get some South Asia, pskreporter showed I was heard there, but never managed to get a QSO. These were all with 20W FT8 from the G90.</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<caption>Activity Summary</caption>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th style="text-align: center;">Band</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">QSOs</th>
<th>Highlights</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: center;">80m</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">2</td>
<td>Ukraine</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: center;">60m</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">10</td>
<td>Aland Islands</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: center;">40m</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">5</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: center;">30m</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">17</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: center;">20m</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">6</td>
<td>Australia, Svalbard</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: center;">17m</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">2</td>
<td>California</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: center;">15m</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">16</td>
<td>Barbados, Uruguay, Brazil, Kyrgyzstan, Japan</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>All in all, 30 countries, three or four new DX, and furthest contact was with VK3JLM, at 16,864 km. Pretty good I think!</p>
<p>Sunday afternoon, it was time to pack it away, and this is when I realised the ground rod might not have been such a good idea. A rod hammered over 0.5m into the ground doesn’t tend to want to come out that easily. Several places online suggested a jack to lift it out, I don’t have one of those, and someone suggested a drill and watering the ground. So that’s what I did. You have to be careful as the drill wants to turn and the rod doesn’t…but once it’s loosened off, then drilling and pulling up brings it out.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="removal.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-9" title="Bish bash Bosch"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/something-for-the-weekend/removal.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Bish bash Bosch"></a></p>
<figcaption>Bish bash Bosch</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Now all that’s left is to figure out how to set it up more permanently. Ideally it needs to go away from the house, but then it needs a lot of cabling running around the garden. There’s also the fact that it’s not the most attractive thing in the garden, even I admit that, and the best place is probably in full view of the kitchen and lounge. I’ve read about people painting them grey/blue to soften their impact on the surroundings. I’ll have to think about it. Probably for now, it’ll be temporary setups, and hopefully I’ll get slicker at that so I can pop it up for the day/evening and then take it down in the morning and not get in anyone’s way. MM0OPX has a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cl7830vNGjo">nice video</a> on quickly setting up a spiderbeam.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Vertical</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/something-for-the-weekend/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 22 Aug 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/something-for-the-weekend/qsos.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="81" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Hill of Garvock</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-085/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="coos.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Beasts of the land"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-085/coos.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Beasts of the land"></a></p>
<figcaption>Beasts of the land</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>In the land of Aberdeenshire, in the rolling hills and verdant fields, there lies a summit of ancient repute: the Hill of Garvock. High above the plains it stands, crowned with a tower of stone that pierces the sky like the dark spire of Barad-dûr itself. And though it is not the Eye of Sauron that watches from its heights, it is nonetheless guarded—by a herd of formidable beasts, more docile in appearance but no less territorial than the fell orcs of Mordor. These were not the servants of some dark lord, but of a farmer, who tended his cows with the same care one might afford to a legion of fearsome trolls.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="warning.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="A warning left by a previous traveler"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-085/warning.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A warning left by a previous traveler"></a></p>
<figcaption>A warning left by a previous traveler</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Yet, it was to this very summit that our company was bound, for in the air lay a quest most urgent: the activation of the Hill of Garvock, a task that would call forth the wizard’s skill in communicating across the very ether, from the highest point in the land.</p>
<p>I, the wizard of our company, bore the mantle of Gandalf, though my power lay not in staff nor sword but in the ancient art of invisible communication. Deep within my pack lay a Kenwood D72, my 6m staff of carbon fiber, and the slim G that would beacon out into the surrounds. The winds would carry my signals to those far off in Aberdeen, and to those kindred spirits who also sought the heights to send their voices across the void. At my side marched four brave souls, each chosen for this journey by the fates, and not being legally allowed to be left at home alone.</p>
<p>There was Legolas, my eldest daughter, whose eyes were sharp and whose feet were swift. She would scout ahead, her keen senses attuned to the slightest disturbance in the fields. Princess Galadriel, my youngest daughter, whose beauty was only matched by her inability to carry anything, walked beside me, her grace a light in the darkening day. And then there were the two hobbits twins, whose hearts were as large as their stature was small, and whose constant complaining, kept the chill of the sea wind at bay.</p>
<p>We set forth from the edge of the Laurencekirk Viewpoint, the last outpost of civilisation before the untamed fields. The sky was overcast, and the air held the promise of rain, yet we were undeterred. Alas, we were also ill-prepared, with only half party bringing their cloaks. The path ahead led us across open land, where no tree or boulder might shield us from the vigilant eyes of the bovine sentinels.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="princess.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Suitable journeying attire"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-085/princess.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Suitable journeying attire"></a></p>
<figcaption>Suitable journeying attire</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The cows, vast in number and broad of horn, gazed upon us with suspicion as we approached their domain. Legolas, ever watchful, whispered of their movements. “They are gathering, Father,” she said, “forming a line as if to bar our passage.” I nodded, drawing my cloak about me as though it might ward off the cows’ ponderous gaze.</p>
<p>“Fear not, my children,” I said, raising my carbon-6 mast. “We have journeyed through lands more perilous than these (Edinburgh Airport customs border). Though the path is fraught with unseen dangers, we must press on.”</p>
<p>And so we did, our footsteps light but purposefully avoiding cow pats, as we crossed the meadow. The hobbits skipped merrily, laughing as they narrowly avoided an enormous pat, recently produced. Princess Galadriel’s voice, soft as a whispering brook, soothed the beasts as we passed, her words lost to the wind but not to the cows, who turned away as though under some enchantment.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="in-sight.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="The tower and its guard"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-085/in-sight.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="The tower and its guard"></a></p>
<figcaption>The tower and its guard</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>At last, we reached the final field before the tower, the summit of Garvock now within our grasp. The stone structure loomed above us, a sentinel of old, marking the land for miles around. As we stepped into the activation zone, the winds howled, and the clouds parted, allowing the briefest shaft of sunlight to illuminate our path.</p>
<p>I raised my staff and sent out the call. The air shimmered with VHF magic, and our presence was made known across the land. The summit was activated, our voices carried far and wide, across hill and valley, to others who awaited our signal.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="qsos.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="Those who heard our calls - including a brave soul a’top Ben Chonzie"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-085/qsos.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Those who heard our calls - including a brave soul a’top Ben Chonzie"></a></p>
<figcaption>Those who heard our calls - including a brave soul a’top Ben Chonzie</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>We awoke a wizard of exceptional experience, housed in our home town of Aberdeen, who’s voice had not been heard on 2m FM for over 20 years, but whose relentless questioning and detailed itemisation of his wizarding horde kept us within the range of the cows for longer than anyone was content with.</p>
<p>The quest was complete, and though the way back was still guarded by those bovine watchers, we knew the day was ours. With spirits high and laughter on our lips, we descended from the Hill of Garvock, in search of a cafe in Johnshaven and with the memory of our adventure etched forever in our hearts.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-085/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 18 Aug 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-085/cover.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Finally Making a LEO QSO</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/finally-making-a-leo-qso/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>After what feels <a href="../../../posts/2023/first-attempts-at-leo/">like ages</a> since I last ventured into the garden with my Yagi antenna and HT to attempt a contact via an FM satellite, I finally succeeded.</p>
<p>Last time I struggled with holding all the things, trying to find the satellite and using the radio. I only managed to hear for a short period and that was it. So I decided to make a phone holder which goes on the antenna. I’ve seen several people do this on YouTube, and there are lots of designs already made online. I printed this <a href="https://www.printables.com/model/69675-arrow-antenna-tripod-and-cellphone-mount">one</a>, and bought a phone holder from Amazon that screws in.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="iphone-arrow.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Phone Mount Ready"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/finally-making-a-leo-qso/iphone-arrow.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Phone Mount Ready"></a></p>
<figcaption>Phone Mount Ready</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>In practice it wasn’t quite as perfect as I thought it would be. It’s probably a few factors, not being perfectly aligned, maybe the metal in the antenna messes with the phone’s compass and perhaps other things but I had to hunt around a little for the satellite. Together with deciding at what orientation I should hold the antenna, and if it’s about time I change the frequency due to doppler, still left me feeling like I wasn’t going to have a chance.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="d72.jpeg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Radio and voice recorder"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/finally-making-a-leo-qso/d72.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Radio and voice recorder"></a></p>
<figcaption>Radio and voice recorder</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I did simplify the radio and audio end. Last time I had a series of cables from the radio splitting the audio into the voice recorder and into ear phones. This was either directly connected to the radio or via the mini-fist mic which has the three buttons on. I thought those buttons might be useful for swithcing VFO and adjusting the memories which have the doppler corrections pre-programmed.</p>
<p>This time I put the voice recorder in my shirt top pocket, and held the HT and used it directly. No audio cables. This cleared out the clutter and meant I had one hand on the yagi and one on the radio.</p>
<p>One Sunday evening in July I decided to go out and try it. I’d seen SO-50 was coming up and had a reasonable pass of around 10-15 minutes and at a good elevation. It was coming up over the neighbour’s house and then I would see it. I found it pretty quick and heard <a href="https://www.qrz.com/db/M5JFS">M5JFS</a> calling CQ. I replied but he made a QSO with someone else, however, he then ended with “I think there’s a GM5 station calling”. Here was my chance, and I made the contact!</p>
<figure class="figure">
<figcaption>
Audio of my first QSO
</figcaption>
<audio controls="" src="first-contact.ogg">
Your browser does not support the <code>audio</code> element.
</audio>
</figure>
<p>However, in the excitement I lost the satellite and only heard the very beginning of John talking about it being my first satellite contact. I did find the satellite again and people had moved on. I didn’t manage to make another contact on that pass.</p>
<p>Hearing John and myself on the audio made me “see” how slick an experienced satellite operator is and how much thinking I was doing just to say what I did 😅.</p>
<p>The D72 is a full duplex radio, however, I didn’t hear myself on the downlink. Now perhaps I didn’t have some setting right (although I checked it several times), but when I emailed John afterwards and mentioned it, he suggested that I wasn’t hearing myself when I tx’d because the sat downlink is weakish relative to my uplink power and it was a fairly low pass. So even with filtering in the radio, there might still have been some de-sense going on sufficient to knock out my downlink.</p>
<p>I have since made one more contact, also on SO-50, also not doing that great at keeping the satellite in my yagi’s path. I’ve heard people talk about printing out the sat’s path, and then working out landmarks around my house and what bearing they are, to then try and follow the path without the AR phone app.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="sarcnet.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="One of these looks good"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/finally-making-a-leo-qso/sarcnet.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="One of these looks good"></a></p>
<figcaption>One of these looks good</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>What I am thinking of doing, is building a rotator for the yagi, and having the computer control the tracking. I think it would be a fun project. I’ve started buying some of the pieces for this <a href="https://www.sarcnet.org/rotator-mk1.html">simple rotator</a> by the Australian SARCnet. It’s not a permanent setup but more of a sunny afternoon in the garden arrangement.</p>
<p>However, at the moment, because of the sunny afternoons, and the school holidays, I haven’t had time to make it, and any free time I have had, I’ve gone out to a SOTA summit instead! So it may take another 6 months before I build it and try for a satellite QSO again. Maybe next time I’ll try a SSB one!</p>
<section id="useful-links" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="useful-links">Useful links</h3>
<p>Some links I’ve saved for figuring out satellites:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.amsat.org/status/">AMSAT Status page</a></li>
<li><a href="https://hams.at/passes">Calculate passes at your location</a></li>
<li><a href="http://amsat.org.ar/pass.htm#top">AMSAT passes tracker</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amsat.org/fm-satellite-frequency-summary/">AMSAT FM Frequency summary</a></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>LEO</category>
  <category>satellites</category>
  <category>QSO</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/finally-making-a-leo-qso/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 14 Aug 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/finally-making-a-leo-qso/d72.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Glas Maol</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-012/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="glas-maol-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Ski Centre"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-012/glas-maol-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Ski Centre"></a></p>
<figcaption>Ski Centre</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I’ve had my eye on this summit for a while. It’s 8 points for starters, and I’ve been doing a lot of 1 pointers recently, but it’s quite the drive to get to, so whilst it doesn’t take long to climb, the total round trip is considerable. It’s also (just) over 1,000m high but the car park is at 670m, so the actual ascent is only 420m - very similar to some lower summits. Morven, a 4 point summit, was a 650m ascent!</p>
<p>The weather was sunny in Aberdeen when I left, and the forecast threaten rain later in the afternoon. I did my calculations and figured I’d be back in the car before the rain came. It’s only a 45-60 minute ascent.</p>
<p>You start in the upper car park at Glenshee ski centre, you can park right by the start of the track. The car park is £4 which you pay for via a website, except in the valley there’s no 4G+, so you need to wait until you’re up the first slope and get signal again before you can pay. The alternative is stop in at the cafe and pay, but I’d already parked and wanted to get going.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="glas-maol-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Perthshire border"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-012/glas-maol-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Perthshire border"></a></p>
<figcaption>Perthshire border</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="route.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="1.5km walk up 420m"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-012/route.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="1.5km walk up 420m"></a></p>
<figcaption>1.5km walk up 420m</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The route is fairly straight forward in summer. The path is obvious, although it had a lot of loose gravel in many places. There are a few ups and downs along the way but nothing too bad. The steepest part is beyond the ski lift buildings on the final rise up to the main plateau. The path looks obvious from a distance but when you’re on it, it blends in with the terrain. Again, lots of loose stones here but a steady pace and I was at the top.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="glas-maol-6.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="The steep part"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-012/glas-maol-6.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="The steep part"></a></p>
<figcaption>The steep part</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>It’s still another 600m or so until you get to the actual summit, and I could see it being very easy to get lost in low cloud at this point, especially on the way back, it’s wide and featureless. Luckily the cloud wasn’t low, it was overcast but the view was still amazing, and on a clear day it must be spectacular.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="glas-maol-5.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="Looking towards Braemar"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-012/glas-maol-5.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Looking towards Braemar"></a></p>
<figcaption>Looking towards Braemar</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="glas-maol-7.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="Looking south"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-012/glas-maol-7.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Looking south"></a></p>
<figcaption>Looking south</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I met another walker sitting in the cairn having his lunch. We spoke for a bit and then I looked for somewhere else to setup. A bit further away there were two smaller piles of rocks I thought I could shelter behind. The wind was persistent and I needed my hood to keep my ears warm.</p>
<p>I’ve taken to just activating summits with VHF if I can, not that I don’t like doing HF, I just enjoy the simplicity of using a handheld and speaking to the locals. This is particularly the case if I don’t want to be sitting around for a long time, and whilst the rain’s arrival was forecast to be later still, I didn’t really want to hang around more than necessary. I setup the slim G on the carbon-6 pole and started calling CQ.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="glas-maol-8.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7" title="CQ CQ SOTA"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-012/glas-maol-8.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="CQ CQ SOTA"></a></p>
<figcaption>CQ CQ SOTA</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I’d forgotten to spot, but I started on 145.500 MHz, the 2m calling frequency, and I’m used to 2m spotting not really helping. Stations started coming back to me from considerable distances, at least what I’m used to. Something I’m not used to is everyone asking to QSY to another frequency. The first caller who asked I sort of ignored his first request as I didn’t think it was necessary, but I did then move and we had a nice chat. I guess when there’s actually some activity or a big area it makes sense to move. I’ve just used to the 4-6 people on 2m when I’m on the lower summits nearer Aberdeen that it doesn’t matter if we talk for 15 minutes on the calling frequency as there’s no-one else!</p>
<p>My furthest was 92 miles right across the west coast to GM4OAS. I was only a 31 for him but we managed. Had GM0USI/M driving on the A90 between Perth and Dundee, and then a guy walking his dog somewhere in East Lothian carrying his boafeng with him. He just had a rubber duck on, but his signal was strong with me, his audio was a bit muffled at times though. He gave his call as M7SGX, and so I was confused where he was, thinking he was in England. However, he’d just chosen to omit the RSL. Unless I misheard him several times!<sup>1</sup></p>
<p>I didn’t get anyone back in Aberdeen but I had 8 which was plenty. I did spot myself and called some more but that was it. I heard someone else but I think it was a repeater and my VFO B happened to be on its frequency but I didn’t have it programmed in (assume it was the Dundee one). As it happens I don’t think any of the repeaters in my D72 are correct, and I should add the others around Scotland.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="qsos.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-8" title="QSOs 2m FM 5W"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-012/qsos.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="QSOs 2m FM 5W"></a></p>
<figcaption>QSOs 2m FM 5W</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The excitement of such far reaching FM contacts had kept me distracted from other walkers who were around and the cold wind. I looked up to see a few other people walking around, but no-one came to talk to me. I finished my lunch, debated about HF for a moment, but then decided I’d rather be getting home and packed up.</p>
<p>The walk down was trickier due to the scree patches and at one point I started marching off in the wrong direction as the path split. I could see the car park so I quickly realised the path wasn’t taking me down to it.</p>
<p>Next time I think a yagi and a radio with 2m SSB!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="selfie.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-9" title="Happy with 2m today"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-012/selfie.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Happy with 2m today"></a></p>
<figcaption>Happy with 2m today</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>I can’t find him on QRZ or anywhere so I do worry if I heard him wrong but I did asked 3 times as I kept thinking “M7?!”↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-012/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 09 Aug 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-012/glas-maol-4.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Craiglich</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-068/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>It’s the summer holidays and so the kids are home all the time, or we’re away etc. and I didn’t think I would get to do very much SOTA during the holidays. However, today the younger ones were off on a play date with some friends, so that just left my eldest and I at home. Left to her own devices she would spend all her time <strong>on</strong> devices! So I figured we should go climb a hill!</p>
<p>My usual research method of browsing the <a href="https://sotl.as/map/">sotlas map</a> and asking the WhatsApp group led to Craiglich with the prospect of a tea room afterwards. The tea room was the real winner here. 🍰</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="route.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Path to the top"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-068/route.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Path to the top"></a></p>
<figcaption>Path to the top</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>There’s a small car park on the north side of the road and after climbing a rickerty gate, we were off!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="craiglich-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Happy to start"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-068/craiglich-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Happy to start"></a></p>
<figcaption>Happy to start</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The path starts along through a field and then enters the forest. It’s a little wet and boggy at first, but nothing major. The pathway is quite narrow with heather and pines growing close by. I was wearing shorts and was beginning to regret that idea on the grounds of tick risk! Although I managed the whole walk without any incident.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="craiglich-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Through the forest"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-068/craiglich-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Through the forest"></a></p>
<figcaption>Through the forest</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>There’s only one real turn that you have to look for in the forest, where you bear to the left to climb the hill. At this point it’s a little steeper but overall the path is gentle and very pleasant. You come out of the forest into the open area with nice purple heather covering the hillside. I’d recently bought <a href="https://apps.apple.com/gb/app/sota-goat/id590206108">Sotagoat app</a>, so my daugther was using it to track the summit. It’s a convenient app for finding the summit and telling you when you’re in the activation area. It offers an offline database too, so you can find information without phone reception, and finally spotting is easy from it. Probably does more but I’ve not looked into it too much yet.</p>
<p>We reached the top and I setup my slim G on the mast on the cairn, with the D72 and called CQ on 2m FM. I spoke to the locals, including Chris, MM7RVC, who’d literally just completed his intermediate exam and had passed. So we all congratulated him on that! I also spoke with Bruce, MM6BWS, who was a new local contact for me.</p>
<p><a href="craiglich-5.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-068/craiglich-5.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p>I did hear another station on a summit, and heard him having a QSO with MM7MOX (Andy), although I couldn’t hear Andy. Looking at MM7MOX’s activations and logs, he was on Torlum (GM/SS-227) at the time I think it must’ve been Lee, MM7LEF/P, on Scald Law (GM/SS-125) that I could hear. He was working 2m FM at exactly the time I could hear him as it was interrupting my chat with Bruce. Pretty amazing as it’s almost 150 km away and there are big hills between us. Aircraft scatter? I don’t know, I should email him!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="mm7lef.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="That is quite the distance!"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-068/mm7lef.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="That is quite the distance!"></a></p>
<figcaption>That is quite the distance!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I got my four and this trip was not about contacts, so we packed and headed down the hill in preparation for the best part of the trip!</p>
<p>We were going to go to Tarland tea room but when I looked at the map I saw there was one in Lumphanan and that was on our route home, so seemed a better choice. Alas! it proved no good as they only took cash and I had none. The nearest cash machine was miles away and, being a Sunday, the local post office was shut. That was a shame as it looked a lovely little tea room. So we continued on into Banchory and found somewhere there. The Birdhouse cafe. It was fine - a bit too hipster coffee house for me but I had a cup of tea and my daugther a can of diet coke.</p>
<p>Our other task was to find some jam sugar after our strawberry picking, and it seems the only store in Aberdeenshire that had any was the Morrisons in Banchory - whilst it was the last shop we visited it wasn’t the first!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="craiglich-6.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="Happy smiles all round"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-068/craiglich-6.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Happy smiles all round"></a></p>
<figcaption>Happy smiles all round</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Maybe we’ll manage another in the holidays…and I’ll have to be better prepared on the tea shop side!</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-068/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jul 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-068/craiglich-5.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
