<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>📻 GM5ALX Radio</title>
<link>https://gm5alx.uk/</link>
<atom:link href="https://gm5alx.uk/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>So many rabbit holes, you’ll struggle to find ground</description>
<generator>quarto-1.6.39</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Sun, 08 Dec 2024 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Carn a’Bhodaich</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-ws-304/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>We were up in Inverness for a swimming competition and I wondered if there were any summits I could manage. Luckily this one is only about 15 minutes from the pool and a fairly short walk up to the top. I dropped off for warm up and then headed up the hill. I’d read it was a bit of a soggy climb, and after the storm the past few days, there was a lot of water around. The path was more like a stream and in places there was deep standing water. It really only got better when climbing to the final top.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhodaich-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Summit in the distance"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-ws-304/bhodaich-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Summit in the distance"></a></p>
<figcaption>Summit in the distance</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhodaich-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Fallen tree on the path"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-ws-304/bhodaich-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Fallen tree on the path"></a></p>
<figcaption>Fallen tree on the path</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The final section of the walk doesn’t really have a path up to the summit, the track just continues around the hill and away, so it was a case of scrambling up the heather and trying to avoid the streams coming down. It was cold but still on the way up, but as soon as I was on the summit the wind was strong. I found a low spot with a post and some shelter and setup on 20m there. As I wanted to be quick, I was going for the 5.5m vertical with counterpoises.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhodaich-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="At the top"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-ws-304/bhodaich-4.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="At the top"></a></p>
<figcaption>At the top</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhodaich-5.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Station location"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-ws-304/bhodaich-5.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Station location"></a></p>
<figcaption>Station location</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Not too busy on 20m, but enough in the log with 9 QSOs. I packed up and headed down the way I came and back to Inverness.</p>
<p>Some good views of the hills from the summit and from the parking area. I’ll come back next time I’m in the area, particularly if it’s during winter bonus!</p>
<p><a href="bhodaich-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-ws-304/bhodaich-3.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p><a href="bhodaich-6.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-ws-304/bhodaich-6.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-ws-304/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 08 Dec 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-ws-304/bhodaich-4.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Mount Blair</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-035/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>In my wisdom to save walking 200m down the road to the start of the track, I decided to just head straight up the hill. Well this turned into a very wet affair, and I gradually made my way across to the path, like I should’ve from the start.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="mt-blair-8.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Summit ahead in the blue skies"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-035/mt-blair-8.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Summit ahead in the blue skies"></a></p>
<figcaption>Summit ahead in the blue skies</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>After the drive over the Mount Blair and looking at the summit with clear blue skies backdrop, the cloud started to move in and blue became grey.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="mt-blair-5.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Skies turning grey"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-035/mt-blair-5.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Skies turning grey"></a></p>
<figcaption>Skies turning grey</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="mt-blair-7.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Looking back at Mealna Letter"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-035/mt-blair-7.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Looking back at Mealna Letter"></a></p>
<figcaption>Looking back at Mealna Letter</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Some SSE folks were up doing things on the mast. They’d come up in their 8 wheeled buggy, some kind of Argocat. They were finishing up as I was looking at the trig and other features. They gave me a cheerful wave as they tootled past to go down the hill.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="mt-blair-6.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Summit things"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-035/mt-blair-6.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Summit things"></a></p>
<figcaption>Summit things</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p><a href="mt-blair-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-035/mt-blair-4.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="mt-blair-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="SSE mobile"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-035/mt-blair-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="SSE mobile"></a></p>
<figcaption>SSE mobile</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Lots of fences and rocks and all sorts to setup on the top. I decided to the south of the main mast by the fence would be good. As I had no guys, I needed something decent to strap the mast to, and setup on 40m. I had a quick QSO with Gerald again, who was on his way down, and I wanted to make this quick as it had started raining and the cold wind wasn’t enjoyable. Not as busy on the band as Monday but enough.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="mt-blair-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7" title="Station"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-035/mt-blair-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Station"></a></p>
<figcaption>Station</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Packed up and headed back down to the car. I’d hoped Gerald and I could’ve found a nice cafe or bar to say hello, but there aren’t many options in the area. In fact, none as far as I could tell. There is the Glenisla Hotel, although that seems to shut its bar/cafe out of season on non-Friday/weekend days. So I waited by the car for Gerald to come by. We had a little chat and nice to put a face to a voice! Then off back home.</p>
<p>It’s a nice area with lots of good hills in close proximity. It would make for a good group SOTA outing - perhaps doing two hills each and rotating around, then back to the hotel bar for a celebration afterwards.</p>
<p>Now I’ve got to try and get back down there to Crock, <a href="https://summits.sota.org.uk/summit/GM/ES-056">GM/ES-056</a>, Hare Cairn, <a href="https://summits.sota.org.uk/summit/GM/ES-063">GM/ES-063</a>, Corwharn, <a href="https://summits.sota.org.uk/summit/GM/ES-048">GM/ES-048</a>, and maybe even Cat Law, <a href="https://summits.sota.org.uk/summit/GM/ES-044">GM/ES-044</a>, before the winter bonus period ends!</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-035/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2024 13:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-035/mt-blair-1.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Ben Gulabin</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-077/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><a href="gulabin-13.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-077/gulabin-13.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p>After quite the adventure on <a href="https://summits.sota.org.uk/summit/GM/ES-040">G</a><a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-040/">M/ES-040</a>, and reports from Fraser as he drove down of Glenshee being quite the white, we were wondering what might be in store. Again, a look at the snow gate cameras showed us it had all gone! The Glenshee camera shows you the side of Ben Gulabin. Gerald was heading up Corwharn, <a href="https://summits.sota.org.uk/summit/GM/ES-048">GM/ES-048</a>, and I on Ben Gulabin. Somewhere between Mount Blair and Gulabin the quickest route from west Aberdeen flips from via the A90 to the A93, and so I drove the scenic route. The route up Gulabin is another straight forward one. Park off the road by the start and follow the path up.</p>
<p><a href="gulabin-12.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-077/gulabin-12.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p><a href="gulabin-9.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-077/gulabin-9.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p><a href="gulabin-10.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-077/gulabin-10.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p>There’s a bit of a stream to cross, and then quite a boggy area once you turn left off the track up to the summit. Probably made worse by the just recent snow melt.</p>
<p><a href="gulabin-8.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-077/gulabin-8.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p>What started as another lovely morning, had started to turn a little. The wind was cold and the clouds were creeping in. It was still nice enough on Ben Gulabin but this would be the best of the day.</p>
<p><a href="gulabin-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-077/gulabin-3.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p>I came to setup on 2m, and found I’d left my guys at home. This was even more annoying as they were in my bag from yesterday, and I’d gone through everything this morning before leaving and obviously left them on the garage floor. So I held the mast and carried on. It didn’t take too long to get four, and then speak with Gerald on his summit. His phone hadn’t been charging properly and so was dead, which meant he couldn’t spot. However, he shared his info and I could spot for him on 2m SSB, which worked out well. After that I packed up and headed back to the car and drive round to the start of Mount Blair.</p>
<p><a href="gulabin-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-077/gulabin-4.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p><a href="gulabin-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-8"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-077/gulabin-4.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-077/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2024 09:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-077/gulabin-13.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Cnap Chaochan Aitinn</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-040/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Fraser shared last night that the snow gates were shut due to the snow. When the sun came up this morning, it was a glorious sunny, crisp, cold day with amazing views of the hills. At 8:30am when I was about to leave the gates were still shut…I was going with a work friend up the hill and he felt confident the gates would be opened by 10. After passing endless signs telling me the road was closed, and finally at 10:15 am when I arrived at Cock Bridge…they were still shut. My friend was about 15 minutes behind me, and so I waited for him by Corgarff Castle.</p>
<p><a href="cnap-chaochan-28.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-040/cnap-chaochan-28.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p>I’d looked at an alternative route to the summit from here, in case the gates were closed. It is possible but it’s twice as far, at around 18.5 km <em>each way</em>.</p>
<p><a href="cnap-chaochan-27.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-040/cnap-chaochan-27.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p>This was too far for my friend and if I was going to do it, he’d maybe only come part way. I was also trying to calculate how long we’d be and if I’d get back home in time for birthday tea with the family! As we were chatting we heard a loud rumbling of a gritter coming along the road. We watched him go up past the trees to where the gate is…road noise stops…engine quietens…CLANG! of metal against metal… that would be the gates being opened! So we headed back and got to the snow gates and sure enough he’d opened them and was heading up. He gave us the thumbs up and we followed.</p>
<p><a href="cnap-chaochan-23.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-040/cnap-chaochan-23.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p>Once he opened the gates at the ski centre we were off to Tomintoul. We parked in the village opposite the hotel, rather than the parking on the route, mostly to be certain we could drive in and out again, and got ready to roll. At 9.9 km each way, this was a much more reasonable distance, and on a good day (i.e.&nbsp;not today) would probably only take about an hour to 1:15hrs to ride.</p>
<p><a href="cnap-chaochan-26.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-040/cnap-chaochan-26.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p>The track down to the bridge (around 5 km) was absolutely treacherous with ice and in some places was just sheet ice across the whole track. I only fell off once and somehow managed to do a magic trick of falling onto my feet in a standing position as the bike slid out from under me and away down the road. We dropped our seats, put out our feet as stablisers and skated down some parts of it. The track is also quite undulating and several ups and downs to make you groan.</p>
<p>I just happened to check my phone and saw Fraser had spotted. We were down in the valley by the river and I didn’t expect much luck (although I was getting phone signal of course), and put out a call to him. He was in a QSO with GM0HLV but then we made contact. Chris was setting up but we kept going and when I checked later I’d missed him.</p>
<p><a href="cnap-chaochan-18.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-040/cnap-chaochan-18.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p><a href="cnap-chaochan-19.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-040/cnap-chaochan-19.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p>The bridge across the river wasn’t much better, probably made worse by the fact cold air can get under as well as above it, but we made it over okay. We met some coos at the remote Wester Gaulrig Cottage, and at this point had probably been going for about 50 minutes.</p>
<p><a href="cnap-chaochan-20.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-040/cnap-chaochan-20.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p>We were past half way but still plenty to go, and now the steeper parts of the route were upon us. We could see the summit in the distance, and partially doubted that it was correct as “it seemed so far away”. We were correct, it was the summit!</p>
<p><a href="cnap-chaochan-13.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-8"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-040/cnap-chaochan-13.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p>I dumped my bike at the base of the final ascent, but my friend Mike, on his ebike, gave it a shot to get to the top. The snow had drifted much more here and snow pattern told tales of strong winds. The cloud was coming in now and the good views across to Ben Avon and surroundings had gone, with only huge clouds looming over the distant high summits.</p>
<p><a href="cnap-chaochan-16.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-9"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-040/cnap-chaochan-16.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p>We made it at 12:30, 1.5 hours after leaving Tomintoul, and much later than my alert. Fraser and Chris were just back at their landys for my first two QSOs on Cnap Chaochan Aitinn. I called a few more times on 2m but didn’t have any luck. I wasn’t that patient with it though and chose not to setup the slim g but just go straight to 40m … I’d come all this way, I couldn’t leave without the 40 on 40 on 40! The wind was brutal and oh so cold. We did have some equipment that we could hide behind, and took some shelter there whilst I tried to setup on 40m.</p>
<p><a href="cnap-chaochan-5.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-10"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-040/cnap-chaochan-5.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-040/cnap-chaochan-6.jpg" class="img-fluid">I’m sure I could’ve used the small towers there to my benefit, but I was also wary of the wind turbine and getting wire caught in it, so I setup my mast down wind of it, trying to keep it close enough so I could operate from the shelter. Typically, as soon as I spotted and called CQ once the mast moved, then fell. It was tricky finding ground to get the pegs in for the guys…so I recruited another guy to hold the mast whilst he ate his super noodles!</p>
<p><a href="cnap-chaochan-12.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-11"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-040/cnap-chaochan-12.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p><a href="cnap-chaochan-15.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-12"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-040/cnap-chaochan-15.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p>I managed 6 on 40m, including a very nice summit to summit with Colin, M1BUU, as above, before I had to call QRT on the pile up. It was just too cold in the wind, even in the “shelter”. Quickly packed up and whilst admiring the views I realised the wind turbine noise had stopped and there was, in fact, no wind whatsoever! I got the HT back out and messaged Dave, MM7HMA, a local who’s just past his test and was keen to get some QSOs, and we had a nice chat. The stillness didn’t last and the return of the wind reminded us it was time to head back.</p>
<p><a href="cnap-chaochan-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-13"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-040/cnap-chaochan-3.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p><a href="cnap-chaochan-7.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-14"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-040/cnap-chaochan-7.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p><a href="cnap-chaochan-11.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-15"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-040/cnap-chaochan-11.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p>Back to the bike - still there 😅- and back to the car. It’s mostly downhill, but still a few steep climbs as the path goes up and down. The temperature had come up a little, and a fair amount of ice had melted so the journey was less hazardous. I was back home in plenty of time.</p>
<p><a href="cnap-chaochan-9.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-16"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-040/cnap-chaochan-9.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p>Not quite the S2S action hoped for, but still a successful trip and good day out! 🎂Plus one more complete for Fraser 😅</p>
<p>I think no-one comes here as there are other summits in the area you’d do first, but the fact you can cycle right to the top does make it quite a unique one, plus with plenty of refreshment options in Tomintoul for afterwards!</p>
<p><a href="cnap-chaochan-14.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-17"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-040/cnap-chaochan-14.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-040/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-040/cnap-chaochan-27.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Meall Mor</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-058/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><a href="meallmor-13.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-058/meallmor-13.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p>Off to the park on the patch of dirt outside the gate into the forest and then up the track. Again, an easy route to follow although the climb up to the summit along the wall, whilst sheltered, is just heather and quite steep in places. Another summit benefitting from a nice wall to shelter behind, I setup again on HF and this time tried 20m.</p>
<p><a href="meallmor-9.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-058/meallmor-9.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p><a href="meallmor-8.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-058/meallmor-8.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p><a href="meallmor-5.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-058/meallmor-5.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p>I had a big pile up on 20m, and whilst I wanted to be packing up at 3pm, I kept saying “QRZ?”! It did eventually die down about 10 past, and I packed up and headed down. The setting sun cast a strange light over the land - my phone camera doesn’t do it justice.</p>
<p><a href="meallmor-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-058/meallmor-4.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p><a href="meallmor-6.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-058/meallmor-6.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p><a href="meallmor-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-058/meallmor-1.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p><a href="meallmor-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-8"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-058/meallmor-2.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-058/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 15:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-058/meallmor-2.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Mealna Letter</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-043/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="mletter.jpeg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Route"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-043/mletter.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Route"></a></p>
<figcaption>Route</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>A bit further to drive this time to the start of Mealna Letter, but plenty of space to park by the path entrance into the woods.</p>
<p><a href="mealna-11.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-043/mealna-11.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-043/mealna-10.jpg" class="img-fluid">The track up is straight forward, just follow the track. When you come out of the trees, then the path disappears and you just make your way up the hill. It’s hard to go wrong as you’re aiming for the junction of the walls on the top of the first hill.</p>
<p><a href="mealna-9.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-043/mealna-9.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p><a href="mealna-7.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-043/mealna-7.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p>You then follow the wall along the top until you get to the summit. If you’re lucky the wall can be a wind break and makes it a pleasant walk. The summit cairn is away from the wall, and is worth visiting as it offers some nice views down to the loch below.</p>
<p><a href="mealna-6.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-043/mealna-6.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p><a href="mealna-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-043/mealna-4.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p>The sky was still clear and offered stunning views all around.</p>
<p><a href="mealna-5.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-043/mealna-5.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p>After two summits on VHF, I thought I’d try HF, particularly with the nice wall to shelter behind, and so setup for 40m.</p>
<p><a href="mealna-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-8"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-043/mealna-1.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p>I had a nice run on 40m, and start chasing summits on other bands. By this time it was 1:30pm and I was 1:30 ahead of schedule. I was starting to debate if I had enough time for a fourth! Ideally, I wanted to be leaving the area at 3:30pm to get home by 5, so if I could run back to the car by 2pm, then I’d have time…not for Mount Blair but for it’s neighbour, Meall Mor, <a href="https://summits.sota.org.uk/summit/GM/ES-058">GM/ES-058</a>. Time for one <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-058/">Meall Mor!</a></p>
<p><a href="mealna-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-9"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-043/mealna-3.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p><a href="mealna-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-10"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-043/mealna-2.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-043/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 12:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-043/mealna-1.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Monamenach</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-028/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>I’ve been planning on doing the “four Folda fours”, specifically Mount Blair, <a href="https://summits.sota.org.uk/summit/GM/ES-035">GM/ES-035</a>, Mealna Letter, <a href="https://summits.sota.org.uk/summit/GM/ES-043">GM/ES-043</a>, Monamenach, <a href="https://summits.sota.org.uk/summit/GM/ES-028">GM/ES-028</a> and Badandun Hill, <a href="https://summits.sota.org.uk/summit/GM/ES-037">GM/ES-037</a>. However, I couldn’t find a route that I could walk the lot in one day, certainly not one December day in the light. I did find that I could chain together four individual walks and drive between the starting points. But I wasn’t sure if I could fit it all in, leaving home at 7am and being back by 5pm. So I settled on multiple visits. Plus Gerald, G4OIG, was going to be visiting at the end of the week and doing some of the summits in the area and I thought it would be nice to meet in person, as well as a chance for 2m S2Ss, so I’d want to return on the Thursday.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="monamenach-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Car park in the morning"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-028/monamenach-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Car park in the morning"></a></p>
<figcaption>Car park in the morning</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>For the Monday, I’d decided on Monamenach, Badandun Hill and then Mealna Letter, and then the Thursday I’d do Ben Gulabin, <a href="https://summits.sota.org.uk/summit/GM/CS-077">GM/CS-077</a>, then Mount Blair. Interestingly the last person on Ben Gulabin was Gerald, almost exactly a year ago! This would let me have a S2S with Gerald and then meet him at the bottom of Mount Blair afterwards.</p>
<p>As Gerald was visiting, we knew the weather would be bad. It was forecast to snow overnight, and I was concerned about the roads, but looking on the <a href="https://www.snowgatecameras.co.uk/">snow gate cameras</a> in the morning, it seemed like it was okay. I set off just after 7am, to arrive around 8:40am. First stop was Monamenach, the highest of the group.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="monamenach.jpeg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Route taken"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-028/monamenach.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Route taken"></a></p>
<figcaption>Route taken</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>It was a nice clear day, although chilly and windy - particularly on the summits - and brisk walk up from parking by the river, soon got me to the top of the hill.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="monamenach-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Summit on right"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-028/monamenach-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Summit on right"></a></p>
<figcaption>Summit on right</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p><a href="monamenach-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-028/monamenach-3.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p><a href="monamenach-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-028/monamenach-4.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p>Whilst there are a lot of handy posts at the summit, there was no shelter and it was blowing an icy gale. I followed the fence line down a little, and found a rock to hide behind. I setup on 2m and called my first CQ of the morning. It wasn’t too long and I had 4 contacts across Edinburgh and Glasgow. Fraser and others tried calling and listening back in Aberdeen area, but no luck. It started to sleet and I still had two more to go, so time to return to the car.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="monamenach-6.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="Across to Badandun Hill"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-028/monamenach-6.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Across to Badandun Hill"></a></p>
<figcaption>Across to Badandun Hill</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="monamenach-8.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7" title="Summit cairn of fence posts"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-028/monamenach-8.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Summit cairn of fence posts"></a></p>
<figcaption>Summit cairn of fence posts</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="monamenach-5.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-8" title="At the summit"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-028/monamenach-5.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="At the summit"></a></p>
<figcaption>At the summit</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="monamenach-9.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-9" title="A small sheltered spot from the wind"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-028/monamenach-9.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A small sheltered spot from the wind"></a></p>
<figcaption>A small sheltered spot from the wind</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="monamenach-11.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-10" title="Back down though the snow"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-028/monamenach-11.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Back down though the snow"></a></p>
<figcaption>Back down though the snow</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p><a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-037/">Time for hill number 2!</a></p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-028/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 09:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-028/monamenach-8.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Mona Gowan</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-034/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>A Friday off and time to find a summit. Weather hasn’t been great but looked mild today, although could be windy. Mona Gowan is a straight forward 4-pointer which has a few routes up to it. I chose the most direct from the west, off the Old Military road. I’d driven 20 minutes and some flags flapping in the breeze reminded me I’d forgotten to pack my mast! I decided it was best to return home and get the mast. Although the summit has a large cairn and I could’ve tried laying the wire over it.</p>
<p>The route is straight forward, just follow the fence line and eventually you’ll see the cairn on the left. There’s a reasonable valley to across before getting to the summit, so there’s uphill on the way back too!</p>
<p>The wind was surprisingly calm when I reached the top and I set up on 2m and 40m. Things were going well but then the wind picked up and it managed to cause the wire to come off the end of the mast and I suddenly saw the SWR maxing out the scale. Decided to call it a day and head home.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="monagowan-14.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Sunny over towards Brown Cow Hill"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-034/monagowan-14.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Sunny over towards Brown Cow Hill"></a></p>
<figcaption>Sunny over towards Brown Cow Hill</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="monagowan-13.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Looking south at the start"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-034/monagowan-13.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Looking south at the start"></a></p>
<figcaption>Looking south at the start</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="monagowan-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Snow filled stream valleys"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-034/monagowan-4.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Snow filled stream valleys"></a></p>
<figcaption>Snow filled stream valleys</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="monagowan-7.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Snow patches in the cloud"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-034/monagowan-7.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Snow patches in the cloud"></a></p>
<figcaption>Snow patches in the cloud</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="monagowan-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="Summit in sight"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-034/monagowan-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Summit in sight"></a></p>
<figcaption>Summit in sight</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="monagowan-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="At the top"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-034/monagowan-3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="At the top"></a></p>
<figcaption>At the top</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="monagowan-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7" title="CQ CQ!"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-034/monagowan-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="CQ CQ!"></a></p>
<figcaption>CQ CQ!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-034/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-034/monagowan-7.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Calibrating the KX2 by ear</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/calibrating-kx2-by-ear/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>On my last <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-011/">SOTA activiation</a>, a couple of reports said I was off-frequency. At the weekend I setup the KX2 in the garden and arranged for a <a href="https://dk1mi.radio/">friend</a> to listen to me and see if I was really off-frequency or if I’d somehow managed to knock the VFO or turn on XIT etc. on the mountain top and not realise.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="kx2-cal-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Calibration setting"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/calibrating-kx2-by-ear/kx2-cal-3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Calibration setting"></a></p>
<figcaption>Calibration setting</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>We had a QSO and he recorded me a few times, once “normally” with the KX2, once with XIT on and then again using the G90. This was very helpful as I could hear my voice was a little high normally, and so I needed to XIT down. I’d guessed at 0.5 MHz but that was slightly too much. The G90 QSO was a nice benchmark as well. Whilst I was swapping to the G90 a US station called Micheal and he ended up talking to him for a while! It was Micheal who then suggested that as I’ve got two radios I can just use them to test myself, without having to deal with propagation and everything else!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="calibration.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Calibration instructions"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/calibrating-kx2-by-ear/calibration.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Calibration instructions"></a></p>
<figcaption>Calibration instructions</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The KX2 manual details what needs to be done to calibrate the radio. It’s fairly straight forward to do, but you need a reference frequency in order to calibrate it. This can either be from a signal generator or a known accurate broadcast. A well known one is <a href="https://www.nist.gov/pml/time-and-frequency-division/time-distribution/radio-station-wwv">WWV</a>, the time station from America, which broadcasts on 5, 10, 15, 20 and 25 MHz. It announces the time and has a nice carrier to lock onto. I tried listening for WWV but had no luck on any bands. I did think I heard a carrier on 10 MHz and tried to use it to calibrate the radio but that put me wildly off.</p>
<p>However, all is not lost, as you can just manually adjust the reference frequency on the radio via the VFO dial, and that’s where listening to my own voice is beneficial.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="kx2-cal-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Checking the bands"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/calibrating-kx2-by-ear/kx2-cal-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Checking the bands"></a></p>
<figcaption>Checking the bands</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>It’s pretty straight forward to do, you put a dummy load on the transceiver you want to transmit from and I just had some wire plugged into the other. Perhaps they’ll both work with dummy loads, or perhaps even no antenna on the receiving station! I found that 40m was fine but 20m and higher frequencies were off by 0.3-0.4 MHz. So I iterated back and forth between changing the reference calibration frequency and then testing my audio again. After a few attempts I was pretty happy and everything sounded good to me.</p>
<p>In the end I went from 24,999,380 to 24,999,440. I’ve yet to try it on the air but my tests sounded good to me. I think if I wanted to improve the accuracy, I’d used CW and then I could lock onto the signal. I might still do that but for now my “by ear” will do.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>KX2</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/calibrating-kx2-by-ear/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/posts/2024/calibrating-kx2-by-ear/kx2-cal-1.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Beinn a’Chaorainn</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-011/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Continuing my journey from <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-005/">Beinn Mheadoin</a>…</p>
<p>It was pretty much downhill and then back up. It was now about 1230 and I was a little behind schedule, but enjoying the sun and rainbows. I looked back over to Mheadoin and, typically, now it was in the sun too!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="chaorainn-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Across to Chaorainn"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-011/chaorainn-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Across to Chaorainn"></a></p>
<figcaption>Across to Chaorainn</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="chaorainn-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="🌈"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-011/chaorainn-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="🌈"></a></p>
<figcaption>🌈</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="chaorainn-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Beinn Mheadoin in the sun"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-011/chaorainn-3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Beinn Mheadoin in the sun"></a></p>
<figcaption>Beinn Mheadoin in the sun</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The climb up Beinn a’Chaorainn starts quite steep with loose gravel but soon turns into a nice climb, aside from the boulder patch, but you can mostly work around it. As I got higher the wind picked up again. The summit cairn didn’t look very impressive, but actually offered decent shelter and I was quite comfortable behind it.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="chaorainn-6.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="At the summit"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-011/chaorainn-6.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="At the summit"></a></p>
<figcaption>At the summit</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="chaorainn-7.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="Station (in the process of being dismantled!)"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-011/chaorainn-7.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Station (in the process of being dismantled!)"></a></p>
<figcaption>Station (in the process of being dismantled!)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>This time I tried 20m and the band was much more enjoyable, with a strong signal everywhere between south of England and Greece around 1,700 miles away.</p>
<p>Denis, MM0CBC on holiday from Wales, was on his way up Ben Tinnes, GM/ES-021, and by the time I was done with HF he was just setting up there, so we had a nice 2m S2S.</p>
<p>It was 1345 and I really needed to be back at Linn of Dee by 1530, to get home in time, so after getting distracted taking more photos, I hot stepped it back down and retrieved my bike. A reasonable number of other cyclists and hikers out, I didn’t meet any on the summits but along the main routes. It seemed now was the best weather of the day and plnety to enjoy as I cycled back.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="chaorainn-8.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="Sun shining on Beinn Mheadoin"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-011/chaorainn-8.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Sun shining on Beinn Mheadoin"></a></p>
<figcaption>Sun shining on Beinn Mheadoin</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="chaorainn-9.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7" title="Looking back up the Glen - Beinn Mheadoin at the back"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-011/chaorainn-9.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Looking back up the Glen - Beinn Mheadoin at the back"></a></p>
<figcaption>Looking back up the Glen - Beinn Mheadoin at the back</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Back at Linn of Dee at exactly 1530, and then the 1.5 hours drive back to Aberdeen. There was a huge moon and the road back to Braemar offered some lovely views of the moon between the trees and hills, together with the start of the sunsetting, my potato photo doesn’t do it justice.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="chaorainn-10.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-8" title="Big moon"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-011/chaorainn-10.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Big moon"></a></p>
<figcaption>Big moon</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Another big trip, probably the last of this year, unless there’s a December heat wave, and two infrequently visited and activated summits. It’s hard not to be biased by the weather but Beinn a’Chaorainn was my favourite today. When the clouds cleared I could see over to Beinn a’Bhuird area, down to Beinn Bhreac and big sweeping expanses of hillsides. It would’ve been nice to have been on Beinn Mheadhoin when the cloud lifted to see across to the west, and probably that would’ve been more spectacular. I’ll be revisiting them both next year, hopefully finding a day with clear blue skies! 🌞</p>
<p>Also posted on the <a href="https://reflector.sota.org.uk/t/beinn-mheadhoin-gm-es-005-and-beinn-achaorainn-gm-es-011/36785">reflector</a>.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-011/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 13:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-011/chaorainn-2.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Beinn Mheadhoin</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-005/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>The weather has been lovely up here all week - next week, however less so…</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="weather.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Mountain Forecast"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-005/weather.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Mountain Forecast"></a></p>
<figcaption>Mountain Forecast</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>So I wanted to make the most of it, and took today off. Monday or Tuesday were better days but alas I couldn’t make that happen. As you can see the forecast was meant to be lovely clear skies and maybe some cloud creeping in later. Well it was the opposite, with the best weather as I was cycling back…oh well. Here we go:</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="route.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Route for the day. Light blue section is mostly cycling."><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-005/route.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Route for the day. Light blue section is mostly cycling."></a></p>
<figcaption>Route for the day. Light blue section is mostly cycling.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Last week I did <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-001/">GM/ES-001</a> and <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-013/">GM/ES-013</a> on a big bike and hike, and today would be similar. I had debated between Cairn Toul + Braeriach and the two summits today, but everyone told me Cairn Toul circuit was too much, and save that for a summer’s day (or maybe camp in the Corrour bothy at the bottom). They’d all done the route so I should probably listen…and eventually I did. I’m glad, because it would’ve been too long, and the weather wasn’t the best - particularly the wind - and so that wouldn’t have been enjoyable.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="mheadhoin-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Crossing Lui Water"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-005/mheadhoin-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Crossing Lui Water"></a></p>
<figcaption>Crossing Lui Water</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="mheadhoin-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Bridge at Derry Lodge"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-005/mheadhoin-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Bridge at Derry Lodge"></a></p>
<figcaption>Bridge at Derry Lodge</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Starting at Linn of Dee car park, around 0830, I cycled on the nice track to Derry Lodge. Here my route would take me east following the Derry Burn up Glen Derry. This section of the track is not great for cycling on, lots of roots, rocks, narrow sections with overhanging heather. It was slow going, much slower than I planned. Once you get to the next bridge and a few 10s metres along it’s much better. Some maps show an ATV track that runs somewhat parallel to this route. I didn’t see the start of it, but wondered if it would be better. Near the bridge you see it, and I did try it on the way back but it was very boggy, muddy and wet, and quick to disappear, so I just stuck to what I knew. The return run is less bad, as at least you’re generally going downhill.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="hardcycle.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="This is not the path to cycle"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-005/hardcycle.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="This is not the path to cycle"></a></p>
<figcaption>This is not the path to cycle</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="mheadhoin-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="Looking up Derry Glen to the summits"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-005/mheadhoin-4.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Looking up Derry Glen to the summits"></a></p>
<figcaption>Looking up Derry Glen to the summits</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The cycling continues along the track, and once you pass the final wooded area it starts to become rocky and difficult again. I started pushing my bike through the bad sections but they just became more and more, and it wouldn’t save time as I’d have to push it on the way back. So I dumped the bike in the heather and continued up to the Y junction.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bikedrop.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7" title="Bike left here"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-005/bikedrop.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Bike left here"></a></p>
<figcaption>Bike left here</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>It was about 09:40, so 1-1:10 of cycling. My route was left at the Y, following the Coire Etchachan burn, past Hutchison Memorial hut and to the shores of little loch Etchachan.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="mheadhoin-5.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-8" title="Footbridge over Coire Etchachan burn"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-005/mheadhoin-5.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Footbridge over Coire Etchachan burn"></a></p>
<figcaption>Footbridge over Coire Etchachan burn</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="mheadhoin-6.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-9" title="Up to the loch, bothy on the left"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-005/mheadhoin-6.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Up to the loch, bothy on the left"></a></p>
<figcaption>Up to the loch, bothy on the left</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I had a peak inside the bothy and looked through the visitors book. Always interesting the little odds and ends people have left for others. Actually my first time in a bothy, would be fun one time…as long as I remembered to bring firewood!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="mheadhoin-7.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-10" title="Bothy"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-005/mheadhoin-7.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Bothy"></a></p>
<figcaption>Bothy</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="mheadhoin-8.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-11" title="Memorial Plaque"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-005/mheadhoin-8.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Memorial Plaque"></a></p>
<figcaption>Memorial Plaque</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="mheadhoin-9.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-12" title="Inside the bothy"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-005/mheadhoin-9.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Inside the bothy"></a></p>
<figcaption>Inside the bothy</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Now the climb really started, and this brought the wind with it. It was relentless, reaching the peak at the top by the Loch.</p>
<p>I’d hoped the wind was just strong in the valley, and coming off the loch and that the summit would be better. Perhaps hoping in vain of course. The weather was not the clear skies forecast but very grey clouds, that I was about to be walking through. Not sure if it was raining or the wind just pushing huge volumes of air against me and the resultant water condensing made it seem like it was raining, but I was pretty wet all over.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="mheadhoin-10.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-13" title="Arriving at the lochs"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-005/mheadhoin-10.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Arriving at the lochs"></a></p>
<figcaption>Arriving at the lochs</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="mheadhoin-11.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-14" title="Path up to Beinn Mheadhoin"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-005/mheadhoin-11.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Path up to Beinn Mheadhoin"></a></p>
<figcaption>Path up to Beinn Mheadhoin</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Eventually a tor appeared out of the cloud and I thought I’d made it…looking at my map I realised it wasn’t and I still had some way to go. The next one appeared and I climbed up on top, but that was pushing it in the wind, and so I decided not to climb anymore. I thought the tors would shelter me from the wind but it seemed to come around from every direction and there was nowhere sheltered. I setup the mast and long wire, as I planned to start with 40m. I had the wrong guy ring for the carbon 6 and so it kept sliding all the way down, plus the peg into the wind kept lifting. I ended up putting three of the guys into the wind, plus pegging down the wire into the wind and it reached some equilibrium and held in place. It did remind me of the wacky waving inflatable arm flailing tube men.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="mheadhoin-12.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-15" title="“Enjoying it”"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-005/mheadhoin-12.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="“Enjoying it”"></a></p>
<figcaption>“Enjoying it”</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>40m wasn’t great, lots of QSB and I didn’t hang around long. Time for summit #2. Packed up and headed down into the Lairig an Laoigh. The sun was starting to peak through and once I was on the descent the wind abated. I took quite a direct route down, which was very steep and probably not the best route, although not sure where would’ve been better.</p>
<p><a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-011/">Read on for Beinn a’Chaorainn.</a></p>
<p>Also posted on the <a href="https://reflector.sota.org.uk/t/beinn-mheadhoin-gm-es-005-and-beinn-achaorainn-gm-es-011/36785">SOTA reflector.</a> Following the discussion there, it turns out my route from Derry Lodge was not the best one when cycling. In fact, not crossing the Derry Burn at the lodge and continuing on the east side until I got to the foot bridge would’ve been a better cycle path - oh well, I know for next time!</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-005/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 10:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-005/mheadhoin-9.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Ben Tirran</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-016/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>I had originally planned to do Ben Tirran, <a href="https://sotl.as/summits/GM/ES-016">GM/ES-016</a>, with Hunt Hill, <a href="https://sotl.as/summits/GM/ES-042">GM/ES-042</a>, starting from Loch Lee and going back and forth, but I had to do the school pick up so needed to be home by 3pm. For a while I still thought I could do both until I realised my time spreadsheet had an error, although it took writing an email to someone saying I was going to be on Ben Tirran at 2pm…and then home by 3pm :thinking: Anyway, I decided to just do Ben Tirran as it’s taller…(only if it were 4m taller still…)</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ben-tirran-16.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Car park and cafe"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-016/ben-tirran-16.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Car park and cafe"></a></p>
<figcaption>Car park and cafe</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Starting by Wheen farm, there’s a little area off the road where you can park, and, at some point during the year, even buy some refreshments!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ben-tirran-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="What’s on the menu"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-016/ben-tirran-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="What’s on the menu"></a></p>
<figcaption>What’s on the menu</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The cloud was low but wind was minimal, and it was mild at 10 degC. The path is straight forward from the car park, with a small stream crossing at one point.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ben-tirran-14.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Looking west down Glen Clova"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-016/ben-tirran-14.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Looking west down Glen Clova"></a></p>
<figcaption>Looking west down Glen Clova</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ben-tirran-13.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Path ahead"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-016/ben-tirran-13.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Path ahead"></a></p>
<figcaption>Path ahead</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I did miss the turning, and then stomped across the heather to find the path. When I came back down I looked to see why I’d missed the turning…</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ben-tirran-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="Turn off here…"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-016/ben-tirran-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Turn off here…"></a></p>
<figcaption>Turn off here…</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Perhaps on a clear day it would be more obvious, and the small cairn would stand out.</p>
<p>As I reached the summit, it was getting brighter, and I had hopes of the sun breaking through. I setup on 2m with the FT65 and RH770 and called a few times. Soon enough I had five contacts, including G6BIA down by Newcastle - who I also got on Mount Battock the other week.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ben-tirran-12.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="Fog bow"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-016/ben-tirran-12.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Fog bow"></a></p>
<figcaption>Fog bow</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>A surprise one was Fraser, MM0EFI, at home, with Mount Keen right between us. At this point the clouds parted and I was in glorious sunshine.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ben-tirran-7.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7" title="Looking south"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-016/ben-tirran-7.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Looking south"></a></p>
<figcaption>Looking south</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ben-tirran-10.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-8" title="North to Mount Keen"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-016/ben-tirran-10.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="North to Mount Keen"></a></p>
<figcaption>North to Mount Keen</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ben-tirran-11.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-9" title="Trig Point"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-016/ben-tirran-11.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Trig Point"></a></p>
<figcaption>Trig Point</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Also out was Denis, MM0CBC, up on holiday from Wales. He was on <a href="https://summits.sota.org.uk/summit/GM/ES-027">GM/ES-027</a> and we had a nice summit to summit on 2m. Also impressive given the high peaks of Lochnagar, and Beinn a’Bhuird were between us.</p>
<p>Several people reported my audio kept dropping and I was difficult to hear, but the carrier was still strong. Think I’ve come to the conclusion the FT-65 mic/design isn’t that great (judging from commentary online) and even though I’m right next to it when talking, small movements cause the levels to drop. That sounded annoying for those at the other end, especially after I’d witter on for 3 minutes and they only heard every 5th word.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ben-tirran-6.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-10" title="Setup for HF"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-016/ben-tirran-6.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Setup for HF"></a></p>
<figcaption>Setup for HF</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I setup for 40m and had plenty of contacts. I’d arrived at the summit sooner than I expected, and so could afford to spend more time on the radio. I tried chasing a few other summits, although not too many active at the time, but made contact with HB9CYX and @DG4SFF. Tried a little 10m, and was rewarded with W4GO and N2BTD on the east of the US. I thought about changing from my sloper L antenna to a vertical but then realised I didn’t have enough time for that. Packing up I heard someone calling on 2m and ended up having a chat with a few others. At this point I was now behind schedule and had to get a move on! Back into the cloud and a quick trot down to the car.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ben-tirran-15.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-11" title="Back at the farm"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-016/ben-tirran-15.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Back at the farm"></a></p>
<figcaption>Back at the farm</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>A very enjoyable day out. It’s a nice summit, with good take off for 2m, some shelter at the trig, and lovely views when the cloud clears. I could see many summits peaking above the clouds - Mount Keen, Lochnagar, and even across to Ben Avon. On a cloudless day, I bet the views would be stunning all round.</p>
<p>It’s almost been two years since anyone came here, <a href="https://reflector.sota.org.uk/t/gm-es-all-88-out-of-87-uniques-activated/31625">Fraser being the last of course 2</a>. Perhaps the route from either north or south isn’t great, and there are plenty of other options closer from both sides. However, it would be one I’d recommend. I did get Tim, G5OLD, on 40m and so now he’s compelled to come up for a complete.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="qsos.jpeg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-12" title="QSOs"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-016/qsos.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="QSOs"></a></p>
<figcaption>QSOs</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Also posted on the <a href="https://reflector.sota.org.uk/t/a-sunny-summit-on-ben-tirran-gm-es-016/36735">reflector</a>.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-016/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-016/ben-tirran-8.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Ben Macdui</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-001/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Ben Macdui is Scotland’s (and the UK’s) second highest mountain at 1,309 m, only beaten by 36m by the famous Ben Nevis. My journey continues from <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-013/">Carn A’ Mhaim</a>, whereby I walked along the ridge, then down (unfortunately) to the side of Ben Macdui. I’d caught up with the lady who passed me at the previous summit, and so we ended up walking to the summit of Ben Macdui together. She was visiting from Manchester and staying a few days in Braemar. She asked lots of questions about amateur radio and seemed interested, particularly in SOTA. Once we started going back up the hill it was just boulders for as far as the eye can see - although we were once again in the cloud so not that far.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ben-macdui-22.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="The start of the ascent - lady in the foreground for scale"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-001/ben-macdui-22.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="The start of the ascent - lady in the foreground for scale"></a></p>
<figcaption>The start of the ascent - lady in the foreground for scale</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ben-macdui-21.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Last view before climbing into the clouds"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-001/ben-macdui-21.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Last view before climbing into the clouds"></a></p>
<figcaption>Last view before climbing into the clouds</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The path came and went a few times as we went up, occasionally small patches of red sandstone gravel could be spotted, and we followed that as best we could. We came to a small stream to cross and that meant we were nearing the top, and the boulders eased off. Soon enough the trig point and cairn appeared in the cloud and we’d made it!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ben-macdui-19.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Trig point"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-001/ben-macdui-19.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Trig point"></a></p>
<figcaption>Trig point</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ben-macdui-20.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Marker from 1920s"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-001/ben-macdui-20.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Marker from 1920s"></a></p>
<figcaption>Marker from 1920s</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>There were a few other people at the top, and a trickle of walkers continued for most of the time I was there. I looked around and found another sheltered cairn to setup behind. There wasn’t much wind at the top, but being in the cloud was a bit damp. Water would condense on the mast and wires and then drip down onto me (and radio if I wasn’t careful).</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ben-macdui-summit-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="Summit setup"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-001/ben-macdui-summit-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Summit setup"></a></p>
<figcaption>Summit setup</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I had hoped 2m would be good from up here, certainly during the <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-087/">145 Alive event</a>, Fraser made contacts all over Scotland and north England. However, after Fraser and calling CQ a few times it seemed no-one was listening and I went to 40m - I also knew I had a long way back to go and didn’t want to hang about too long. 40m was good, with 13 contacts, including a summit to summit with 2W0OMX on GW/SW-001 - the tallest Brecon Beacon in Wales. As I was thinking of packing up I heard a mobile station call on 2m, and had a brief chat with him. I’d been on the air for about 30 minutes and it was time to pack up and head down.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ben-macdui-18.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="Uh oh - broken tip of mast"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-001/ben-macdui-18.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Uh oh - broken tip of mast"></a></p>
<figcaption>Uh oh - broken tip of mast</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The lady (who I never asked her name) who climbed with me had gone on to do the big loop around Derry Cairngorm and back to Derry Lodge. I’d looked at that route but it would add at least 30 minutes, and I was on a schedule to get home for 5pm, so I’ll save that Munro for next year. A bit of wandering around and I found my route down, and after not very long the clouds started to part and the views improved considerably!</p>
<p><a href="ben-macdui-15.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-001/ben-macdui-15.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ben-macdui-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-8" title="Cloud over Cairn Toul"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-001/ben-macdui-3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Cloud over Cairn Toul"></a></p>
<figcaption>Cloud over Cairn Toul</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ben-macdui-12.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-9" title="Ridge walk from Carn A’ Mhaim"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-001/ben-macdui-12.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Ridge walk from Carn A’ Mhaim"></a></p>
<figcaption>Ridge walk from Carn A’ Mhaim</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ben-macdui-10.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-10" title="Route down"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-001/ben-macdui-10.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Route down"></a></p>
<figcaption>Route down</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I soon found the path in the photo above, and then it was plain sailing from there. It did get quite steep in places on the way down but manageable. The cloud had cleared more in the glen too, so looking back the mountainsides were impressive to see.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ben-macdui-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-11" title="Descent route on right, and ridge on left"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-001/ben-macdui-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Descent route on right, and ridge on left"></a></p>
<figcaption>Descent route on right, and ridge on left</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>My route back to my bike made me realise I didn’t want to leave my bike right by the bridge as now I had to go down to get it. Going down was easy enough but then getting my bike back was a pain. I decided to carry my bike back up to the top path but this was a mistake as the path was narrow, rocky and difficult to cycle. I should’ve kept it to the middle path. If I do this route again, I might even leave the bike at the start of the trees and just walk. It would mean crossing the burn at the ford, and risk getting wet at the start of the journey!</p>
<p>Back on the reasonable path towards Derry Lodge, navigating the bog and mud again before crossing the bridge - that’s slightly too narrow to easily push my bike over! I was washing the mud off my wheels in the stream when the lady I’d met earlier was crossing the bridge! Seems like my estimate of 30 minutes extra for the Derry Cairngorm route was about right as that’s how long I was on the radio for, so good to know for next time.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ben-macdui-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-12" title="Route down from Sron Riach"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-001/ben-macdui-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Route down from Sron Riach"></a></p>
<figcaption>Route down from Sron Riach</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The cycle from Derry Lodge back to Linn of Dee car park is very easy, although I’d not be wanting to walk all that way! I was back home by 5pm, just in time to take the boys for their haircuts!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="route.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-13" title="Route I took - 30km round trip and over 1,200m of cumulative ascent."><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-001/route.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Route I took - 30km round trip and over 1,200m of cumulative ascent."></a></p>
<figcaption>Route I took - 30km round trip and over 1,200m of cumulative ascent.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-001/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2024 13:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-001/ben-macdui-20.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Carn a’Mhaim</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-013/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>After the lovely weekend’s weather, I was watching the forecast and today’s was looking good, so I decided to take the day off work and go for a big trip in the Cairngorms. Unfortunately, by the time it got to today, the weather wasn’t quite as nice as originally forecast. It was mild though, 12 degC at the Linn of Dee when I set off in the morning.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="mhaim-13.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Cycle through the forest"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-013/mhaim-13.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Cycle through the forest"></a></p>
<figcaption>Cycle through the forest</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="mhaim-12.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Path to Derry Lodge, Carn a Mhaim in the clouds at the back"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-013/mhaim-12.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Path to Derry Lodge, Carn a Mhaim in the clouds at the back"></a></p>
<figcaption>Path to Derry Lodge, Carn a Mhaim in the clouds at the back</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I started at Linn of Dee, and cycled along the nice track to Derry Lodge, a now boarded up hunting lodge. It’s common for people to leave their bikes here as the paths beyond aren’t quite as nice, or people are doing the big loop around Derry Cairngorm, Ben Macdui and back, and this is where all the paths return to. My route today did have a loop but not as big, and I continued to cycle on to Luibeg burn.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="mhaim-9.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Derry Lodge Bridge"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-013/mhaim-9.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Derry Lodge Bridge"></a></p>
<figcaption>Derry Lodge Bridge</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>After crossing the bridge, the ground soon beomes very muddy and boggy, with the bike wheels disappearing half way into the mud. It was hard work finding a path across, but once that was done the track was reasonable again. There were some surface drains across the path but they were wide and easy to cycle over, but as I neared Luibed these became more rocky and less navigable whilst cycling. I reached Luibeg and wanted to leave my bike near the bridge, as this would be where I’d be coming on the way back.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="luibeg.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Luibeg Bridge - I was approaching from the right and heading to the left on this map"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-013/luibeg.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Luibeg Bridge - I was approaching from the right and heading to the left on this map"></a></p>
<figcaption>Luibeg Bridge - I was approaching from the right and heading to the left on this map</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>There are actually three routes from east to west from when you meet the trees at Luibeg. I’d planned to take the upper route, ended up on the lower route, and found that the middle one would’ve been best! I ended up trying to get my bike through the woods on a tiny track, with rocks and roots and all sorts. It was not easy, but I eventually made it to the bridge. I left my bike there, crossed the bridge and walked down to rejoin the path before taking the northern split to ascent Carn a Mhaim. As I was walking up I realised I’d lost my LoRa tracker somewhere in those woods. It was on the top of my bag and the trees must’ve knocked it off. 😢 It wasn’t on as there are no igates nearby and I’m in the valley, so it’s not like I can even track the tracker!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="mhaim-8.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="Luibeg Bridge - the alternative to fording the burn"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-013/mhaim-8.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Luibeg Bridge - the alternative to fording the burn"></a></p>
<figcaption>Luibeg Bridge - the alternative to fording the burn</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="mhaim-10.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="Looking back the way I came along Glen Lui"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-013/mhaim-10.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Looking back the way I came along Glen Lui"></a></p>
<figcaption>Looking back the way I came along Glen Lui</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>As I climbed I entered the cloud and the lovely views all disappeared. The walk up was steep but straightforward.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="mhaim-5.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7" title="In the cloud"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-013/mhaim-5.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="In the cloud"></a></p>
<figcaption>In the cloud</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Then out of the mist the summit cairn appeared and I setup for my first activation of the day. I’d hoped to qualify the summit on 2m, so I could get moving, but being mid-week I wasn’t hopeful. I did get three 2m QSOs fairly quickly, and then set up the quick 5.5m vertical for 20m. Contacts came in quick with that and then I thought I heard Bill, GM0NRT, call on 20m but I think it was on the HT still and then in my confusion the chasers stopped. However, I had enough contacts so just packed up. As I was doing so, Denis, MM0CBC, was out on a summit further west near Aviemore and he’d just reached the top. We had a tricky QSO as Bill thought I was speaking to him still on 2m, he struggled to hear me but heard me asking Denis to QSY, again thinking it was me asking Bill to QSY! Denis couldn’t hear Bill so it was probably confusing for him too but we made it in the end. As I was chatting with Denis, a lady came by to the summit. She was curious as to what I was doing and we had a brief chat. She then left and continued up to Ben Macdui. I packed up and started towards it myself.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="mhaim-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-8" title="At the summit"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-013/mhaim-3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="At the summit"></a></p>
<figcaption>At the summit</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="mhaim-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-9" title="Station setup"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-013/mhaim-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Station setup"></a></p>
<figcaption>Station setup</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The path that continues towards Ben Macdui follows the ridge between the two glens until it gets to the side of the mountain. This is quite a narrow ridge, but thankfully the wind was gentle. The clouds did start to part and I had a few glimpses down into Lairig Ghru, including Corrour bothy at the foot of Cairn Toul and Devil’s Point climb.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="mhaim-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-10" title="Corrour Bothy"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-013/mhaim-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Corrour Bothy"></a></p>
<figcaption>Corrour Bothy</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="mhaim-6.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-11" title="Ridge to Ben Macdui"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-013/mhaim-6.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Ridge to Ben Macdui"></a></p>
<figcaption>Ridge to Ben Macdui</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Then on to <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-001/">Ben Macdui</a>!</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-013/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2024 10:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-013/mhaim-6.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Geallaig Hill</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-036/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>My auntie was visiting for the weekend and she’s a keen hill walker, so of course we had to go out! I picked Gaellaig Hill as it’s not too long, and close to Ballater for a nice lunch afterwards and then still home in time to do school pick up.</p>
<p>Whilst yesterday the weather was lovely, and the forecast looked great over the weekend, today was much greyer and wetter. Thankfully it had stopped raining by the time we reached the start, and even a little blue sky appeared.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="geallaig-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Looking back down the hill"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-036/geallaig-3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Looking back down the hill"></a></p>
<figcaption>Looking back down the hill</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The walk up was straight forward, following the track right to the summit. I forgot to take any photos of the summit, but there’s a nice cairn you have to climb into with the trig point, and you’re very well protected from any wind. The rain less so, for obvious reasons.</p>
<p>Whilst the radio is somewhat of a novelty for her, I didn’t think that would last long. Fraser, MM0EFI, knew I was going up and we had a quick QSO on 2m, but then I jumped straight to 20m on HF. It was quite a considerable pile up and I really struggled to make anyone out. There was some QRM, tuning, tones that kept sounding too which made it harder. Probably if I had headphones on I would’ve done better but I at least wanted auntie to be able to hear.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="qsos.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="QSOs"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-036/qsos.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="QSOs"></a></p>
<figcaption>QSOs</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Had a few England and Welsh stations come back who were booming signals, and cut through the pile up! Quite the short skip on 20m. Managed three summit-to-summits in England, Italy and Germany too.</p>
<p>After about 30 minutes, it was time to pack up and head back down…and warm up again! We went into Ballater - the first time I’ve actually been there! - had lunch at The Bothy and had a look around a few shops. Some classic granny shops on the high street!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="geallaig-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Smile!"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-036/geallaig-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Smile!"></a></p>
<figcaption>Smile!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-036/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-036/geallaig-3.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Mount Battock</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-032/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>This is the most the most easterly Corbett, which make it the most easterly mountain in Scotland. The weather was absolutely lovely, although the forecast for the summit was high winds.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="battock-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Clachnaben view from the start"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-032/battock-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Clachnaben view from the start"></a></p>
<figcaption>Clachnaben view from the start</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The route was a long cycle, around 1:30, including pushing it up much of the steep parts to have a quick journey home. The path is very well made up the whole way, but you just have to watch you take the right turns at a few locations.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="battock-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Was it left or right?"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-032/battock-3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Was it left or right?"></a></p>
<figcaption>Was it left or right?</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p><a href="battock-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-032/battock-4.jpg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p>I dropped my bike at the turn off to the summit. As I approached the summit the wind was picking up considerably, I could also smell and see a lot of smoke in the air. Seemed to be some fires to the south, but at times the wind would blow great clouds of it towards me and it were as if I was right to a bonfire.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="battock-8.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Fires"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-032/battock-8.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Fires"></a></p>
<figcaption>Fires</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="battock-7.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="Looking north with view of path from the summit"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-032/battock-7.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Looking north with view of path from the summit"></a></p>
<figcaption>Looking north with view of path from the summit</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>This is a good summit for 2m, I think Fraser has done a 145 Alive event from here, and from looking at past logs on <a href="https://sotl.as/summits/GM/ES-032">sotlas</a>, so I was hoping for a quick activation on 2m. It wasn’t quite as quick as I’d hoped, but also turned out my spot didn’t really work properly, and showed as Test, due to the changes to the SOTA API and SOTAGoat not being updated.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="battock-9.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="At the top, in the wind!"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-032/battock-9.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="At the top, in the wind!"></a></p>
<figcaption>At the top, in the wind!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>However, my first CQ, with just the RH-770 telescopic antenna on, was immediately replied by G6BIA from South Shields, outside Newcastle, at 235 km/146 miles away! Great signal! It took another 30 minutes to get the 3 more needed to qualify and then one more from Hibby, MM0RFN, who met Fraser, MM0EFI, for lunch in Westhill.</p>
<p><a href="qsos.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-032/qsos.png" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p>Some good shelter on the summit - thank goodness - but also lots of fences and posts for future antenna mounting options! A good summit to spend the day if the weather co-operates.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="battock-10.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-8" title="Slim G in the air"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-032/battock-10.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Slim G in the air"></a></p>
<figcaption>Slim G in the air</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Descent was quick, thanks to pushing the bike up so much of the ascent. Some parts were a bit hairy - steep, loose gravel and gusty winds, but once I was a little lower it was some nice free wheeling much of the way. It’s also a nice close summit, only being about 30 minutes drive from my house.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="battock-6.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-9" title="More views from the top"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-032/battock-6.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="More views from the top"></a></p>
<figcaption>More views from the top</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-032/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-032/battock-10.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Fourman Hill</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-083/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="fourman-6.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Looking NE"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-083/fourman-6.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Looking NE"></a></p>
<figcaption>Looking NE</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The kids have been enjoying the <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-077/">previous</a> <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-087/">adventures</a> we’ve gone on, and wanted to go out again. Tim, GM5OLD, was going to be going up Sgor Mor but had hurt his knee on the descent of Morven, so called it off. I’d originally planned to go up Craigendarroch, as that’s likely to be in reach, via 2m, of Sgor Mor, but as we weren’t constrained by that anymore, I decided Fourman Hill would be a good summit. It’s quite a low summit and the route up is short, around 1.3 km with 115m of elevation change. Makes for a nice pleasant walk, also when you’re carrying a tent, lunch for four and various things the kids want, you appreciate the short trip! If I was on my own, it would’ve only taken 20 minutes to get to the top.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="fourman-5.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Looking south"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-083/fourman-5.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Looking south"></a></p>
<figcaption>Looking south</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Perhaps I should’ve done it that day I did <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-071/">three 1-pointers</a> in the area - then I could’ve used Mike’s, 2M0WNA, joke about being a four hill man.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="fourman-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Following the leader"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-083/fourman-4.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Following the leader"></a></p>
<figcaption>Following the leader</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Weather was good today, nearly clear blue skies, although some wind, particularly on the summit. The walk up is mostly sheltered by trees but when you near the top these are sparse and we were getting blown about quite a bit. The trig point is in the middle of some gorse and there’s not much space around it. We found a nearby tree in the heather to setup camp.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="fourman-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Tent and station"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-083/fourman-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Tent and station"></a></p>
<figcaption>Tent and station</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The kids kept out of the wind in the tent and had their lunch in there. I setup just behind a tree and used another to tie off the random wire in more of an inverter L shape rather than the usual inverted sloper L. I also had the slim G on the mast for 2m. Fraser, MM0EFI, was first in the log on 60m. I thought others would come but after about 10-15 minutes of calling, no-one else appeared so I moved to 40m. Whilst the CQ Worldwide DX Contest was going on, there was still space on the band and I worked 5 stations - including Tim, GM5OLD, from his camper van across at Glenshee.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="gm5old.jpeg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="GM5OLD Station"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-083/gm5old.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="GM5OLD Station"></a></p>
<figcaption>GM5OLD Station</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>As the contest was on, I thought I’d make the most of it and see what DX I could work. I moved to 10m and the band was chock-a-block! I started with a few European and Russian contacts, and they were easy to work. Everyone just gives you a 59 in a contest so not sure what my signal really was but when they come back after my first call and get my callsign correct, it must be a pretty decent signal. I saw Barbados, 8P5A, on the cluster, so thought I’d give them a try. It took a few attempts but eventually managed to get through! My first transatlantic SOTA QSO!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="qsos.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="QSOs - Green is 10m"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-083/qsos.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="QSOs - Green is 10m"></a></p>
<figcaption>QSOs - Green is 10m</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I switched the antenna to the 5.5m random vertical and started at 29.000 MHz and worked down. Lots of US stations at this end of the band and pretty much each one I tried, came back straight away. I heard many stations worldwide, Canada, Aruba, China, Brazil, Saudi Arabia, but didn’t manage to work them. It’s always a trade off of how long do you keep calling them before you decide they can’t hear you due to propagation vs.&nbsp;being drowned out by bigger stations. Plus the kids had had enough by this point and wanted to move on.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="fourman-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7" title="Heading back down"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-083/fourman-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Heading back down"></a></p>
<figcaption>Heading back down</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I did join the lunchtime net and made a couple of local contacts on 2m, I didn’t spot on 2m or try calling, as I wanted to spend the time on 10m instead. We were back to the car in 20 minutes and nearly everyone fell asleep on the way home! A friend at work asked me about good walks for kids, and thanks to SOTA. I now have a long list of nice walks to recommend!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="fourman-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-8" title="Cheese!"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-083/fourman-3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Cheese!"></a></p>
<figcaption>Cheese!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>And I’m in another of Fraser’s videos… 😅</p>
<iframe width="515" height="915" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/GEsa10V0FQM" title="60m NVIS #QRP #SOTA chase on a contest day. #hamradio #portableradio #ssb #60m" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen="">
</iframe>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-083/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 26 Oct 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-083/qsos.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="88" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Brown Cow Hill</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-023/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Tim, GM5OLD, is up in the area and doing a few summits. I took the opportunity (with kind support from the family…for the morning at least!) to be out at the same time for some S2S action. Tim was going up both Mona Gowan and Morven today, and so I picked a 4-pointer nearby - the very Scottish sounding, Brown Cow Hill.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="brown-cow-14.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Corgarff Castle"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-023/brown-cow-14.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Corgarff Castle"></a></p>
<figcaption>Corgarff Castle</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The route starts in the car park for Corgarff castle and takes a nice track up the hill. Weather was okay, some low cloud and the possibility of rain in the afternoon. Our rendezvous time was around 10-10:30am. After my previous epic journey up two high peaks, this felt like a walk in the park. There was almost no wind and that alone made it enjoyable.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="brown-cow-12.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Watchers"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-023/brown-cow-12.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Watchers"></a></p>
<figcaption>Watchers</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I soon entered the cloud and visibility dropped considerably. This was fine whilst I was following the track but after a while it mostly disappears into the heather…and peat hags.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="brown-cow-13.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Mist"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-023/brown-cow-13.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Mist"></a></p>
<figcaption>Mist</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="brown-cow-11.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Peat hags"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-023/brown-cow-11.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Peat hags"></a></p>
<figcaption>Peat hags</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="brown-cow-10.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="and more peat hags"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-023/brown-cow-10.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="and more peat hags"></a></p>
<figcaption>and more peat hags</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>There must’ve been some serious water coming down as the channels carved by it were huge, I had to make quite a few detours to find crossable areas without having to scramble down a muddy cliff face. It was wet and boggy underfoot, and I had plenty of full foot submersions.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="brown-cow-6.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="New fence"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-023/brown-cow-6.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="New fence"></a></p>
<figcaption>New fence</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Near the top, I emerged from the cloud and could enjoy some of the scenery again. A very new looking fence seemed to cross across the path but luckily a gate was nearby, so I didn’t have to clamber over it. Being out of the mist, I was rewarded with some lovely views across to nearby summits, including <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-006/">Ben Avon</a> I recently did. There wasn’t any snow at the top of them any more, they were out of the cloud and probably enjoyed the minimal wind as I was. Today would’ve been a much better day to climb them! If I did have the whole day, it would’ve been good to try Ben Macdui or some of the other high peaks too.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="brown-cow-7.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7" title="Culardoch to the south"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-023/brown-cow-7.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Culardoch to the south"></a></p>
<figcaption>Culardoch to the south</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="brown-cow-8.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-8" title="A sunny summit - not sure which, Morrone?"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-023/brown-cow-8.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A sunny summit - not sure which, Morrone?"></a></p>
<figcaption>A sunny summit - not sure which, Morrone?</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="brown-cow-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-9" title="Ben Avon and Beinn a’Bhuird (perhaps South Top)"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-023/brown-cow-4.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Ben Avon and Beinn a’Bhuird (perhaps South Top)"></a></p>
<figcaption>Ben Avon and Beinn a’Bhuird (perhaps South Top)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I reached the summit about 10am and setup my mast with the slim G and sloper L random wire antenna. The complete lack of wind was so enjoyable, although I still managed not to fully extend the mast and it collapsed on me! I knew Tim was nearly at the top too, so once setup I just listened to the bands and had something to eat. Unfortunately, just at the moment the cloud came in and the lovely views disappeared - oh well!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="summit.jpeg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-10" title="Not much of a cairn"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-023/summit.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Not much of a cairn"></a></p>
<figcaption>Not much of a cairn</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="brown-cow-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-11" title="Station setup"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-023/brown-cow-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Station setup"></a></p>
<figcaption>Station setup</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I brought the G90 and 4Ah LiFePO4 battery today. I like the G90, it’s a bit heavier than the KX2, but as my first radio, I have a soft spot for it. It’s pretty capable, especially given the price, and 20W and a tuner than can match the 5.5m vertical random wire on 40m is pretty sweet. 20W over 10W probably makes no discernible difference, but I do like the little waterfall for finding quiet spots on the band. If I’m going on a long walk, and multiple summits, I’d probably stick with the KX2. If the weather is bad, I’d lean more to the KX2 also, as its form factor makes it easier to keep hidden from the rain in my shadow or a plastic bag. However, on a short walk, and nice weather, I’d probably take the G90, or if I just want a change.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="qsos.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-12" title="QSOs"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-023/qsos.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="QSOs"></a></p>
<figcaption>QSOs</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I had some nice QSOs with Tim, GM5OLD, Fraser, MM0EFI, and Chris, 2M0RVZ, on 2m. I could hear Bill, GM0NRT, in Aberdeen about a 31, but he couldn’t hear me. Tim had Bill as a 59, but it seemed Mona Gowan/Morven were enough to block my signal. Tim and I had a nice chat for a while, on 145.500, but there’s no-one around here so it doesn’t matter 😅, and then we both went to HF. Plenty of contacts on 40m, in England, Ireland and into Europe. I hunted a few summit to summits, with a pair in Italy and one in Norway. I moved up to 10m, a band I’ve not tried much, usually as I’m in a rush and once the summit is qualified I’m off, and got several more stations in Europe and a couple into “Africa”, the Canary Islands, receiving 55 and 59 from them.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="brown-cow-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-13" title="Views to the north"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-023/brown-cow-3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Views to the north"></a></p>
<figcaption>Views to the north</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I was meant to be home by 1pm but I was having a blast on the air, and the weather was pleasant, so I ended up staying at the summit for much longer than I planned. However, I did have to get back, so I packed up and headed down. I tried walking a straight route from crossing the fence back to the main track, but managed to wind all over the place. There did seem to be fewer peat hags on the way back, although the few that there were, they were a lot steeper. I also managed to miss the turning on the track back to the castle and looked up to find the castle much higher than me, so then scrambled up the side of the slope to get back on the proper track. At this point it started to rain a little but I was nearly back to the car.</p>
<p>I’m only the 8th person to activate Brown Cow Hill. It’s clearly not a popular summit, and likely one for just those looking to complete GM/ES or other lists. There are plenty of other ones nearby that are more appealing. However, if the weather is clear, you get some stunning views all around, and the walk up isn’t that bad - around 6.6 km and 425m ascent, with minimal ups and downs - just the peat hags to deal with but other summits have those too. I still stand by that Morven is the worst summit for brutality of ascent!</p>
<p>Here’s Fraser at the other end of our 2m QSO.</p>
<iframe width="515" height="915" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/r1TF48JEdYU" title="Two #SOTA in 20 secs. #Yaesu VX-7r #portableradio #hamradio" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen="">
</iframe>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-023/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-023/brown-cow-14.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Beinn a’Bhuird - North Top</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-004/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>After activating <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-006/">Ben Avon</a>, and a brief stop for some food, it was time to head back to The Sneck and then up to Beinn a’Bhuird.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhuird-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="A barren landscape"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-004/bhuird-3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A barren landscape"></a></p>
<figcaption>A barren landscape</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhuird-6.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="How is it still standing in this wind?"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-004/bhuird-6.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="How is it still standing in this wind?"></a></p>
<figcaption>How is it still standing in this wind?</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The frozen burns were interesting, some I could walk over, and some were only partially frozen. The small waterfalls would trap air underneath and then the bubbles would travel under the ice for a few meters before escaping.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhuird-7.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Frozen burns"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-004/bhuird-7.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Frozen burns"></a></p>
<figcaption>Frozen burns</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The summit was hard to find, my GPS route had come to an end but I couldn’t see anything. Some general blind amberling around eventually found it hidden in the cloud. I was a bit disappointed in the cairn, I was hoping I could at least hide in it, and even when crouched down behind it, the wind still got me.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhuird-8.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="At the summit!"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-004/bhuird-8.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="At the summit!"></a></p>
<figcaption>At the summit!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I then proceeded to spend ages messing about, trying to get setup on HF, but nothing would stay still. The wind pulled out guys and pegs, it bent the top of mast over 90° and so wires would come off, I angled the mast 35° off the ground into the wind, and the top still bent over enough for the wire to be pulled off. I held the mast with my body weight but still the wind could pick me up with only the surface area of the mast! Just when I had everything set for 40m it all blew down :sweat_smile: I thought I’d try 2m but that was just as challenging. I could hear the local lunch time net in Aberdeen but it was hard to get a word in edgeways and I’m not sure they could hear me anyway. So back to HF it was, this time with a short 5.5m vertical random wire for 20m. This I did manage to make some contacts with but, again, the wind blew me and the mast over mid-way through a QSO. By this time I was fed up, cold and wet, but had qualified the summit, so it was time to go! Also, there was no signal just behind the cairn…to add to the fun.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhuird-5.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="Which way was it?"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-004/bhuird-5.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Which way was it?"></a></p>
<figcaption>Which way was it?</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I generally took the same route back, without a compass, or device with a compass, it would be impossible to know which way to go. At one point on the way back it was so windy I could lean into the wind and it would hold me up! But I was soon back at The Sneck and heading down, and it wasn’t long before the conditions were more pleasant again. The weather wasn’t quite so nice down in the valley on the way back, but much nicer than on the summits. Found my bike, generally took the same route back, and was pleased to arrive back at the car to drive home.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="bhuird-1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="Back down and out of the clouds"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-004/bhuird-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Back down and out of the clouds"></a></p>
<figcaption>Back down and out of the clouds</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>A big day out for me, 38 km or so round trip…and did I mention it was windy? 🍃</p>
<p>Also on the <a href="https://reflector.sota.org.uk/t/a-very-windy-ben-avon-gm-es-006-and-beinn-abhuird-gm-es-004/36517">SOTA reflector</a>.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-004/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 13:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-004/bhuird-7.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Ben Avon</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Johnstone</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-006/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>After a lovely&nbsp;<a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-008/">Lochnagar trip</a> the other week (with the now amusing subtitle of windy munro), I was keen to do some more high summits before the weather got worse and the darkness set in. Although turns out the weather is already worse! It’s school holidays here, so with no family schedule constraints, I could go out for the whole day, and I decided to try these two big uns - Ben Avon and Beinn A’Bhuird, pronounced Ben Ann and Ben a Vour respectively.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="route.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Journey there and back"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-006/route.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Journey there and back"></a></p>
<figcaption>Journey there and back</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The route is pretty standard for these two, parking at Keiloch, paying the £3.50, then cycling, before hiking. I decided to bike as far as I could towards The Sneck (the T junction between the two summits at 986m), and just retrace my steps from Beinn a’Bhuird back. This is instead of doing the loop where you walk from Beinn a’Bhuird North Top (the full summit name) to South Top across the plateau, then down the side and meet the path again after crossing Quoich Water. As I could see the low cloud I thought I’d rather not be walking that route for the first time, and just retrace my steps. Although given my “retracing” aka wildly veering route, and the completely indistinguishable terrain, it probably didn’t matter. It also meant more cycling on the way in, which helped my timing, for a chance of a good summit to summit with Fraser, MM0EFI, on Mull.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ben-avon-5.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Into the Valley"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-006/ben-avon-5.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Into the Valley"></a></p>
<figcaption>Into the Valley</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The route in has a few parallel paths, including the Fairy Glen, and I’m not sure I took the best ones, and had to push the bike up some steep rocky parts in places. I tried the other way on the way back and it wasn’t much better, and then I missed the turn and went through the Fairy Glen - although didn’t see the secret howff (a hidden bothy), but also didn’t look very hard as I wanted to get back.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ben-avon-2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Looking back along Gleann an t-slugain route"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-006/ben-avon-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Looking back along Gleann an t-slugain route"></a></p>
<figcaption>Looking back along Gleann an t-slugain route</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ben-avon-3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Low route from fairy glen"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-006/ben-avon-3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Low route from fairy glen"></a></p>
<figcaption>Low route from fairy glen</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ben-avon-4.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="Some snow on Carn Faiclach"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-006/ben-avon-4.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Some snow on Carn Faiclach"></a></p>
<figcaption>Some snow on Carn Faiclach</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ben-avon-7.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="Path up to The Sneck"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-006/ben-avon-7.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Path up to The Sneck"></a></p>
<figcaption>Path up to The Sneck</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ben-avon-9.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-7" title="Lots of waterfalls"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-006/ben-avon-9.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Lots of waterfalls"></a></p>
<figcaption>Lots of waterfalls</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The weather was reasonable in the morning, patches of sun between the clouds and fairly mild for 8am. The forecast had the summits in cloud with strong winds, 30-40 mph with gusts of 50 mph. However, until I got to The Sneck, there was minimal wind, but boy, once I did! 🌬️ It was absolutely relentless, with my hood acting like a reed in a trumpet with an enthusiastic player. I gave the edge a wide berth, not trusting myself if there was a sudden gust that I wasn’t braced for. Snow was minimal on the way to the Ben Avon summit, with just small pockets that resisted being blown away.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ben-avon-11.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-8" title="A bleak route to the summit"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-006/ben-avon-11.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A bleak route to the summit"></a></p>
<figcaption>A bleak route to the summit</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Out of the mist the tor emerges and I have arrived! Peaking through the rock formation - which acted like the mouth piece of the trumpet - revealed more snow on that side.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ben-avon-12.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-9" title="Snow on the east side of the tor"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-006/ben-avon-12.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Snow on the east side of the tor"></a></p>
<figcaption>Snow on the east side of the tor</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I found a nice rock to hide behind and setup the slim G on the carbon mast. My last activation on <a href="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-cs-030/">Carn a’Gheoidh</a>, suffered a lot from the mast bending too much in the wind and the antenna sliding off. Up until this point, I’d forgotten about this and so hadn’t prepared anything else. Luckily the slight sheltering seem to keep the antenna on and I managed to make my QSOs. The most exciting was a summit to summit with Fraser, MM0EFI, who’s on Mull and was up <a href="https://sotl.as/summits/GM/SI-016">GM/SI-016</a>, 100 miles away. We were both on HTs and slim G antenna!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="s2s.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-10" title="160km summit to summit on 2m FM"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-006/s2s.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="160km summit to summit on 2m FM"></a></p>
<figcaption>160km summit to summit on 2m FM</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Off to the next summit! The walk was barren, non-identifiable and had much more snow, oh, plus the wind continued.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ben-avon-14.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-11" title="Selfie at the top"><img src="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-006/ben-avon-14.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Selfie at the top"></a></p>
<figcaption>Selfie at the top</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sota</category>
  <guid>https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-006/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 10:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gm5alx.uk/sota/2024/gm-es-006/ben-avon-5.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
